Hi again.
What we&#39;re going to do now, is we&#39;re going to have a look at
R. Doing data analysis, these days, definitely requires a
very good computing environment.
And there&#39;s lots around.
But from my point of view R is probably be the best
environment these days.
R is free, as we&#39;ve mentioned before.
And it&#39;s got a vast range of capabilities.
And there it&#39;s got quite a steep learning curve, but the
more you learn, the more capable you become.
So R allows you to do all kinds of basic
operations and data.
And it&#39;s also got lots of built-in packages.
And once you learn or R, you&#39;ll discover it&#39;s also good
very beautiful graphics.
And after a while, you&#39;ll find that to start writing
functions yourself, and expanding your abilities.
So really, R, and/or tools like R are fundamental to
doing good data analysis and statistical modeling.
And so we&#39;re making this an essential part of this course.
So what I&#39;m doing here is, I&#39;m actually running R in another
free program called R-Studio.
So that&#39;s just an environment for running R and for
developing presentations in R. And it&#39;s convenient for giving
a presentation of this kind.
So we&#39;ll now go to a introductory session in
R-Studio, and I&#39;ll just show you some of the features of R.
So here we are.
You&#39;ll see I&#39;ve got a script in the R-Studio session, in
the top left panel.
And in the bottom left panel, there&#39;s the R work in session.
And what&#39;s going to happen is, I&#39;m going to click on commands
that I&#39;ve pre-entered, and that will get sent to the R
session Window and executed.
Now of course, I could have tried to do you do this live
and just type in the commands, but I don&#39;t touch type, and
that would have been painful for you and me.
So here we go.
So the first thing we&#39;ll do is just see, working with basic
vectors and matrices.
So here we assign three numbers to a vector x.
And you see the commands going down below.
And if we just type in x, it will print the vector.
And there we see the three numbers.
Now there&#39;s many ways of creating vectors.
So here&#39;s another way, making a sequence, starting from 4,
and having length 3, and in steps by 3.
So that&#39;s a kind of natural thing one would want to do.
This command, seq, is actually very useful.
And if you want to find out more about it, in R the way to
get help on functions and objects is to put a question
mark in front.
So we do question mark seek, and in R-Studio, on the right
panel, we see the panel comes up giving us all
the options for seq.
And you&#39;ll see this quite a few options in the command seq
that let you make sequences in flexible ways.
If we type y, we see the values.
And as you might have expected, we see 4, 7, and 10.
So now I&#39;ve got two vectors, x and y,
both of the same length.
And now we can do things with them.
And R does vector operations in parallel.
So if we say x plus y, even though they&#39;re both vectors,
we get the sum of those two vectors, element by element.
And likewise, other operations, like x/y means x
divide y, and it does element-wise
division of the elements.
And you can do x to the power y, and it&#39;ll do element-wise
exponentiation.
Ooh, that gave us a rather big number over there.
So that&#39;s some simple operations
for creating vectors.
What about accessing elements of a vectors?
Well, so there&#39;s a subscript convention in R
using square braces.
So x square brace 2 gives us the second element of x.
If we go x square brace 2 colon 3, that says we want the
elements of x starting from element 2 and
ending at element 3.
OK.
So it gives us the two values.
And a very convenient option in R for subsetting is to put
negative signs in subscripts.
So x minus 2 means remove the element 2 from x, and return
the subsetted vector.
And so there we see that&#39;s done.
And you can remove more than one element at a time.
And so here we&#39;re moving the collection of indices 1 and 2,
and they can be arbitrary collection of indices.
And that just gives us a vector of length 1.
Something to note, there&#39;s no scalars in R.
Everything&#39;s a vector.
So a scalar is just a vector of length 1.
OK.
So those are vectors.
The next higher up object we&#39;re
interested in are matrices.
So matrices, and as a case of another array, you can high
dimensional arrays, as well, in R. A matrix
is a two-way array.
And here&#39;s a simple way of making a matrix.
So here we&#39;ve got z is equal to a matrix.
And we give it the numbers 1 to 12.
So the first argument are the actual numbers in the matrix.
And then we give it the dimensions 4 and 3.
So we want to make a 4 by 3 matrix.
And there it is.
And so you see it&#39;s taken the numbers in column order, which
is a convention in R. And so now, just like with vectors,
we can subset elements of a matrix.
So here we want to see the third and fourth row, and the
second and third column.
And there we go.
And if just put a comma and ignore the first index, you&#39;ll
just get the columns.
So this gives us a second and third column of z.
And there is the first column of z.
Now notice what&#39;s happened.
When we took just the first column of z, that became a
vector, and it actually dropped its matrix status.
Sometimes that&#39;s convenient.
But a lot of the time, it&#39;s not, especially when your
programming and you don&#39;t want to accidentally lose the
status of a matrix.
So the matrix subsetting has an argument, drop, and here we
say, drop equals false, and it keeps that one column matrix
as a matrix, and not a vector.
So there&#39;s various functions.
You could query the dimension of a matrix.
So dim of z gives you the dimensions of the matrix.
OK.
So those are vectors and matrices.
ls is a very nice command.
It tells you what you have available in
your working directory.
And so we&#39;ve got a number of variables there.
The ones we&#39;ve just made are x, y, and z.
You can clean up your working directory.
So for example, you can use the rm command to remove y.
And there we see y is gone.
OK.
All right.
So that&#39;s making data, sort of directly.
There&#39;s other convenient ways, especially in statistics.
You can often be doing simulations to test out
routines, and to test out ideas.
And so we need a good suite of tools for generating data.
So runif is random uniform.
So this command will create 50 random uniforms on 01.
And rnorm, is random norm, random Gaussians, random
normal variables.
It will create 50 standard random normal variables.
And let&#39;s look at a plot of these variables.
And so we plot x and y.
And there we get a plot on the right.
Now I must say, R graphics is really well designed.
One doesn&#39;t think too much about the design of graphics,
but a lot goes into it, such as aspect ratios, how much
space to put around the points on a plot, between the edge of
the points and the axes.
Just things like spacing of the axes, how many
ticks, and so on.
That all seems like a trivial details, but it&#39;s not.
And this has been carefully thought of and designed.
And therefore, R graphics, I think, are particularly
attractive.
Of course, I may be a little impervious since I&#39;ve been an
R, and its predecessor S, user for many, many years.
So you could put, or you can annotate your plots.
And add all kinds of features to your plots.
So there&#39;s the same plot, but we changed the plotting
character, and we put axis labels.
And there&#39;s many, many options for making plots.
Here&#39;s an option.
And the power command allows you to set
some of these options.
Some you can do directly in the plot command, and some,
like layout commands, you can set with power.
So this is one that&#39;s often used, mf row.
It says we want to have a panel of plots with two rows
and one column.
And so that we do with the mf row command.
And so now, if we do the same plot, in our plot region,
you&#39;ll see it&#39;s a little squashed up now, because we
want two plots in this region.
And so in the second part of the region, we&#39;re going to do
a histogram of y.
And so that mf row, that division will stay in place
until you reset it with another mf row command.
And so there, we&#39;ve reset it.
OK.
So we&#39;ve created data manually.
We&#39;ve generated data using random uniform number
generators.
And we saw uniform and normal.
And there&#39;s many other distributions you
can generate from.
OK.
So now we get a read in some data that we&#39;ve got in some of
the system.
For example, Excel is often the place where
you store your data.
And so we&#39;re going to read that.
There&#39;s ways of doing this in R. So we use
the read.csv function.
And so this requires that you&#39;ve saved your data in
comma separated value from Excel.
And then you can just read it in, in R, and it respects the
rows, and columns, and the headings, and everything else.
And of course, you need to know where the data is.
In this case, I know where the data is.
If not, you&#39;ll get an error.
But, yeah, we do know where that is.
And so now we can query the data that we
have just read in.
And you can see it&#39;s got a number of columns.
And those are the names of the variables.
And we can look at the dimension of the data.
It&#39;s 397 by 9.
And we can see, what is this object that we read in?
The class of order is dataframe.
And you&#39;ll learn more about dataframes.
They&#39;re very valuable objects.
It&#39;s sort of like a matrix, except that the columns can be
variables of different kinds.
So you can have what we call factors, and continuous
variables, and matrices, and so on, which is really the way
we think of observations in statistics.
Summaries are a useful function for a dataframe.
It&#39;ll give you a summary of each of the variables in the
data frame.
And you can see it&#39;s things like min, max, and so on.
Horsepower, for example, is a categorical variable, so it
actually gives you all the values.
And the name of the automobile is also categorical.
It&#39;s an effective variable.
It gives you the values.
So dataframes and summary of dataframes is very useful.
Now you can plot the elements of a dataframe.
So a dataframe is also a list.
And a list, you get the elements of the list by giving
the name of the list, which is Auto here, and
then use dollar sign.
And then you can give the name.
So that&#39;s one way of getting the elements of a list.
And so here, we want to plot the column cylinders against
the column miles per gallon, MPG.
And so we access both of those in the same way.
And so there we have.
Here&#39;s the plot.
And so you can see that cylinders also takes on
discrete values.
And yeah, we do cylinders against miles per gallon.
So that&#39;s a little cumbersome, having to do that dollar
indexing of the elements of the dataframe.
So what you can actually do is you can attach the dataframe.
And what it does, is it creates a workspace with all
the named variables as now variables in your workspace.
So now you can access them by name.
OK.
And so if we do issue the command Search, it tells us
our various workspaces.
And there we see the global environment is where we&#39;ve put
all our vectors, like x, y, and z, and the variables we&#39;ve
created in the session.
But this dataframe that we&#39;ve attached is in the second
position here.
And it&#39;s got the variables that are in the order
dataframe available for our direct use.
And you&#39;ll see there&#39;s other things in the
Search path, as well.
And these are largely packages, at this point, whose
functions we have available.
So now we can do that plot command more directly.
And here, we&#39;ve plotted cylinders
and miles per gallon.
And in this case, it&#39;s plotted it as a box plot.
And we see, for each level of cylinders, we get a box plot
of the values for miles per gallon, which is like a little
one dimensional summary of the values at
that level of cylinder.