OK, we&#39;re going to have an R session now in RStudio.
We&#39;ve learned about some techniques for fitting linear
regression models.
And now we&#39;re going to see how we do it in R.
So you&#39;ll see I&#39;ve got a session open in RStudio with
some commands that I&#39;ve already typed in.
And I&#39;m just going to go through these with you.
And we&#39;ll see some of the features in R for fitting
regression models.
OK, here we are.
We&#39;ve got a script window over here.
And we&#39;ll send commands down to the console.
So first, we&#39;ll do library(MASS) which has some
data sets that we&#39;re going to access.
And then we&#39;ll go library(ISLR), which is our
own library with data sets used in the book.
So first of all, we&#39;ll do simple linear regression.
So one of the data sets is the Boston data.
And it&#39;s got a bunch of variables.
And if you say names of Boston, you see all the names
of the variables.
Well, they&#39;re abbreviated names.
And so if you want more detail, you&#39;re going to ask
for help on Boston.
So we do that by putting a question mark before Boston.
Boston is a data frame.
And in the right panel now, we see the help
file for the Boston.
So we see it&#39;s housing values in suburbs of Boston.
It&#39;s got 506 rows and 14 columns.
And it now tells you details about each of the variables.
So crim, for example, is per capita crime rate by town.
zn is proportion of residential land zoned for
lots over 25,000 square feet, and so on, if
you go down the list.
And these are all features about these regions in Boston.
And they are summary features that describe the
socio-economic conditions in those regions.
lstat, lower status of the population, percentage, it&#39;s a
percentage of the population in that region
that&#39;s of lower status.
And medv is median value of owner
occupied homes in $100,000.
So you can do help on data frames.
So the first thing we do is we put a linear model--
oh, I beg your pardon.
The first thing we do is plot some variables.
So we&#39;ll plot medv and lstat, the two variables we just
mentioned, and comma Boston, which tells the plot function
to find those variables in the data frame Boston.
And by using a twiddle between medv and lstat, you&#39;re
actually telling it that really the response is medv,
that&#39;s the median housing value.
It&#39;s going to put that on the vertical axis.
And so there&#39;s the plot on the right.
And sure enough, as the lower status in the region
percentage increases, the median
housing value decreases.
We&#39;ll fit a linear model now to those data.
And you&#39;ll see the formula is the same as
we used in the plot.
And we call that fit one.
And there it&#39;s fit.
And then we&#39;ll print it out.
And it gives us an intercept and a coefficient.
And sure enough, the coefficient is negative.
As you can see, there&#39;s a negative relationship.
So printing out a linear model fit gives you
a very brief summary.
And for a more detailed summary, you can
say summary of fit.
And when we do that, we get a lot more.
So we get residuals.
Some of it has got cut off here.
If you just look up, you&#39;ll see you get the call that
created the fit.
And then you get the coefficients, their standard
errors, t-values, and p-values.
And both of these are very significant.
We&#39;re typically not interested too much in the intercept.
It&#39;s the coefficient of lstat that we&#39;re interested in here.
And it&#39;s negative, and very significantly so.
And then there&#39;s some other submarine material underneath,
which we&#39;ll maybe touch on a bit later.
So notice in the formula here, we had the response on the
left-hand side.
Twiddle means is modeled as.
And then lstat is the single predictor in this case.
And then we give the name of the data frame where these
variables can be found.
So that&#39;s the standard format for fitting linear models.
And there are other options, too.
But for the moment, we won&#39;t need them.
Now, we can add that linear model fit to the plot.
And there&#39;s a function called abline in R, which is able to
pick up a linear model and just do that.
And you&#39;ll see in the right-hand plot, it was
augmented with the line that corresponds to the fit.
Now, we&#39;ve done various things with the fit.
We&#39;ve plotted it with this abline.
We&#39;ve looked at it with summary and with print by just
printing its name.
You can see what other components are on it.
Actually, it has got quite a few components.
These are largely to do with the details
of fitting the model.
And we won&#39;t trouble ourselves too much with them.
But basically, you can see the coefficients on the fit.
And that was picked up by the summary.
And then a whole lot of other things that are used rather
internally, so we won&#39;t really concern ourselves with them.
confint finds your confidence interval for the fit.
And in this case, it gives a confidence interval for the
coefficients.
And by default, it gives the lower 25% and
upper 97.5% a balance.
So this is a 95% confidence interval for each of those
coefficients.
The predict function is another one of these methods
where we can use to query a linear model fit.
In this case, we&#39;re going to predict with three new values
for lstat, or three particular values, five, 10, and 15.
And we&#39;re going to not only ask for predictions, we&#39;re
going to ask for a confidence interval.
So those are additional arguments to predict.
And when we do that, we get the fit at those three values,
and then the lower confidence interval, and the upper
confidence band.
So you can give as many values here as you like and get those
lower and upper values.
So that&#39;s simple linear regression.
Let&#39;s move on to multiple linear regression.
And now we fit a linear model, fit2, which is going to be a
linear model with lstat and age.
And we separate those with a plus in the right-hand side of
the formula.
And we can fit that and do a summary.
Well, it&#39;s much like we had before, except now we&#39;ve got
two coefficients, two standard plus intercepts, so three
altogether, with their standard errors,
t-value, and p-values.
And age is also significant, quite strongly so, but not as
significant lstat.
One of the things down below is the r squared, which we
talked about as well, for the model.
Remember, r squared, it&#39;s the higher the better.
It&#39;s a percentage of variance explained.
And it also gives you a summary of the model.
The f statistic is the f statistic that we&#39;ll obtain if
we dropped out both of the predictors in this model.
Fit3, we&#39;re going to fit a linear model
with response medv.
And it goes twiddle dot.
And what that signifies is that we&#39;re supposed to use all
the other variables in the Boston data frame except medv,
which is the response, and all the others will be predictors.
And sure enough, when we do a summary of that model, you see
there&#39;s a lot of coefficients.
And they each get their estimate, their standard
error, the t-value, and the p-value.
Most of them are significant.
Some are not.
Age, now, is no longer significant.
So age, when it was in the model just with lstat, was
significant.
But now it&#39;s in the model with all these other predictors.
And it&#39;s no longer significant.
What that means is there&#39;s basically a lot of other
predictors that are very correlated with age.
And in the presence of them, age is no longer required.
Let&#39;s do a plot.
You can plot linear models.
I made a two by two layout, because I know that four plots
get produced when you do a plot.
These are a little small here.
But we can see what&#39;s going on.
These give you various views of the linear model.
The first one is the residuals against the fitted values.
The vector fitted values is just a single vector.
So we can plot the residuals against that.
And the reason we do that is we are looking for
non-linearities.
And we kind of know there&#39;s a non-linearity in this one.
We saw that in the very first plot.
And by the curve in the residuals here, we can see
that the model is not quite capturing everything
that&#39;s going on.
There seems to be some non-linearity.
And these other plots, which are somewhat beyond the scope
of what we&#39;re doing here today, that give you aspects
of the linear model fit.
This one here, this lower left one, is the square root of the
absolute standardized residuals.
One plots this to see, perhaps, if the variance is
changing with the mean or the fit.
In this case, it looks like there may be some
relationship there.
But that could be a result of a non-linearity that we seem
to have missed in the model.
Update is a nice command.
You fit a model, fit3, and you can update it.
And in this case, we&#39;re going to update.
The formula we give is twiddle dot minus age.
Twiddle means--
nothing on the left means we&#39;re going to
use the same response.
Dot means whatever the model was in fit3.
That&#39;s replaced in dot.
And minus age means we want to remove age.
And minus indus, we want to remove indus as well.
So this will fit the model with those two variables
removed, all the others in.
And sure enough, if we do the fit, we see that those two
variables are out.
And now everything that&#39;s left in the model appears to be
significant.
OK, moving on, non-linearities and interactions.
The first thing we&#39;ll do is make a fit where we put an
interaction between lstat and age.
And that we do with a star, sort of like multiply.
But in this formula language, it means an interaction.
And we&#39;ve just got those two variables in the model.
And so when we do a summary of the fit, we see that we get a
main effect for lstat, a main effect for age, and then the
interaction, which here is represented as a colon.
So that star in the formula means that we&#39;re going to have
main effects for each and the interaction.
And the pure interaction is indicated by a colon.
And while the main effect for age is not significant here,
the interaction is somewhat significant.
The next thing we do here is we fit lstat.
And we saw that there was a non-linear looking scatter
plot between medv and lstat.
And so here we explicitly put in a quadratic term.
And there&#39;s two things going on here.
The one is we&#39;ve--
the quadratic we indicate by lstat power two.
But power has a meaning in this formula language.
And so if you want it to mean actually just raise lstat to
the power of two, we protect it with
this identity function.
So the formula language doesn&#39;t dig inside this
identity function.
So it literally puts in the square of lstat.
And the other thing that&#39;s going on here is we&#39;ve put two
commands in one line, which you can do in R. But you have
to separate them with a semi-colon.
So you can have as many commands in one line as you
like, but separate them with semi-colons.
And so both of those commands got executed now.
And sure enough, no surprise, both coefficients are strongly
significant, the linear and the quadratic.
So now we&#39;re going to plot this.
What I do now is attach Boston.
We&#39;ve seen this before.
That means that the named variables in Boston are
available in our data space.
It just makes it easier for making nice looking plots.
We go back to a single pane plot layout.
So par (mf row=c(1,1).
That means a one by one layout.
And now we&#39;ll plot our two variables.
There they are.
We&#39;ve seen that plot before.
And now we&#39;ll include the quadratic fit.
Now, we can&#39;t use abline anymore, because that only
works when you&#39;ve got a straight line fit.
Now, we need to somehow get the fitted values from our
quadratic fit and include them in the plot.
And so we do that with a points command.
And the first argument is lstat itself.
The second argument are the fitted values from fit6.
That was our quadratic fit.
So the fitted values are for each value of lstat, it&#39;s the
fitted value from the model.
So that&#39;s exactly what we want.
And that will be plotted as a series of points.
And we tell it the color should be red.
And the pch, which is the plotting
character, is to be 20.
Let&#39;s see what it does for us first.
Well, it puts the quadratic fit in the plot.
It looks like the plotting character 20 is a
little round ball.
We&#39;ll have a little look in a moment and see a bit more
about that.
Before we do that, there&#39;s an easier way of fitting
polynomials.
And that&#39;s to use a poly function in R. So here we&#39;re
going to fit medv as a polynomial of
degree four in lstat.
And we&#39;ll add that to the plot with color blue.
And you can see that the fourth degree polynomial is
getting a little bit too wiggly.
It&#39;s starting to over-fit the data a little bit, especially,
you can see in the right tail over here, it&#39;s maybe going
after these rather isolated points here.
So before we end, let&#39;s have a look at what plotting
characters are available.
So here&#39;s a simple way of seeing them all; plot one to
20 and plotting characters one to 20.
We can see the whole lot.
And there you see them.
And so you have available a whole bunch of plotting
characters, actually more than these.
And number 20 was, sure enough, this one over here.
And cx=2 means that we want to enlarge those plotting
characters by 2.
We want to double the size.
Qualitative predictors, so car seats is another
one of the data sets.
So the command fix is a way of throwing up an editor in R. So
you can actually look at the data that you&#39;re about to use.
So it will throw up a data frame and allow you to use it.
So here&#39;s the car seats data frame thrown up on the screen.
It may be a little bit small for you to use.
I just wanted to show you that.
I&#39;ll quit out of that, get back to our RStudio session.
So that&#39;s one way of seeing the data.
There&#39;s the names of car seats.
And so this was a study on children&#39;s car seats.
You can also do a summary of a data frame.
And for each variable, it tells you something about the
values in the data frame for that variable.
And you can see, for quantitative variables, it
gives you summaries like the mean, the median, and upper-
and lower-quantiles But for categorical or quantitative
variables, it actually gives you a table of
the distinct values.
So ShelveLoc is a qualitative variable in this case.
So we&#39;ll fit a model for the car seats&#39; data.
And the first call is sales twiddle dot.
It means everything in the frame but sales.
Plus we&#39;re going to add in interactions between income,
and advertising, and age, and price.
And we do that.
And sure enough, there we get the model.
And there&#39;s, again, a bunch of significant variables.
And there&#39;s those two interactions we put in.
And income and advertising appears to be strongly
significant.
But price and age is not.
ShelveLoc was a qualitative variable.
If you look at contrasts function, it shows you how R
will code that variable when it&#39;s put in a linear model.
And in this case, it&#39;s a three-level factor.
And so it puts in two dummy variables.
And the values are, if ShelveLoc is
bad, zero for both.
If it&#39;s good, the first one is one.
And the second one is zero.
If it&#39;s medium, see they&#39;re named actually good and
medium, zero and one.
And so bad is not neither good nor medium.
So that&#39;s zero on both.
So that you can actually find out how R codes
quantitative variables.
So the final thing we&#39;ll do here is see some examples of
writing R functions.
So let&#39;s write a little R function to fit a regression
model and make a plot.
So we start off by saying regplot is equal to function
of xy, open curly brace.
So that open curly brace indicates that we&#39;re going to
start giving the code in our function.
And the x and y says our function is going to take
arguments x and y.
And so the first thing we do is we&#39;re going to fit a linear
model between y and x.
Then we&#39;re going to plot xy.
And then we&#39;re going to abline the fit with color equals red.
And then close curly brace, that&#39;s
the end of our function.
OK, so that&#39;s a very simple little
function, which we&#39;ve written.
And so now, let&#39;s try it out.
We&#39;ll attach car seats.
And we&#39;ll do a regplot of price and sales.
So it takes two arguments, we&#39;ve given
it price and sales.
And you see the plot on the right, red plot silently went
off and did that and produced the plot and put in the line.
Well, let&#39;s make our function a little bit more useful.
And you can see I&#39;m defining with essentially the same
commands, but I&#39;ve added a dot dot dot in the argument.
And this is a very useful construct in R
when writing functions.
Dot dot dot means these are unnamed arguments.
But you&#39;re allowed to add extra arguments.
And they&#39;ll get passed on exactly as they supplied
wherever they are used inside the function.
And here I have passed them on to the plot function.
And what that does is it allows us to add extra
arguments to the plot function via our regplot.
And so now when we make the call, we call regplot price
and sales, and we give it x lab and y lab.
So that tells it how to annotate the labels, the axes
of the plot.
And we add some color and other information.
So regplot just called the axes x and y.
Meanwhile, our variables were price and sales.
Now, when we make the plot, you see the plot points were
colored in blue.
And the axes were labelled.
So that&#39;s a little introduction to some of the
linear model software in R. The scope is really large.
And there&#39;s many other things you can do.
But as always, with software, you&#39;ve got to start at the
beginning and get your hands dirty.
And so we&#39;ve done that a little bit here.
And I encourage you to play with this yourself and explore
the functions, use the help files, and see
how far you can get.