So that&#39;s a good segue into what do we do when we have
more than one variable.
The two models we&#39;ve considered so far just perform
logistic regression with single variables.
But of course, if we&#39;ve got a collection of variables, we
want to take them all into account.
And so, in that case, we&#39;re going to build a multi-variant
logistic regression model.
So the transformation of the probability is the same as we
had before, except now we&#39;ve got a general linear model
with an intercept and a coefficient
for each of the variables.
And if you invert that transformation, that, again,
gives you a form for the probability that&#39;s guaranteed
to be between zero and one.
Well, we can fit that using glm and r
just like we did before.
And we&#39;ll through in our variable balance as well, and
income, and the student variable.
And now, we get three coefficients, three standard
errors, three z statistics, and three p values.
And the first thing we see here is that as they were in
the single variable case, balance and student are
significant.
Income is not significant.
So it seems like two of the variables are important.
But here&#39;s something rather striking.
We know this at the coefficient for student is
negative while it was positive before.
So before, when we just measured student on its own,
it had a positive coefficient.
But when we fit it in a multivariate model, the
coefficient is negative.
Do you think this is an error, Rob?
I don&#39;t think so.
So how could that happen?
Well, remember the last time we talked about in regression
models how difficult it is to interpret coefficients in a
multiple regression model, because the correlations
between the variables can affect the signs.
So there&#39;s going to be--
we&#39;re going to see now the role of
correlations in the variables.
So here&#39;s a picture.
There we see credit card balance.
And we see the default rate the vertical axis.
And the student center of, let&#39;s see--
so students status, brown is yes and blue is no.
So students tend to have higher balances than
non-students.
So their marginal default rate is higher than for
Because we just saw that.
Balance plays a role.
But what we see in this plot on the left is that for each
level of balance, students default less than
non-students.
So when you just look at student on its own, it&#39;s
confounded with balance.
And the strong effect of balance makes it looks like
students are worse defaulters.
But this plot explains it all.
For each level of credit card balance, if we look separately
for students and non-students, students tend to have a lower
default rate.
And so that we can tease out by multiple logistic
regression, which takes these correlations into account.
Let&#39;s move on to another example with more variables.
We talked about this example in the introduction.
This is a South African heart disease data set.
Remember, South Africans eat a lot of meat.
Rob, did I ever tell you the story about the
South Africans and--
More than once.
I think Rob doesn&#39;t want to hear the story again.
Any way, they do eat a lot of meat.
So they did a study in South Africa.
It was a retrospective study.
They went and found 160 cases of white males who&#39;d had
myocardial infarction, which is a fancy
name for a heart attack.
And amongst the many people who hadn&#39;t had a heart attack,
they took a sample of 302 controls.
It&#39;s called a case control sample.
And for these people, they were all white males in the
age range 15 to 64.
And they were from this Western Cape
region of South Africa.
This was done in the early 1980s.
So in this region, the overall prevalence was very high for
heart disease, 5.1%, which is very high risk.
So in the study we have measurements on seven
predictors or, in this case, known as risk factors.
And they show in the scatter plot matrix, which I&#39;ll show
you right here.
Remember, the scatter plot matrix is a very nice way of
plotting every variable against every other variable.
And now, because it&#39;s a classification problem, we can
code into the plot the heart disease status.
And so the brown or red points here are those cases that had
heart disease.
And the blue points are the controls.
And look at the top plot, for example, if you were high in
tobacco usage and your systolic blood pressure is
high, you tend to be a brown point.
To those are the people who tended to have heart attacks.
So each of these plots shows a pairwise plot of two of the
risk factors and codes in the heart disease status.
You forgot one risk factor.
What was that?
Talking with a funny accent.
We&#39;ve all got that.
Very good, Rob.
I&#39;m doing all the hard work here.
And he&#39;s just sitting here thinking of jokes.
The coffee&#39;s good, too.
There&#39;s one funny variable here, family history.
Well, it&#39;s a categorical variable.
It turns out to be an important risk factor, apart
from being South African or not.
If you have a family history of heart
disease, the risk is high.
And you can see that it&#39;s a zero-one
variable in this case.
And you probably can see there&#39;s more browns in the
right-hand category than the left-hand category.
So in this case, we&#39;re not really trying to predict the
probability of getting heart disease.
What we&#39;re really trying to do is to understand the role of
the risk factors in the risk of heart disease.
And actually, this study was an intervention study aimed at
educating the public on healthier diets.
But that&#39;s a whole other story.
Did it work?
Um, I think it might have worked a little bit.
But this crowd is really hard to get them
away from their meat.
Do you know that they call a barbecue in South Africa?
No.
Braaivleis.
OK.
Every South African loves their braaivleis and their
bull tongue.
So here&#39;s the result of GLM for the heart disease data.
And here I actually show you some of the
code used to fit it.
We&#39;ll get into the code session later.
But it&#39;s just interesting to see that it&#39;s
pretty easy to do.
Here&#39;s a call to glm.
We tell it the response is CHD, which is the name of the
response variable.
And tilde means to be modeled as.
And dot means all the other variables in the data frame
which, in this case, is heart.
So that&#39;s a data frame that&#39;s got all the
variables in the study.
And the response here is CHD.
And we tell it the family&#39;s binomial, which just tells it
to fit the logistic regression model.
And then we fit that model.
Save it in the object called heartfit.
And then we do a summary of heartfit.
And we get printed out this summary, which is the same
summary that we&#39;ve seen before.
And so now we get coefficients for each of the variables.
In this column, we get standard errors, c
values, and p values.
And here the story is a little bit mixed.
We&#39;re not too interested in the intercept.
Tobacco usage is significant.
Low density lipoproteins, that&#39;s a cholesterol measure,
that&#39;s significant.
Remember, there&#39;s a good and bad cholesterol.
This is the bad cholesterol.
Family history, very significant.
And age is significant.
We know the risk of heart disease goes up with age.
Now, interest in the obesity and alcohol usage are not
significant here, which seems a little surprising, no?
Mm hmm.
But this is a case, again, of having correlated variables.
If we look in the previous plot, you see that there is a
lot of correlation between variables.
So age and tobacco usage are correlated.
Alcohol usage and LDL seem to be negatively correlated.
LDL is the good cholesterol.
So there&#39;s lots of correlations.
And so those are going to play a role.
And so, for example, we&#39;ve got LDL is
significant in the model.
And once LDL is in the model, perhaps alcohol usage is not
needed anymore.
Because it&#39;s been taken care of.
These variables act as surrogates for each other.