OK, we&#39;re going to talk about statistical learning and
models now.
I&#39;m going to tell you what models of good for, how we use
them, and what are some of the issues involved.
OK so we see three plots in front of us.
These are sales figures from a marketing campaign as a
function of amount spent on TV ads, radio ads,
and newspaper ads.
And you can see at least in the first two there&#39;s somewhat
of a trend.
And, in fact, we&#39;ve summarized the trend by a little linear
regression line in each.
And so we see that there&#39;s some relationship.
The first two, again, look stronger than the third.
Now, in a situation like this, we typically like to know the
joint relationship between the response sales and all three
of these together.
We want to understand how they operate together
to influence sales.
So you can think of that as wanting to model sales as a
function of TV, radio, and
newspaper all jointly together.
So how do we do that?
So before we get into the details
let&#39;s set up some notation.
So here, sales is the response, or the target, that
we wish to predict or model.
And we usually refer to it as Y. We use the letter Y to
refer to it.
TV is one of the features or inputs or predictors, and
we&#39;ll call it X1.
Likewise, radio is X2 and so on.
So in this case, we&#39;ve got three predictors, and we can
refer to them collectively by a vector as X equal to, with
three components X1, X2, and X3.
And vectors we generally think of as column vectors.
And so that&#39;s a little bit of notation.
And so now in this small compact notation, we can write
our model as Y equals function of X plus error.
OK and this error, it&#39;s just a catch all.
It captures the measurement errors maybe in Y and other
discrepancies.
Our function of X is never going to model Y perfectly.
So there&#39;s going to be a lot of things we can&#39;t capture
with the function.
And that&#39;s caught up in the error.
And, again, f of X here is now a function of this vector X
which has these three arguments, three components.
So what is the function f of X good for?
So with a good f, we can make predictions of what new points
X equals to little x.
So this notation capital X equals little x.
You know, capital X, we think as the variable, having these
three components.
And little x is an instance also with three components,
particular values for newspaper, radio, and TV.
With the model we can understand which
components of X--
in general, it&#39;ll have P components, if there&#39;s P
predictors--
are important in explaining Y, and which are irrelevant.
For example, if we model in income as a function of
demographic variables, seniority and years of
education might have a big impact on income, but marital
status typically does not.
And we&#39;d like our model to be able to tell us that.
And depending on the complexity of f, we may be
able to understand how each component Xj affects Y, in
what particular fashion it affects Y. So models have many
uses and those amongst them.
OK, well, what is this function f?
And is there an ideal f?
So in the plot, we&#39;ve got a large sample of points from a
population.
There is just a single X in this case and a response Y.
And you can see, it&#39;s a scatter plot, so we see
there&#39;s a lot of points.
There is 2,000 points here.
Let&#39;s think of this as actually the whole population
or rather as a representation of a very large population.
And so now let&#39;s think of what a good function f might be.
And let&#39;s say not just the whole function, but let&#39;s
think what value would we like f to have at say the value of
X equals 4.
So at this point over here.
We want to query f at all values of X. But we are
wondering what it should be at the value 4.
So you&#39;ll notice that at the X equals 4, there are many
values of Y. But a function can only take on one value.
The function is going to deliver back one value.
So what is a good value?
Well, one good value is to deliver back the average
values of those Y&#39;s who have X equal to 4.
And that we write in this sort of mathy notation over here
that says the function at the value 4 is the expected value
of Y given X equals 4.
And that expected value is just a fancy word for average.
It&#39;s actually a conditional average given X equals 4.
Since we can only deliver one value of the function at X
equals 4, the average seems like a good value.
And if we do that at each value of X, so at every single
value of X, we deliver back the average of the Y&#39;s that
have that value of X. Say, for example, at X equals 5, again,
we want to have the average value in this little
conditional slice here.
That will trace out this little red curve that we have.
And that&#39;s called the regression function.
So the regression function gives you the conditional
expectation of Y given X at each value of X. So that, in a
sense, is the ideal function for a population in this case
of Y and a single X.
So let&#39;s talk more about this regression function.
It&#39;s also defined for a vector X. So if X has got three
components, for example, it&#39;s going to be the conditional
expectation of Y given the three particular instances of
the three components of X. So if you think about that, let&#39;s
think of X as being two dimensional because we can
think in three dimensions.
So let&#39;s say X lies on the table, two dimensional X, and
Y stands up vertically.
So the idea is the same.
We&#39;ve got a whole continuous cloud of Y&#39;s and X&#39;s.
We go to a particular point X with two coordinates, X1 and
X2, and we say, what&#39;s a good value for the
function at that point?
Well, we&#39;re just going to go up in the slice and average
the Y&#39;s above that point.
And we&#39;ll do that at all points in the plane.
We say that&#39;s the ideal or optimal predictor of Y with
regard for the function.
And what that means is actually it&#39;s with regard to a
loss function.
What it means is that particular choice of the
function f of X will minimize the sum of squared errors.
Which we write in this fashion, again, expected value
of Y minus g of X of all functions g at each point X.
So it minimizes the average prediction errors.
Now, at each point X, we&#39;re going to make mistakes because
if we use this function to predict Y. Because there&#39;s
lots of Y&#39;s at each point X. Right?
And so the areas that we make, we call, in
this case, them epsilons.
And those are the irreducible error.
You might know the ideal function f, but, of course, it
doesn&#39;t make perfect predictions at each point X.
So it has to make some errors.
But, on average, it does well.
For any estimate f hat of X. And that&#39;s what we tend to do.
We tend to put these little hats on estimators to show
that they&#39;ve been estimated from data.
And so f hat of X is an estimate of f of X, we can
expand the squared prediction error at X into two pieces.
There&#39;s the irreducible piece which is just the variance of
the errors.
And there&#39;s the reducible piece which is the difference
between our estimate, f hat of X, and the true
function, f of X. OK.
And that&#39;s a squared component.
So this expected prediction error breaks up
into these two pieces.
So that&#39;s important to bear in mind.
So if we want to improve our model, it&#39;s this first piece,
the reducible piece that we can improve by maybe changing
the way we estimate f of X. OK, so that&#39;s all nice.
This is a kind of, up to now, has been somewhat of a
theoretical exercise.
Well, how do we estimate the function f?
So the problem is we can&#39;t carry out this recipe of
conditional expectation or conditional averaging exactly
because at any given X in our data set, we might not have
many points to average.
We might not have any points to average.
In the figure, we&#39;ve got a much smaller data set now.
And we&#39;ve still got the point X equals 4.
And if you look there, you&#39;ll see carefully that the solid
point is one point up, I put on the plot,
the solid green point.
There&#39;s actually no data points whose X
value is exactly 4.
So how can we compute the conditional
expectation or average?
Well, what we can do is relax the idea of at the point X to
at in a neighborhood of the point X. And so that&#39;s what
the notation here refers to.
N of x or script N of x is a neighborhood of points defined
in some way around the target point which is
this X equals 4 here.
And it keeps the spirit of conditional expectation.
It&#39;s close to the target point X. And if we make that
neighborhood wide enough, we&#39;ll have enough points in
the neighborhood to average.
And we&#39;ll use their average to estimate the conditional
expectation.
So this is called nearest neighbors or local averaging.
It&#39;s a very clever idea.
It&#39;s not my idea.
It has been invented long time ago.
And, of course, you&#39;ll move this neighborhood, you&#39;ll
slide this neighborhood along the x-axis.
And as you compute the averages, as you slide in
along, it&#39;ll trace out a curve.
So that&#39;s actually a very good estimate of the function f.
It&#39;s not going to be perfect because the little window, it
has a certain width.
And so as we can see, some points of the true f may be
lower and some points higher.
But on average, it does quite well.
So we had a pretty powerful tool here for estimating this
conditional expectation, just relax the definition, and
compute the nearest neighbor average.
And that gives us a fairly flexible way
of footing a function.
We&#39;ll see in the next section that this doesn&#39;t always work,
especially as the dimensions get larger.
And we&#39;ll have to have ways of dealing with it.