Welcome back.
In the last session, we talked about cross validation for the
estimation of test air for supervised learning.
Now we&#39;ll talk about a closely related
idea called the bootstrap.
It&#39;s a powerful method for assessing
uncertainty in estimates.
And particularly good for getting standard errors of an
estimate, and getting confidence limits.
It sounds like a powerful technique, Rob.
Are there any good books on the topic?
As a matter of fact--
Rob has got a very famous book with Brad
Efron on the bootstrap.
Actually, speaking of famous, my supervisor was Brad Efron,
who is now our colleague.
And he&#39;s the inventor of the bootstrap.
And there&#39;s a conversation with Brad in this course, in
which he talks about how he came to
think of the bootstrap.
The bootstrap was something he thought of in 1979, and it&#39;s
become one of the most important techniques in
statistics in the last 30 years.
So where does the name come from?
Well, it&#39;s the idea of pulling yourself up by your
bootstraps, which is from a fable by Rudolph Erich Raspe,
&quot;The Adventures of Baron Munchausen.&quot; The Baron had
fallen to the bottom of a deep lake and couldn&#39;t get out.
So he had an idea.
He thought he&#39;d pull himself up by his bootstraps, his own
bootstraps.
And in the fable, he managed to pull himself out of the
lake and save his life.
So that&#39;s thought where the term bootstrap came from.
And that&#39;s the term we&#39;re using here.
It&#39;s not the same as the term bootstrap that one uses in
computer science to boot a computer.
But it&#39;s the same idea.
You&#39;re trying to pull yourself up from what you&#39;ve got.
In this case, we&#39;ll see the bootstrap-- the bootstrap, is
we&#39;re going use the data itself to try to get more
information about our estimator.
So let&#39;s start with a simple example.
Suppose we have a fixed sum of money which we want to invest,
in two assets that yield returns x and y, where x and y
are round quantities, depending on
how the assets do.
And we want to invest a fraction alpha of our money in
x, and the remaining 1 minus alpha in y.
You want to choose the fraction alpha to minimize the
total risk or the variance of our investment.
So we have random variables x and y.
We want to choose the alpha to minimize the variance of alpha
x plus 1 minus alpha times y.
Now in this population model, you can show that the best
fraction alpha is given by this formula.
Sigma squared y, that&#39;s the difference of y, there&#39;s the
variance of x.
This is the covariance between x and y.
And they&#39;re defined here.
So in other words, if we know the variance of x, the
variance of y, and their covariance, then this is the
best amount proportion to put into x, and the remaining goes
into y, to minimize the total variance.
Those are population quantities, aren&#39;t they?
Those are population quantities.
So since they&#39;re population quantities, they&#39;re are not
known to us in general.
But if we have a data set from the population under study
here, we can get an idea of these quantities, the
variances and the covariances, from the sample values from
the data set.
And then plug them into the formula to get the alpha hat,
which is the proportion that we should invest in x.
So again, if we have a sample of x and y, we can get the
empirical estimates of the variances and covariances,
plug them in, and get an estimate of alpha.
So in this next slide, we see we&#39;ve created a simulated
population.
We&#39;ve simulated investments x and y.
There are four different simulations here, each one
containing 100 pairs of x and y.
And for each one, we take that data.
We compute the variances and covariances.
And we plug it into the formula to get an
estimate for alpha.
And here, we see the four estimates of alpha for the
four panels.
0.576 et cetera to 0.651.
So they&#39;re averaging around 0.6.
So if we want to get an idea of the standard deviation of
alpha hat, we can just repeat this process lots of times.
Let&#39;s say 1,000 times.
So we would get 1,000 pounds like this.
Each one gives us an alpha hat from the formula on the
previous slide.
And we do this 1,000 times.
We take the standard error of those--
well, actually, let&#39;s.
If it&#39;s 1,000 times, we&#39;ll go to look at the histogram in a
couple of slides.
This histogram on the left shows the 1,000 values over
1,000 simulations from this experiment.
Each one is a value of alpha hat, and they
average around 0.6.
It&#39;s called the sampling
distribution of that estimator.
Right.
And the true value, actually, since we know in this case--
we&#39;re playing God, right?-- we know the true variances and
covariances.
We know the true alpha.
And it&#39;s about 0.6.
So I&#39;ve indicated here with a purple line the 0.6.
And the sampling distribution is averaging around 0.6, as we
think it should.
I should say--
I&#39;ve said this already--
here&#39;s the histogram we&#39;ve seen.
For the simulations actually, these were the values, the
parameters, that we set.
And that implied a true of alpha of 0.6, which was that
middle value in the histogram.
That&#39;s the true value of alpha.
And now we can also use this histogram to get the standard
deviation of the estimates, just by picking the standard
deviation of those 1,000 values of alpha hat.
And here we&#39;ve done that, and that&#39;s 0.083.
So the standard error of alpha hat is roughly 0.083.
The standard error of an estimator is the standard
deviation in that sampling distribution.
So if you&#39;re able to recompute the estimator many, many times
from your samples, the standard deviation is called
the standard error.
Right.
So if we repeat this experiment, we expect each
time that, on average, alpha hat will be about 0.6, and
would vary by a standard deviation of 0.0.83.
Which we&#39;re seeing in this histogram, right?
It&#39;s averaging about 0.08, and the standard deviation is
about 0.08 of this histogram.
OK.
So that&#39;s all fine, except we can actually apply
this with real data.
If we had a sample of investments, x and y, we don&#39;t
actually have the ability to sample from the population.
We don&#39;t have the population.
We have a single sample.
So most of statistics, we don&#39;t have access to the
population.
All we have is a sample.
If we had access to the population, we actually
wouldn&#39;t need statistics at all, for the most part.
We could learn all we wanted to know from the population.
But in the real world, we have data.
We don&#39;t actually know the populations from which that
data arose.
We have an idea of what it might look like, but we can&#39;t
generate more data.
So we can&#39;t actually.
We can&#39;t produce the histogram on the left because we don&#39;t
have the ability to generate more data.
But the bootstrap is going to try.
It&#39;s going to mimic this process by sampling not from
the population, but from the data itself.
So the data itself is going to act as the population.
So instead of obtaining independent data sets from the
population, which we can do without access to the
population, we&#39;re going to sample from the data itself
with replacement.
And I&#39;ll remind you in a minute what that means.
But basically, we&#39;re going to sample from the data set
itself, and then use those samples to get an idea of the
variability, in the same way that we use the samples from
the population to produce this histogram.
We&#39;re going to sample from the data, the data itself as a
population.
So here&#39;s an idea.
This is an illustration of bootstrap sampling, which is
sampling with replacement.
I&#39;ve created a data set here just with three observations,
just so we could draw it on a single slide.
Here&#39;s our original data.
Here&#39;s our three observations.
And now, each of these is a bootstrap sample.
A bootstrap sample is drawn with replacement of the same
size as original data.
So the original data here&#39;s about three observations.
So we&#39;re going to draw three observations with replacement.
What does that mean?
It means that the chance of each observation being sampled
is the same, 1/3.
But it&#39;s done with replacement.
So imagine you put three balls into a bag, say,
numbered 1, 2, and 3.
We put our hand in the bag.
We pull out one at random.
Maybe we&#39;ll get number 1.
That&#39;s our first observation.
Now to get our second observation, we put the ball
back in the bag.
That&#39;s why it&#39;s called with replacement.
And we sample again, from all three balls.
So at every stage, each ball has the same probability of
being sampled.
And it can be sampled more than once, from
stage one to end.
So here, for example, we&#39;ve got observation 3 twice,
conservation 1 once.
Observation 2 didn&#39;t get sampled at all.
In this second bootstrap sample--
and we&#39;re drawing three samples from these three
observations--
we happen to get to 2, 3, and 1.
So each observation actually occurred once.
This next sample, we&#39;ve got observation 2 twice, and then
observation 1.
So just to summarize, we sampled the same number of
observations as in our original sample, with
replacement.
Meaning, each observation can appear more than once, or
maybe not at all, depending on what happens
as we draw the samples.
So these are called bootstrap samples, or
bootstrap data sets.
And then to each bootstrap data set, we apply the
estimator-- in this case, the alpha.
This is the proportion of investment x.
We compute it from this sample just as we computed it from
the original sample.
And we use the standard deviation of these numbers to
give us an idea of the standard error, the standard
deviation of alpha hat.
So having drawn 1,000 bootstrap samples and got our
estimates of alpha hat, we can draw the
histogram as we did before.
Let&#39;s go back to the slide.
So now, back on slide 29, remember on the left is the
histogram, the one we sampled from the population, the
histogram of alpha hat values.
We can&#39;t sample from the population because we don&#39;t
have the population.
So we did bootstrap sampling.
Look at the histogram in the middle, the blue histogram.
It looks very much like the one on the left.
It&#39;s averaging around 0.6, and its variability is about the
same as we got sampled from the population.
As a matter of fact, over here we&#39;ve got the box plots of the
alpha hat values, the true ones from the sample from the
population and the bootstrap ones.
And they&#39;re looking pretty similar.
They&#39;re averaging around 0.6, although the bootstrap&#39;s a
little lower in this case.
But in general, this gives you a pretty good idea of what we
get if we could sample from the population.
In the standard error estimate--
let&#39;s see, we have back here?
Yeah, the standard error estimate is 0.087.
Which is similar, we got 0.083 before when we used a sample
from the population.
So the bootstrap has use the data itself as the population
and got us a good estimate the standard error, very similar
to the one we&#39;d get if we could sample from the
population.
So we&#39;ve seen some examples of the
bootstrap in simple problems.
In the next session, we&#39;ll talk about the method in more
generality.