OK.
That&#39;s discriminant analysis when we
use Gaussian densities.
But now the form that we wrote down is quite general.
And you can use other estimates of densities and
plug them into this rule and get classification rules.
Up till now we&#39;ve been using Gaussian densities with the
same variance for the X&#39;s in each class.
What if the variances are different in each class?
Well, you can plug those forms in.
And then remember we had that magic cancellation because of
the equal variances?
Well, when the variances are different in each class, the
quadratic terms don&#39;t cancel.
And so now your discriminant functions are going to be
quadratic functions of X. OK?
That&#39;s one form.
It&#39;s called quadratic discriminant analysis.
Another thing you can do--
and especially this is useful when you have a large number
of features, like the 4,000 or so that Rob mentioned, when
you really wouldn&#39;t want to estimate these large
covariance matrices--
you can assume that in each class the density factors into
a product of densities.
That amounts to saying that the variables are
conditionally independent in each of the classes.
And if you do that and plug it into this formula over here,
you get something known as the naive Bayes classifier.
For linear discriminant analysis, this means that the
covariances, sigma sub k are diagonal.
And instead of estimating the covariance matrix, if you&#39;ve
got P variables it&#39;s got P squared parameters.
But if you assume that it&#39;s diagonal, then you need to
estimate P parameters again.
And although the assumption seems very crude--
the assumption is wrong--
this naive Bayes classifier is actually very useful in
high-dimensional problems.
And it&#39;s one actually we&#39;ll return to later
in different forms.
Right.
In fact, we&#39;d probably think it&#39;s always wrong, wouldn&#39;t
[? we, Rob? ?]
Right.
Yeah.
And so what happens is we end up with quiet flattened and
maybe biased estimates for the probabilities.
But in terms of classification, you just need
to know which probability&#39;s the largest to classify it.
So you can tolerate quite a lot of bias and still get good
classification performance.
And what you get in return is much reduced variance from
having to estimate far fewer parameters.
Then there&#39;s much more other general forms where we don&#39;t
assume Gaussian at all.
We can estimate the densities using our favorite density
estimation technique and then go and plug them back into
this formula, and that&#39;ll give you a classification rule.
That&#39;s a very general approach that can be used.
And in fact, many of the classifiers that we know we
can understand from this point of view.
So here we have it.
Quadratic discriminant analysis uses a different
covariance matrix for each class.
And so there&#39;s no cancellation of the sigmas.
The discriminant functions now have this distance term that
involves sigma sub k, which is for the kth class.
There&#39;s a term to do with the prior probability, and there&#39;s
a determinant term that comes from the covariance matrix.
And you can see it gives you a curved discriminant boundary.
And the quadratic terms matter here,
because they&#39;re different.
In the left plot here, we see a case when the true boundary
really should be linear.
That&#39;s the dotted curve.
And in this case, of course linear discriminant analysis
does a good job.
Quadratic discriminant analysis curves somewhat and
gives a slight bent boundary.
But it won&#39;t really affect most classification
performance much.
In the right hand plot, on the other hand, the true data came
from a situation where the covariance were different.
The Bayes decision boundary is curved, and the quadratic
discriminant analysis pretty much got it, whereas linear
discriminant analysis gives you quite a different boundary
in that case.
Quadratic discriminant analysis is attractive if the
number of variables is small.
When the number of variables or features is large, you&#39;ve
got to estimate these big covariance matrices, and
things can break down.
And even for LDA it can break down.
Here&#39;s where naive Bayes becomes attractive.
It makes a much stronger assumption.
It assumes that the covariance in each of the classes,
although different, are diagonal.
And so that&#39;s much fewer parameters.
Now when you look at the discriminant functions,
because diagonal and Gaussian means that the densities are
independent and so we have this product here, when we
take logs we get a relatively simple expression, which is in
each class there&#39;s a contribution of the feature
from the mean for the class scaled by the variance,
there&#39;s the determinant term, and there&#39;s the prior term.
This is the discriminant function for the kth class for
naive Bayes.
And you compute one of these for each of the classes, then
you classify it.
You can use mixed features for naive Bayes.
And in that case, what we mean by that is some qualitative
and some quantitative futures.
For the quantitative ones, we&#39;d use the Gaussian.
And for the qualitative ones, we replace the Gaussian
densities by just histograms or probability mass functions,
in this case, over the discrete categories.
Naive Bayes is very handy from this point of view.
And even though it has strong assumptions, it often produces
good classification results.
Because also, once again in classification, we&#39;re mainly
concerned about which class has the highest probability
and not whether we got the probabilities exactly right.
OK.
We&#39;ve seen two forms of classification, logistic
regression and linear discriminant analysis.
And we saw its generalizations.
How do they differ?
It seems there may be similarities between the two.
Now it turns out you can show for linear discriminant
analysis that if you take its--
We had expression for the probabilities
for each of the classes.
So if you have two classes, we can show that if you take the
log odds, just like we did in logistic regression, which is
the log of the probability for class one versus the
probability for class two, it&#39;s a linear function of X
for two classes.
It&#39;s got exactly the same form as logistic regression.
They both give you linear logistic models.
So the difference is in how the parameters are estimated.
Logistic regression uses the conditional likelihood based
on probability of Y given X. Remember, it was using the
probabilities of a 1 or a 0 given X
in each of the classes.
And in machine learning, this is known as discriminative
learning using the conditional distribution of Y given X.
Discriminant analysis, it turns out it&#39;s estimating
these parameters over here using the full likelihood.
Because it&#39;s using the distribution of X&#39;s and Y&#39;s,
whereas logistic regression was only using the
distribution of Y&#39;s.
And in that case, it&#39;s known as generative learning.
Remember, we modelled the means and variances of X in
each of the classes, and we modeled the prior probability.
So that can be seen as modelling the joint
distribution of X and Y. That&#39;s one way of seeing
what&#39;s different between the two.
But despite these differences, in practice the results are
often very similar.
And you can use one method with the other, and you&#39;re
going to get very similar results.
As a footnote, logistic regression can also fit
quadratic boundaries.
We used quadratic discriminant analysis to get quadratic
boundaries.
But we can fit quadratic boundaries by explicitly
including quadratic terms in the model.
Just like we did in linear regression, in logistic
regression we can put in X squareds and XI&#39;s times XJ&#39;s
and terms like that and just explicitly
get a quadratic boundary.
OK.
That&#39;s the end of this section.
That&#39;s an introduction to classification using these two
very popular methods.
And later on in the class, you&#39;re going to see that we&#39;re
going to come back to some of these methods and look at more
general versions of them and build richer
classification rules.
And importantly, we&#39;ll discuss another very popular method
called the support vector machine, which is another
approach to classification.
And by way of coming attractions, the next section
is going to be on
cross-validation and bootstrap.
In that section, we&#39;ll get to meet Brad Efron, who&#39;s our
colleague and also was my PhD supervisor many years ago.
And he was the person who invented the bootstraps.
So he&#39;ll tell us a bit about the bootstrap and how he
proposed it in his 1980 paper.
Oh, fantastic.