OK, now we&#39;re going to have an R session to
demonstrate the bootstrap.
The bootstrap is one of the really powerful tools we have
in modern statistics invented by our friend Brad Efron, just
across the road from us here.
And what it does is it lets you get at the sampling
distribution of statistics, for which it&#39;s really hard to
develop theoretical versions.
So the bootstrap gives us a really easy way of doing
statistics when the theory is very hard.
And to illustrate it we&#39;ll use the example we used in the
book in section 5.2 where we have a particularly non-linear
formula for picking an optimal combination of two
investments.
OK?
So let&#39;s have a look at that.
OK, so remember you had two investments, x and y.
And let&#39;s say they had risk, which we&#39;ll call variance of x
and variance of y.
This is a guy who cannot distinguish uppercase and
lowercase letters.
And we saw--
well, we told you that the optimal formula for getting a
minimum risk investment, if you&#39;re going to use alpha of x
and 1 minus alpha of y, is given by the formula variance
of y minus covariance of x and y divided by--
there we go, lower case a again--
plus variance of y minus 2 times covariance of x and y.
OK?
So that&#39;s a formula which, of course, if we have data on x
and y we can just compute those variances and
covariances and plug them in and compute
our value for alpha.
Now that&#39;s fine, but then you might say, well, what is the
sampling variability of alpha?
What&#39;s the standard error of alpha?
Right?
How variable is it going to be?
Well, that&#39;s a non-linear formula of x and y.
And we just wouldn&#39;t know a priori how to do that.
This is a case where the bootstrap really helps out.
So we&#39;ll write a function for computing that formula.
It&#39;s a simple formula.
Given two vectors, x and y, of actual data we write our
function alpha and inside it we compute variance of x
variance of y covariance of x and y and then we just write
out that formula.
And closed parens, which means that the function will return
the last line that was evaluated, which is
actually our alpha.
OK?
And so now we&#39;ve got a data set portfolio, which has x and
y in it, and we can run alpha on the x and y
in that data frame.
And when we do it we see that alpha comes up to 0.5758.
OK, so in order to use the bootstrap function we need to
make a little wrapper that allows a bootstrap to work.
And this is this function we&#39;ll call alpha.fn.
And what it does is it takes a data frame and an index, which
indexes rows of the data frame, and then computes your
statistic--
in this case alpha index, for which it wants to compute the
variance in this case, the standard error.
Now what index does, it&#39;s going to be an index into the
numbers 1 to n, it&#39;ll have values of 1 to n, and there
will be n of them, and they can be repeats of course.
Because the bootstrap, what the bootstrap does is does a
re-sample of your training observations and some
observations can be represented more than once and
some not at all.
And index will say which observations get represented
and if they&#39;re repeated that&#39;ll be fine, because
that&#39;s what the bootstrap does.
And so what this function does is--
let&#39;s just enter the function.
OK?
It uses the function, &quot;with,&quot; which is very handy function.
With takes first argument of data frame
and then some commands.
And what it says is, using the data in the data frame,
execute the commands.
So in this case, we use with data of index, so that gets
the right observations for this
particular bootstrap sample.
Compute alpha of x and y.
And the main value of with is that you can use the named
variables x and y that are in the data frame.
OK?
Very handy.
All right, let&#39;s see if this works.
We&#39;ll run our function just once using the original index
of the data, portfolio 1 to n, and we see we get the same
value as we got before.
So that works.
And so now we&#39;ll run the bootstrap.
And since a bootstrap involves random sampling, and if we
want to get reproducible results just for purpose of
demonstration, it&#39;s good to set the random number seed.
So there we set seed 1.
And now we run alpha.fn one more time, but we take a
random sample instead of giving an index 1 to n.
So here we&#39;ve sampled the numbers 1 to 100, sample of
size 100, with replace equals 2.
This is the kind of thing the bootstrap&#39;s going
to do over and over.
Here we just do it once.
OK?
So we get a different value of index.
That&#39;s like a bootstrap sample of size 1.
Well, we&#39;ll let the bootstrap do the work for us.
And so we call the function boot, we give it the data
frame portfolio, we give it our little function alpha.fn,
and we tell it to do 1,000 bootstraps.
Look how fast that was.
It&#39;s come back already.
If we type boot.out it gives a little summary of the
bootstrap and it tells us our original statistic was 0.575--
the estimate--
and it gives us the estimate of bias and standard error.
We were interested in the standard error.
The bias is negligible.
The standard error in this case is 0.08.
And that&#39;s computed by the bootstrap.
And you can also plot the bootstrap.
It&#39;s nice to see what the distribution looks like.
And you get a two paddle plot.
One is a histogram and it looks like a pretty nice
symmetric distribution, maybe Gaussian.
And in fact the second plot is a qqplot, which plots the
ordered values against the ordered
statistics of a Gaussian.
And if it lines up on a straight line like it pretty
much does here, you may say it looks close to Gaussian, maybe
a slightly bigger tail on the right.
So there&#39;s a bootstrap.
Very handy way of getting very good reliable estimates of
standard error for nasty statistics.