OK, well, welcome back.
We&#39;re going to have a conversation now.
And once again, we&#39;ll use RStudio, which is a very
convenient platform for running R, and for
demonstrating R. So we&#39;ll go to our screen now, and we&#39;ll
do an RStudio session on linear discriminant analysis
first of all, and then followed by nearest neighbor
classification.
So here we are right now, RStudio session window.
And the first thing we do is we require ISLR.
That&#39;s our package with some of our data sets.
So I&#39;ll hit the Control button and return,
and it loads a package.
And then we require the math package, which is available in
Ripley&#39;s package of useful functions, including the
function for doing linear discriminant analysis.
You&#39;ll see in the right-hand panel, I&#39;ve got a help file
for linear discriminant analysis.
So as always in R, if you don&#39;t know or if you&#39;re not
too familiar with the new procedure, you do Help, and
make sure you understand the syntax and all the
options, and so on.
So the first thing we do, we&#39;re going to use the stock
market data here, and the response is going to be the
direction that the market took on a particular day.
And we&#39;re going to use the returns on the previous two
days to try and predict the direction on
this particular day.
OK, and so there, we use a command, [? LDA.fct. ?]
And it takes a formula, so the response is direction.
There are the two predictors.
It&#39;s telling you the data comes from s
market, stock market.
And we&#39;re going to use the subset, which is years less
than 2005, because later on, we&#39;re going to make
predictions for year 2005.
So you can put that directly in the formula, subset equals
year less than 2005.
And this variable, year, of course is referenced in s
market, as well as these variables over here.
OK, so off we go, and we fit it.
And it fits it so very quickly, and we print it by
just typing its name.
And there&#39;s a little summary printed below here.
And you see, typically you get the formula that was used to
create it, and then it gives a summary of the linear
discriminant analysis.
So the prior probabilities are just the proportions of ups
and downs in the data set.
It&#39;s roughly 50%, which says something
about the market, right?
It&#39;s kind of a random walk.
Half the time it goes up, half the time it goes down.
It summarizes the group means for the two groups, for the
downs and the ups.
It looks like there may be a slight difference
in these two groups.
The means seem to be separated a little bit.
And then it gives the LDA coefficients.
So if you remember the LDA function fits a linear
function for separating the two groups.
And so, it&#39;s got two coefficients.
OK, well there&#39;s some methods that work for the LDA.
For example, you can plot a [? LDA.fct ?],
which we&#39;ll do here.
And it gives a very convenient plot.
It plots a linear discriminant function separately, the
values of the linear discriminant function,
separately for the up group and the down group.
And when we look at this, it looks to the eye like there&#39;s
really not much difference.
Those two histograms look pretty much on top of each
other, which of course, is not a big surprise, because if we
could very easily like this predict the movement of the
stock market, we&#39;d be making lots of money, and we wouldn&#39;t
be sitting here giving R demonstrations.
So now we&#39;re going to see how well our rule predicts on the
year 2005, OK?
So now, I&#39;m doing this in a slightly different way to what
was described in the book.
We first will make a subset of the data frame, s market, and
we&#39;ll call it s market dot 2005.
And we use a command in R-- a useful command--
called subset.
And so the first argument is the data frame that you&#39;re
going to subset, which is s market.
And then following that are some logical expressions that
can use variables in that data frame to define the subset.
And so, here it is year equals equals 2005, OK?
And that will create a data frame with just the 2005
observations.
And so now we can use that as the test data, or the place
where we want to make our predictions.
So we&#39;d call the predict method for an LDA fit, and we
give it our fit, and we give it this new data frame, s
market dot 2005.
And it&#39;ll produce some predictions for us.
And let&#39;s just print the first five of these, and oops-- it
didn&#39;t like that.
So I was assuming it was in a matrix format, and it&#39;s not.
So what format is it?
So we don&#39;t throw up our hands and run away when we get an
error, we just investigate.
So let&#39;s look at the class of [? LDA.prd. ?]
Well, it&#39;s a list.
Now I happen to know what kind of list it is.
And when you have a list of variables, and each of the
variables have the same number of observations, a convenient
way of looking at such a list is through data frame.
And so we can do data frame of [? LDA.prd, ?]
and then look at the first five rows.
And this is what we get.
And you&#39;ll see what this gives us.
It gives a row name, it gives the classification--
the first five are all up.
And one of the components of the list was a matrix of
posterior probabilities, which actually have
a two-column matrix.
But data frame is smart enough to understand that these can
fit into the data frame.
And so it makes two columns, one for up and one for down--
the posterior probabilities.
And then there&#39;s the actual values of the LDA score, OK?
And so now, now we realize that the output of print has
these different components.
The thing we&#39;re really interested in here is the
classification, so that&#39;s class.
So we&#39;re going to do a table of [? LDAprd$class. ?]
That&#39;s a true class label for the 2005--
versus the prediction--
sorry, that is the prediction--
versus the true value, right?
So this is the predicted class, and this is the true
value over here in the data frame.
We&#39;ll do a table of that, and we get the little confusion
matrix, which tells us which downs were classified as down,
which downs are classified as up, and so on.
And it&#39;s the off-diagonal elements of those that are the
mistakes, and the diagonal elements which are the correct
classifications.
And so, one simple command tells us our current
classification rate, which is we&#39;ve got a conditional here,
which is the predicted class is equal to the true class.
So that&#39;ll be true if they&#39;re equal, and it&#39;ll be false if
they&#39;re not.
And since trues and falses can be coerces to be zeros and
ones, we can just take the mean of that, and it&#39;ll give
us our current classification rate, which in this case is
about 0.56.
So it&#39;s not huge, but again, in this kind of industry, any
little edge like that, that actually helps.
And so, that&#39;s a little session using linear
discriminant analysis, and there&#39;s many other approaches.
There&#39;s some more examples in the book, and you should have
a look there.