Welcome back.
So in the last section of the course, we talked about the
situation where the response was quantitative, a
regression.
In this section, we&#39;re going to talk about classification
where the response variable has got two or more values.
And this is actually a very commonly occurring problem--
actually, probably more commonly occurring than
regression.
In machine learning, especially, there&#39;s a big
concentration on classification where, for
example, we&#39;re trying to predict whether an email is a
good email or spam, or in a medical area, trying to
predict whether a patient is going to survivor or die with
a given disease.
So it&#39;s a very commonly occurring
problem, and very important.
So we&#39;re going to spend some time today on this, actually
in the next set of lectures, on classification.
And Trevor and I are both here.
Trevor&#39;s going to give most of the talk.
And I&#39;m going to pipe in and correct him when he makes
mistakes and make fun of his accent and things like that.
That means we won&#39;t hear much from you, no?
We&#39;ll see.
Anyway, let&#39;s go to the slides.
The first thing we do is just show you what categorical
variables look like.
I&#39;m sure you know-- so for example, eye color.
That takes on three values-- brown, blue, and green.
Those are discrete values.
There&#39;s no ordering.
They&#39;re just three different values.
Email we&#39;ve talked about already.
There&#39;s spam and ham.
I like that word, ham.
I like ham myself.
I wish I had thought of it.
Anyway, ham is good email.
So spam filters need to classify into spam or ham.
So what is a classifier?
Well, you&#39;ve got a feature vector X, just like we had in
regression.
And now, you have one of these qualitative response variables
like those above.
And here&#39;s the mathy description of a classifier.
The response takes values in a set C, which is a set of
discrete values.
And the classification task is to build a function that takes
X as input and delivers one of the elements of the set C. And
so this is how we write it in math language--
C of X gives you values in the set C.
So for example, in the spam/ham problem, C of X would
either come back as spam or ham.
Now, although classification problems are always couched in
this form, we&#39;re often more interested in estimating the
probabilities that X belongs to each category C. So for
example, it&#39;s more valuable for an insurance company to
have an estimate of the probability that an insurance
claim is fraudulent than a classification
fraudulent or not.
You can imagine, in the one situation, you might have a
probability of 0.9 the claim is fraudulent.
And in another case, it might be 0.98.
Now in both cases, those might both be above the threshold of
raising the flag that this is a fraudulent insurance claim.
But if you&#39;re going to look into the claim, and you&#39;re
going to spend some hours investigating, you&#39;ll probably
go for the 0.98 first before the 0.9.
So estimating the probabilities is also key.
OK, so here&#39;s some data.
Two variables--
this is the credit card default data set that we&#39;re
going to use in this section.
And the part on the left here is a scatter plot of balance
against income.
So those are two of the variables.
And as we can with classification problems, we
can code the response variable into the plot as a color.
And so here, we have the blue points and the brown points.
And the brown points are going to be those that defaulted.
And the blue points are those that did not.
Now, this is a fictitious data set.
Typically, you don&#39;t expect to see that many defaulters.
But we&#39;ll talk about balance in classification tasks a
little bit later as well.
So in this plot, it looks like balance is
the important variable.
Notice that there&#39;s a big separation between the blues
and the browns, the defaulters and those that didn&#39;t, OK?
Whereas with income, there doesn&#39;t seem to be much
separation at all, OK?
In the right, we actually show box plots
of these two variables.
And so we see, for example, for default, there&#39;s--
oh, I beg your pardon.
Default is at the bottom-- no or yes, no, yes in both cases.
We&#39;ve got balance, and we&#39;ve got income.
And here, we also clearly see that there&#39;s a big difference
in the distributions--
balance default or not, whereas for income, there
hardly seems to be any difference.
I&#39;ve never seen a box plot before.
What is that?
Oh, you tell me, Rob.
OK, well, a box plot, what&#39;s indicated there--
Trevor, you can point--
the black line is the median.
There&#39;s a black line.
That&#39;s a median.
So that&#39;s the median for the S, the median income for
people who have defaulted.
And then, the top of the box are the quartiles.
That&#39;s the 75th quartile, 75th percentile, quartile.
And the 25th is the bottom of the box.
So really, it&#39;s a good summary of the distribution of income
for those in category yes.
What about these things at the end, Rob?
OK, I think they&#39;re called hinges.
They are called hinges.
And those are the ranges, are they, or approximately the
ranges of the data?
Yeah, I think a hinge is defined to be a fraction of
the interquartile range.
And so it gives you an idea of the spread of the data.
And if data points fall outside the hinges, they&#39;re
considered to be outliers.
By the way, it&#39;s a very useful data display.
Almost one of the first things you should do when you get
some data to analyze is do some scatter plots and create
some box plots.
Who invented the box plot, Rob?
John Tukey.
John Tukey, one of the most famous statisticians--
he&#39;s no longer with us, but he&#39;s left a big legacy behind.
OK, well, one question we can ask is, can we use linear
regression to solve classification problems?
It seems like we may be able to.
So supposed for the default classification task that we
code the response 0 if no default, 1 if
yes default, right?
It&#39;s somewhat arbitrary, but 0 and 1 seem sufficient.
And then, we could simply perform a linear regression of
Y on X with X being the two predictors in this case, and
classify as yes if Y hat is bigger than 0.5, 50%, right?
0.5 is halfway between 0 and 1.
It seems like a reasonable idea.
It turns out that you actually can do this.
For a binary outcome, linear regression does a pretty good
job and is equivalent to linear discriminant analysis.
And that&#39;s something we&#39;re going to discuss later.
So for a two class classification problem like
this, it doesn&#39;t do a bad job at all.
And there&#39;s even some theoretical justification.
In the population, remember, in the population, we think of
regression as estimating the conditional mean of Y given X.
Well, in our coding here of 0 and 1, the conditional mean of
the 0, 1 variable given X is simply the probability that Y
is 1 given X just by simple probability theory.
So for that reason, you might think that regression is
perfect for this task.
What we&#39;re going to see, however, is that linear
regression might actually produce probabilities that
could be less than 0, or even bigger than 1.
And for this reason, we&#39;re going to introduce you to
logistic regression, which is more appropriate.
And here&#39;s a little picture that illustrates it.
Here, we&#39;ve got out balance variable.
Now, we&#39;ve plotted against balance.
We&#39;ve plotted the 0&#39;s at the bottom as little dashes here,
the browns.
And the little brown spikes are all clumped together at
the bottom.
And the 1&#39;s are plotted at the top here.
And we see the separation.
The brown 0&#39;s are towards the left of balance.
And the 1&#39;s are towards the right.
And the blue line is a linear regression line.
And lo and behold, it goes below 0.
So that&#39;s not a very good estimate of a probability.
It also seems not to go high enough on the right-hand side
where it seems clear that there&#39;s a preponderance of
yeses on the right-hand side.
In the right-hand plot, we&#39;ve got the foot of logistic
regression.
And it seems to do a pretty good job in this case.
It never gets outside of 0 and 1, and it seems to go up high
where it&#39;s meant to go up high.
So it seems things aren&#39;t looking terrific for linear
regression in terms of estimating probabilities.
So now, what happens if we have a
three category variable?
So here&#39;s a variable that measures the patient&#39;s
condition at an emergency room and takes on three levels.
So it&#39;s 1 if it&#39;s a stroke, 2 if it&#39;s a drug overdose, and 3
if it&#39;s an epileptic seizure.
So if we code those as, say, 1, 2, and 3, which would be an
arbitrary but natural choice, this coding might suggest an
ordering when in fact there&#39;s not necessarily an ordering
here at all.
And it might in fact imply that the difference between
stroke and drug overdose, which is one unit, is the same
as the difference between drug overdose
and epileptic seizure.
So when you have more than two categories, assigning numbers
to the categories just arbitrarily seems a little
dangerous, and especially if you&#39;re going to use it in
linear regression.
And it turns out linear regression is
not appropriate here.
And for problems like this, we&#39;re going to prefer
multiclass logistic regression or discriminant analysis.
And both of those we will discuss.