OK, up till now, we&#39;ve talked about estimating regression
functions for quantitative response.
And we&#39;ve seen how to do model selection there.
Now we&#39;re going to move to classification problems.
And here, we&#39;ve got a different
kind of response variable.
It&#39;s what we call a qualitative variable.
For example, email is one of two classes, spam or ham, ham
being the good email.
And if we classify in digits, it&#39;s one of the class is 0, 1,
up to 9, and so it&#39;s a slightly different problem.
And our goals are slightly different as well.
Here, our goals up to build a classifier, which we might
call c of x, that assigns a class label from our set c to
a future, unlabeled observation x, where is x is
the feature vector.
We&#39;d also like to assess the uncertainty in each
classification, and we&#39;d also like to understand the roles
of the different predictors amongst the x&#39;s in producing
that classify.
And so we are going to see how we do that in the
next number of slides.
OK.
To try and parallel our development for the
quantitative response, I&#39;ve made up a
little simulation example.
And we&#39;ve got one x, one y.
The y takes on two values in this example.
The values are just coded as 0 and 1.
And we&#39;ve got a big sample of these y&#39;s from a population.
So each little vertical bar here indicates an occurrence
of a zero, the orange vertical bars, as a
function of the x&#39;s.
And at the top, we&#39;ve got where the ones occurred, OK?
So this scatter plot&#39;s much harder to read.
You can&#39;t really see what&#39;s going on.
And there&#39;s a black curve drawn in the figure.
And the back curve was what actually generated the data.
The black curve is actually showing us the probability of
a one in the model that I used to generate the data.
And so up in this region over here, the high values of x,
there&#39;s a higher probability of a one, close to 90% of
getting a one.
And so of course, we see more blue ones there than we see
zeroes down there.
And even though it&#39;s hard to see, there&#39;s a higher density
of zeroes in this region over here, where the probability is
0.4 of being a one, versus a zero it&#39;s 0.6.
OK, so we want to talk about what is an ideal
classifier c of x.
OK, so let&#39;s define these probabilities that I was
talking about.
And we&#39;ll call p sub k of x, this quantity over here,
that&#39;s a conditional probability that y is k given
x equals x.
In this case, we&#39;re just looking at probability of one
in the plot.
We&#39;re just showing the probability that y is one is
only two classes.
But in general, they&#39;ll be, say, capital K classes.
And they&#39;ll be capital K of these conditional
probabilities.
Now in classification problems, those conditional
probabilities completely capture the distribution, the
conditional distribution, of y given x.
And it turns out, that those also deliver the ideal
classifier.
We call the Bayes Optimal Classifier the classifier that
classifies to the class for which the conditional
probability for that element of the class is largest.
It makes sense.
You go to any point.
So here we&#39;ve gone to point 5 in the x space.
And you look above it, and you see that there&#39;s about 80%
probability of a one, and 20% probability of a zero.
And now we&#39;re going to say, well, if you were to classify
to one class at that point, which class would
you classify to?
Well, you&#39;re going to classify to the majority class, OK?
And that&#39;s called the Bayes Optimal Classifier.
Here&#39;s the same example, except now we&#39;ve only got a
handful of points.
We&#39;ve got 100 points having one of the two class labels.
The story is the same as before.
We can&#39;t compute the conditional probabilities
exactly, say, at the point 5.
Because in this case, we have got one one
at five and no zeroes.
So we send out a neighborhood, say, and gather 10% of the
data points.
And then estimate the conditional probabilities by
the proportions, in this case of ones and zeros in the
neighborhood.
And those are indicated by these little bars here.
These are meant to represent the probabilities or
proportions at this point, 5.
And again, there&#39;s a higher proportion of
ones here than zeroes.
I forgot to say that in the previous slide, that&#39;s the
same quantity over here that&#39;s indicating the probabilities
of the ones and the zeroes.
This is the exact in the population.
And here it is estimated with the nearest neighbor average.
So here we&#39;ve done the nearest neighbor
classifying in one dimension.
And we can draw a nice picture.
But of course, this works in multiple dimensions as well,
just like it did for regression.
So suppose we, for example, have two x&#39;s, and
they lie on the floor.
And we have a target point, say this point over here, and
we want to classify a new observation that
falls at this point.
Well, we can spread out a little, say, circular
neighborhood, and gather a bunch of observations who fall
in this neighborhood.
And we can count how many in class one, how many in class
two, and assign to the majority class.
And of course, this can be generalized to multiple
dimensions.
In all the problems we had with nearest neighbors for
regression, the curse of dimensionality when the number
of dimensions get large also happens here.
In order to gather enough points when the dimension&#39;s
really high, we have to send out a bigger and bigger sphere
to capture the points, and things start to break down,
because it&#39;s not local anymore.
So, some details.
Typically, we&#39;ll measure the performance of the classifier
using what we call them misclassification error rate.
And here, it&#39;s written on the test data set.
The error is just the average number of
mistakes we make, OK?
So it&#39;s the average number of times that the classification,
so c hat at a point xi, is not equal to the class label yi
averaged over a test set.
It&#39;s just the number of mistakes.
So that&#39;s when we count a mistake, mistaking a one for a
zero and a zero for a one as equal.
There are other ways of classifying error, where you
can have a cost, which gives higher cost to some mistakes
than others.
But we won&#39;t go into that here.
So that base classifier, the one that used the true
probabilities to decide on the classification rule, is the
one that makes the least mistakes in the population.
And that makes sense if you look at our population
example over here.
By classifying to one over here, we are going to make
mistakes on about 20% of the conditional population at this
value of x.
But we&#39;ll get it correct 80% of the time.
And so that&#39;s why it&#39;s obvious we want to classify to the
largest class.
We will make the fewest mistakes.
Later on in the course, we going to talk about support
vector machines.
And they build structured models for the
classifier c of x.
And we&#39;ll also build structured models for
representing the probabilities themselves.
And there, we&#39;ll discuss methods like logistic
regression and generalized additive models.
The high dimensional problem is worse for modeling the
probabilities than it is for actually building the
classifier.
For the classifier, the classifer just has to be
accurate with regard to which of the
probabilities is largest.
Whereas if we&#39;re really interested in the
probabilities themselves, we going to be measuring them on
a much finer scale.
OK, we&#39;ll end up with a two dimensional
example of nearest neighbors.
So this represents the truth.
We got an x1 and an x2.
And we&#39;ve got points from some population.
And the purple dotted line is what&#39;s called the Bayes
Decision Boundary.
Since we know the truth here, we know what the true
probabilities are everywhere in this domain.
And I indicated that all the points in the domain by the
little dots in the figure.
And so if you classify according to the true
probabilities, all the points, all the region colored orange
would be classified as the one class.
And all the region colored blue would be classified as
the blue class.
And the dotted line is called the decision boundary.
And so that&#39;s a contour of the place where, in this case,
there are two classes.
It&#39;s a contour of where the probabilities are equal for
the two classes.
So that&#39;s an undecided region.
It&#39;s called the decision boundary.
OK, so we can do nearest neighbor, averaging in two
dimensions.
So of course what we do here is, at any given point when we
want to classify--
let&#39;s say we pick this point over here--
we spread out a little neighborhood, in this case,
until we find the 10 closest points to the target point.
And we&#39;ll estimate the probability at this center
point here by the proportion of blues versus oranges.
And you do that at every point.
And if you use those as the probabilities, you get this
somewhat wiggly black curve as the
estimated decision boundary.
And you can see it&#39;s actually, apart from the somewhat ugly
wiggliness, it gets reasonably close to the true decision
boundary, which is, again, the purple dashed line, or curve.
OK, in the last slide, we used k equals 10.
We can use other values of k.
k equals 1 is a popular choice.
This is called the nearest neighbor classifier.
And we take literally at each target point, we find the
closest point amongst the training data and
classify to its class.
So for example, if we took a point over here, which is the
closest training point?
Well, this is it over here.
It&#39;s a blue.
So we&#39;d classify this as blue.
Right, when you&#39;re in a sea of blues, of course the nearest
point is always another blue.
And so you&#39;d always classified as blue.
What&#39;s interesting is as you get close to some of the
orange points.
And what this gives you-- you can see the boundary here is a
piecewise linear boundary.
Of course, the probabilities that we estimate is just one
and zero, because there&#39;s only one point to average.
So there&#39;s no real probabilities.
But if you think about the decision boundary, it&#39;s a
piecewise linear decision boundary.
And it&#39;s gotten by looking at the bisector of the line
separating each pair of points when they&#39;re
of different colors.
So you get this very ragged decision boundary.
You also get little islands.
So for example, there&#39;s a blue point and a
sea of oranges here.
So there&#39;s a little piecewise linear boundary around that
blue point.
Those are the points that are closest to that blue point,
closer to the blue point than the oranges.
Again, we see the true boundary here, or the best
base decision boundary is purple.
This nearest neighbor average approximates
it in a noisy way.
Now then, you can make k really large.
Here, we&#39;ve made k 100.
And the neighborhood&#39;s really large.
It&#39;s essentially, there&#39;s 200 points here.
So it&#39;s taken half the points to be in any given
neighborhood.
So let&#39;s suppose our test point was over here.
We&#39;d be sending out quite a big circle, gathering 100
points, getting the proportional of blues, the
proportion of oranges, and then making the boundary.
So as k gets bigger, this boundary starts smoothing out
and getting less interesting in this case.
It&#39;s almost like a linear boundary over here, and
doesn&#39;t pick up the nuances of the decision boundary.
Whereas with k equals 10, it seemed like a pretty good
choice, and of approximates that this is the decision
boundary pretty well.
OK, so the choice of k is a tuning parameter.
And that needs to be selected.
And here we showed what happens as you vary k, first
on the training data and then on the test data.
So on the training data, k tends to just keep on
decreasing.
It&#39;s not actually monotone.
Because we&#39;ve actually indexed this as 1/k, because as 1/k
gets big, let&#39;s see.
K large means we get a higher bias, so 1/k small.
So this is the low complexity region.
This is the high complexity region.
Now you notice that the training error for one nearest
neighbors, which is right down at the end here,
1/k is one is zero.
Well, if you think about it, that&#39;s what it&#39;s got to be, if
you think about what training error is.
For the test error, it&#39;s actually
started increasing again.
This horizontal dotted line is the Bayes error, which you
can&#39;t do better than the Bayes error in theory.
Of course, this is a finite test data set.
But it actually just touches on the Bayes error.
It starts decreasing, and then at some point, it levels off
and then starts increasing again.
So if we had a validation set available, that&#39;s what we use
to determine k.
So that&#39;s nearest neighbor classification.
Very powerful tool.
It&#39;s said that about one third of classification problems,
the best tool will be nearest neighbor classification.
On the handwritten zip code problem, the classifying
handwritten digits, nearest neighbor classifiers do about
as well as in any other method tried.
So it&#39;s a powerful technique to have in the tool bag, and
it&#39;s one of the techniques that we&#39;ll use for
classification.
But in the rest of the course, we&#39;ll cover other
techniques as well.
In particular, with the support vector machines,
various forms of logistic regression and linear
discriminant analysis.