OK.
Now we slipped one thing by you.
We said in South Africa the risk for heart disease is
about 5% in this age category.
But in our sample, we&#39;ve got 160 cases and 302 controls, so
in the sample we&#39;re showing a risk of 0.35.
It seems like the model is going to be off.
It&#39;s going to estimate probabilities too high.
Well, case-control sampling is one of the favorite tools in
epidemiology.
Especially when you have a rare disease, you take all the
cases you can find, and then you can just
sample from the controls.
The reason is that for the logistic regression model it
turns out that you can estimate the regression
parameters of interest-- these of the coefficients of the x&#39;s
in this case--
accurately.
That&#39;s if the model&#39;s correct.
But the constant term will be incorrect.
Then you can just go ahead and correct the constant too by a
simple transformation.
And in fact, for those that are interested, I just give
you the transformation.
So pi [INAUDIBLE] here is the apparent risk of heart
disease, in this case in our population, which is 0.35.
And after all, this is just the logit transformation of
the prior probability or the prior apparent probability.
And here&#39;s the logit transformation of the true
risk, which is pi, in this case, 0.05.
And so we take the logit transformation of those two,
and we correct the intercept.
This is the currently estimated intercept.
We correct it by adding in the log odds of the true
probability, subtract the apparent one.
That correct the intercept.
Maybe it&#39;s worth saying a little bit about case-control
sampling, why the sampling&#39;s done this way.
One thing we could have done instead, or the investors
could have done was to take maybe 1,000 people and to
follow them for 20 years and to record their risk factors
and then see who gets heart disease.
We think about 5% will get heart disease.
That&#39;s a valid thing to do, but the problem is it takes 20
years and maybe more than a few thousand
people to get enough--
Actually, with 1,000 people, we&#39;d get,
what 50 cases, right?
Right.
So that&#39;s not very practical.
We need a large sample, and we need many years to do it.
Right.
Case-control sampling says, well, let&#39;s not do things
prospectively like that.
Let&#39;s rather find people who we already know have heart
disease or don&#39;t have heart disease and then sample them.
Now in the proportion in this case, we&#39;ll take 160 cases and
302 controls and then record their risk factors.
We start with cases and controls, and
we get lots of cases.
And we do this without waiting 20 years.
We can do it right now.
And then we record the risk factors.
That&#39;s a good point, [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
And that&#39;s very popular in epidemiology.
There are other issues involved with case-control
sampling, retrospective sampling.
Yeah.
We won&#39;t take that up now.
But that&#39;s the reason it&#39;s so popular.
On the same issue, in many modern data sets, we&#39;ll have
very imbalanced situations.
For example, if you&#39;re modelling the click-through
rate on an ad on a web page, the probability of someone
clicking is less than 1%, maybe 0.005 or even smaller,
0.001, which means if you just take a random sample of
subjects who&#39;ve been exposed to ads, you&#39;re going to get
very, very few 1&#39;s and a huge amount of 0&#39;s.
OK?
And these data sets get really large.
So the question is, do we need to use all of that 0, 1 data
to fit the models?
Well, from what we&#39;ve told you, no.
You can take a sample of the controls.
And this picture over here just gives an indication of
the trade-off.
The main point is that ultimately the variance of
your parameter estimates has to do with the number of cases
that you got, which is the smaller class.
And so what this plot shows is it&#39;s showing the variance of
the coefficients as a function of the case-control ratio, in
fact the control case ratio.
What it says is when you&#39;ve got about 5 or 6 to 1, the
variance kind of levels off here.
And so there&#39;s diminishing returns in
getting even more controls.
So if you&#39;ve got a very sparse situation, sample about 5 or 6
controls for every case, and now you can work with a much
more manageable data set.
So it&#39;s very handy, especially in modern
extremely large data sets.
Just a comment about what this case-control sampling is.
The most obvious way to study the risk factors for heart
disease would be to take a large group of people, maybe
1,000 or 100,000 people, follow them for maybe 20
years, record their risk factors, and see who gets
heart disease and who doesn&#39;t after 20 years.
If you&#39;re still around.
If we&#39;re still around.
Right.
Now that actually is a good way to do things, except it&#39;s
very expensive and it takes a long time.
You have to get a lot of people, and you have to wait
for many years.
Case-control sampling is a lot more attractive.
Because what you do is rather than taking people and
following them forward in time, you sample people who
you know have heart disease.
You also get a comparison sample of people who do not
have heart disease, the controls.
And then you record their risk factors.
So it&#39;s much cheaper, and it&#39;s much quicker to do.
And that&#39;s why case-control sampling is a very commonly
used technique in epidemiology.
OK.
What if we have more than two classes?
Can we still do logistic regression?
Well, we can.
It easy generalizes to more than two classes.
There&#39;s various ways of doing this.
And one version-- which actually is how we do it in
the glmnet package in R, which you&#39;ll will be
learning more about--
is we have this exponential form that we saw before but
modified for multiple classes.
So notice in the numerator we&#39;ve got an e
to the linear model.
And this is for the probability that Y is k given
X, a small k.
And we&#39;ve got, say, capital K classes, where capital K is
bigger than 2.
In the denominator, we&#39;ve just got the sum of those
exponentials for all the classes.
In this case, each class gets its own linear model.
And then we just weigh them against each other with this
exponential function, sometimes
called the softmax function.
OK?
The mathier students would recognize that some
cancellation is possible in this ratio.
And that&#39;s true.
What that means is actually you only need K minus 1 linear
functions, as you do in a 2-class logistic regression.
That&#39;s somewhat of a detail.
It turns out for our glmnet application this is a more
symmetric representation, and it&#39;s actually more useful.
This multiclass logistic regression is also referred to
as multinominal regression.