OK, so that was with a single variable, and usually when you
do classification, we&#39;ve got more than one variable.
So now we&#39;re going to go to multi-variant Gaussians.
So here&#39;s a picture of the Gaussian density when we&#39;ve
got two variables.
So it&#39;s one of these fancy-looking three
dimensional plots.
It&#39;s beautiful.
Beautiful, isn&#39;t it?
The height&#39;s color coded, could you make a plot like
this, [INAUDIBLE]?
I could try, and then you&#39;d criticize it.
You do criticize it.
The beautiful thing is that R made this plot with very
little work from us.
So there&#39;s two variables, x1 and x2, and you can see the
Gaussian density in two dimensions
looks like a bell function.
And this is-- left hand case is the case when two variables
are uncorrelated, so it&#39;s just really like a bell.
And the right hand case is when there&#39;s correlation, so
now it&#39;s like a stretched bell.
See there&#39;s positive correlation between x1 and x2.
So those are pictures of the densities.
The formula for the density doesn&#39;t look nearly as pretty,
and here it is over here.
And it&#39;s somewhat complex.
We should go over this in great detail.
Excruciating detail, please.
I have a feeling that&#39;s a hint not to go
into it in great detail.
Anyway, this is just a generalization of the formula
we had for a single variable.
This is called a covariance matrix, and if you stare at
this formula, and you stare at the previous formula, you will
see that they&#39;re somewhat similar.
Especially if you know a bit of vector algebra.
If you go through the simplifications, if you know
your linear algebra, you can to do and do the cancellation
similar to what we did before, you can the discriminant
function which is given over here.
And it looks complex, but important thing to note is
that it&#39;s, again, linear in x.
Here&#39;s x alone multiplied by a coefficient vector, and these
are all just constants.
So this, again, is a linear function.
If the math&#39;s beyond you, don&#39;t let it bother you.
This is a linear function, and we&#39;ll make that more clear a
little bit later on, as well, that
this is a linear function.
In fact, we make it clear right here.
It might look complex, but this can just be written in
this form over here.
It&#39;s a linear function.
So the ck0--
so this is a function for class k--
ck0 is built up of all these pieces over here.
And then each of the coefficients of x1, x2, up to
xp come from this part over here.
Remember, x is a vector in this case.
And so you can expand this expression and get
this term over here.
And I think I forgot to mention it before.
What the idea of the discriminant function is, you
compute one of these for each of the classes, and then you
classify it to the class for which it&#39;s largest.
You pick the discriminant function that&#39;s largest.
Well, we can draw other nice pictures for discriminant
analysis similar to the one-dimensional picture we
drew before.
So here, we&#39;ve got two variables and three classes.
And instead of showing those density plots, what we do is
show contours, in this case, of the density.
So here&#39;s the blue class.
And we show the contour of a particular level of
probability for the blue class, for the green class,
and for the orange class.
And lo and behold--
and the decision boundary is the dotted line here.
And it&#39;s really very pretty.
It shows you where you classify to blue versus
orange, and it&#39;s exactly where it cuts--
the line goes exactly through the points where the contours
are cut, both for the orange to blue, for the blue to
green, and for the green to orange.
And you can see they all meet in the middle over here, right
in the center over here.
And so if you knew the true densities, it
would tell you exactly--
and in this case, the Gaussian--
you get the exact decision boundaries.
Again, these are called the Bayes decision boundaries.
These are the true decision boundaries.
Now, of course, we don&#39;t.
But we go ahead and estimate the parameters for the
Gaussians in each of the class using formulas similar to what
we had before, but appropriate for this multivariate case.
So in this case, we&#39;ve got to get the mean for x1 and x2 for
the blue class--
it&#39;s about there-- for the green class, with data points
about there, for the orange class, say there.
And then we plug them into the formula.
Instead of getting the dotted lines, we get the solid lines.
And in this case, it&#39;s remarkably close.
Now, these data were actually generated from a Gaussian
distribution, so it&#39;s not too surprising that we got close.
But with relatively few points, we get decision
boundaries that look pretty close to the real ones.
You cannot learn about discriminant analysis without
seeing Fisher&#39;s iris data.
It&#39;s maybe one of the most famous datasets around.
It studies three species of iris.
These species are setosa, versicolor, and virginica, and
they&#39;re color-coded in a scatter plot matrix again,
with three colors in this case.
And the four variables that are going to be used to try
and automatically classify these three classes, sepal
length, sepal width, petal length, and petal width.
So these are aspects of the flower.
And there&#39;s 50 samples in each class.
Now, if you look at these scatter plots, you can see
that there&#39;s some really good separation.
For example, in this plot of petal length and petal width,
the blue class really stands out as being different from
the other two classes.
They seem to be more confused in some of the plots, and in
some, there&#39;s slightly more separation.
But the idea here is to use all of these variables
together to come up with a
discriminant rule and classify.
And so this was a motivating example that Fisher used in
his first description of linear discriminant analysis.
And in fact, it&#39;s often known as Fisher&#39;s linear
discriminant analysis.
Importantly, what comes with discriminant
analysis is a nice plot.
In this previous picture, there&#39;s four variables, so we
showed a scatter plot matrix of each
variable against the rest.
But it turns out that there&#39;s a single plot that captures
the classification information for all of them.
And here it is.
And I&#39;ve got discriminant variable one and discriminant
variable two as the horizontal and vertical axes.
And it turns out these are linear combinations of the
original variables.
But they&#39;re special linear combinations.
And when you plot the variables against these two,
you see really good separation.
And these arise from actually performing the linear
discriminant analysis.
Because you&#39;ve got three classes, what Fisher&#39;s linear
discriminant analysis is really doing--
or Gaussian LDA is really doing--
is it&#39;s measuring which centroid is the closest.
But it&#39;s measured in a distance that takes into
account the covariance of the variables.
But ignoring the covariance for a moment, the three
centroids actually line in a plane, a subspace of the
four-dimensional space.
And it&#39;s really distance.
So if you have three points, they span a
two-dimensional subspace.
And that&#39;s essentially what we plot in here, is the
So seeing which class is closest really amounts to
distance in that subspace.
And that leads to these nicely dimensional plots.
And so we have three classes here.
We can make a two-dimensional plot, and it captures exactly
what&#39;s important in terms of the classification.
And when we have more than three classes, we can still
find two-dimensional plots.
But in that case, it doesn&#39;t capture all the information,
the two-dimensional plot.
But you can find the base two-dimensional plot for
visualizing the discriminant rule.
And that&#39;s another important reason why linear discriminant
analysis is very popular for multi-class classification.
Keep in mind, this case, we only four features, four
variables, right?
Discriminant analysis was a very attractive method.
But imagine we had 4,000 features.
Then in [INAUDIBLE], what we just did was
the covariance matrix.
We had to plug in an estimate of the covariance matrix.
If you have 4,000 features, that covariance matrix would
be of size 4,000 by 4,000.
Yes, that&#39;s a great point, Rob.
And we just can&#39;t carry out discriminant analysis without
other modifications if the number of
variables are very large.
And we can talk about some ways of doing that.
And later on in the class, we&#39;ll talk
about it in more ways.
We&#39;ve talked about discriminant functions, which
is telling you how you classify.
But it turns out that you can turn these into probabilities
very easily.
And here&#39;s the expression over here.
And so remember we got the dks by doing a lot of
simplification.
Well, it turns out that those simplifications and
cancellations hold exactly for computing the probabilities.
So in other words, those expressions we had earlier for
computing the probabilities--
let&#39;s go back to it-- for example, here&#39;s an expression
here that&#39;s used for computing the probabilities.
Where is it?
This is the expression for the single variable case, with all
these constants in there.
All the cancellation happens, and we get to this nice simple
expression over here, which just involves the
discriminant functions.
So see, you can see if you can actually show that as well.
It&#39;s not that hard to show.
And so not only does discriminant analysis give us
a classified.
It also gives us the probabilities.
When K is 2, we&#39;ll classify to class two if these
probabilities are bigger than 0.5, else to class one, just
like in logistic regression.
Here&#39;s the credit data.
And we produce, in this case, misclassification table.
So this table, along the horizontal, it&#39;s
got the true status.
So it&#39;s a true default status, which is no or yes.
You can see we have 10,000 samples in the credit data.
And in the vertical, we&#39;ve got the predicted
status, no or yes.
So of course, we&#39;d like everything
to lie on the diagonal.
It turns out we got a lot of the no&#39;s right and not that
many of the yes&#39;s right.
So on the diagonal is what you got correct.
On the off diagonals is what you got incorrect.
Nevertheless, overall we make 2.75%
misclassification errors here.
So this is called a confusion matrix.
It tells how well you did.
Now, there&#39;s some caveats.
This is training error.
We fit the rule to these data, and now we see how well it
performs on these data.
So we may be over-fitting.
Well, we&#39;ve got 10,000 training samples here, and
we&#39;ve only fit a handful of parameters.
So it&#39;s very unlikely in this case that we&#39;re over-fitting.
For small training sets, that would be an issue, and you
would need to have a separate test set.
Another thing to note is that although 2.75% seems a really
goodness misclassification, right?
If we just use a very naive classification rule and say
always classify to the largest class-- in other words,
classify according to the prior--
we&#39;d only make 3.33% errors because there&#39;s a predominance
of no&#39;s in this dataset.
The total number of no&#39;s is 333 out of 10,000.
So this we call the null rate.
And so you always bear in mind the null rate when getting
excited about a misclassification error rate.
The other thing to look at, though, is you can break the
errors into different kinds.
So of the true no&#39;s, we make 0.02% errors.
So we hardly ever misclassify a no.
But of the yes&#39;s, we make a whopping 75.7% errors.
So the errors are very lopsided in this case.
And that&#39;s maybe not such a good idea.
So we break down these errors into finer categories.
So we call the false positive rate the fraction of negative
examples that are classified as positive.
So they&#39;re false positives.
In that case, that was the 0.02% in this case.
And the false negative rate, that&#39;s a fraction of positive
examples that are classified as negative,
75.7% in this case.
Now we produce the classification table by
intuitively correct classifying default as yes if
the probability of default was bigger than 0.5.
But it gave us this very lopsided false positive and
false negative rate.
In some cases, especially for these kinds of screen-in
examples, you may want to change the false positive and
false negative rates and skew them to one side or the other.
And you can do this by changing this threshold.
Instead of classifying--
in this case, to default if it&#39;s bigger than 0.5, you can
change the threshold and maybe make the threshold in this
case smaller so that you can catch more of the high risk
cases for default.
And so here we&#39;ve done it as a function of the threshold.
And we&#39;ve just looked at negative thresholds, or
decreasing thresholds.
And so in this plot, we&#39;ve got in black the
overall error rate.
In orange, we&#39;ve got the false positive rate, and in blue,
we&#39;ve got the false negative rate.
And so as we decrease the threshold, the false positive
rate increases because now we&#39;re going to classify more
and more negatives as positive.
But it increases very slowly, you&#39;ll see, for a long part of
the threshold going down, the decrease in threshold, the
false positive rate doesn&#39;t increase very fast.
Of course, the false negative rate increases as we do that.
And so even at 0.1, the false positive rate hasn&#39;t increased
a huge amount.
And the false negative hasn&#39;t increased a huge amount.
But we&#39;ve changed the balance of classification.
And so you can change the threshold.
Well, you can capture that change in threshold in what&#39;s
known as an ROC curve.
So what this shows is the two error rates, in this case,
false positive rate and true positive rate, as we change
the threshold.
And we&#39;d like the false positive rate to be low and
the true positive rate to be high.
And so this ROC curve traces out as
we change the threshold.
And the 45 degree line is the kind of no information line.
And what you&#39;d like is you&#39;d like this curve to be right up
as far as possible into the top left hand corner, so if
you had a true positive rate of one and a false positive
rate of zero.
If you flipped a coin, you&#39;d be on the straight line.
You&#39;d be on the straight line.
And so this is a single curve that sort of captures the
behavior of the classification rule for all possible
thresholds.
And you can compare different classifiers by comparing the
ROC curves.
And to summarize it even more, we sometimes use the area
under the curve, or AUC, which captures the extent to which
you&#39;re up in the northwest corner.
And higher AUC is good.