Hello, everyone.
We&#39;re going to continue now our discussion
of supervised learning.
Linear regression is the topic, and actually, as we&#39;ll
see, it&#39;s a very simple method.
But that&#39;s not a bad thing.
Simple&#39;s actually good.
As we&#39;ll see, it&#39;s very useful, and also the concepts
we learned in linear regression are useful for a
lot of the different topics in the course.
So this is chapter three of our book.
Let&#39;s look at the first slide.
As we say, linear regression is a simpler approach to
supervised learning that assumes the dependence of the
outcome, Y, on the predictors, X1 through Xp, is linear.
Now, let&#39;s look at that assumption.
So in this little cartoon example, the true regression
function is red.
And it&#39;s not linear, but it&#39;s pretty close to linear.
And the approximation in blue there, the blue line, it looks
like a pretty good approximation.
Especially if the noise around the true red curve, as we&#39;ll
see, is substantial, the regression curve in blue could
be quite a good approximation.
So although this model is very simple--
I think there&#39;s been sort of a tendency of people to think
simple is bad.
We want to use things that are complicated and fancy and
impressive.
Well, actually, I want to say the opposite.
Simple is actually very good.
And this model being very simple, it actually works
extremely well in a lot of situations.
And in addition, the concepts we learn in regression are
important for a lot of the other supervised learning
techniques in the course.
So it&#39;s important to start slowly, to learn the concepts
of the simple method, both for the method itself and for the
future methods in the course.
So what is the regression model?
Well, before I define the model, let&#39;s actually look at
the advertising data, which I&#39;ve got in the next slide.
This data looks at sales as a function of three kinds of
advertising, TV, radio, and newspaper.
And here I&#39;ve got scatter plots of the sales versus each
of the three predictors individually.
And you can see the approximations by the
regression line are pretty good.
Looks like, for the most part, they&#39;re reasonable
approximations.
On the left side, maybe for low TV advertising, the sales
are actually lower than expected,
which we can see here.
But for the most part, the linear approximation is
reasonable, partly because, again, the amount of noise
around the curve, around the line, is quite large.
So even the actual regression function was nonlinear, we
wouldn&#39;t be able to see it from this data.
So this is an example of how it&#39;s this crude approximation,
which is potentially quite useful.
So what are the questions we might ask of this kind of
data, and would you might ask the regression model to help
us to answer?
Well, one question is, is the relationship between the
budget of advertising and sales.
That&#39;s the sort of overall global question, is, do these
predictors have anything to say about the outcome?
Furthermore, how strong is that relationship?
The relationship might be there, but it might be so weak
as not to be useful.
Now, assuming there is a relationship, which media
contributed to sales?
Is it TV, radio, or newspaper, or maybe all of them?
If we want to use this model to predict, how well can we
predict future sales?
Is the relationship linear?
We just discussed that already.
If it&#39;s not linear, maybe if we use a nonlinear model,
we&#39;ll be able to make better predictions.
Is there synergy among the advertised media?
In other words, do the media work on their own in a certain
way, or do they work in combination?
And we&#39;ll talk about ways of looking at synergy later in
this section.
OK, well, what is linear regression?
Well, let&#39;s start with the simplest case, where a simple
model with just a single predictor.
And this is the model here.
It says that the outcome is just a linear function of the
single predictor, x, with noise, with errors,
[INAUDIBLE] epsilon.
So this is just the equation of a line.
We&#39;ve added some noise at the end to allow the points to
deviate from the line.
The parameters that the constants, beta 0 and beta one
are called parameters or coefficients.
They&#39;re unknown.
And we&#39;re going to find the best values to make the line
fit as well as possible.
So you see a lot terminology.
Those parameters are called the intercept and slope,
respectively, because they&#39;re the intercept and
slope of the line.
And again, we&#39;re going to find the best-fitting values to
find the line that best fits the data.
And we&#39;ll talk about that in the next slide.
But suppose we have for the moment some good values for
the slope and intercept.
Then we can predict the future values simply by plugging them
into the equation.
So if we have a value of x, we want it for
what you want to predict.
The x might be, for example, the advertising
you budget for TV.
And we have our coefficients that we&#39;ve estimated.
We simply plugged them into the equation, and our
prediction for future sales at that value of x is given by
this equation.
And you&#39;ll see throughout the course, as is standard in
statistics, we put a hat, this little symbol, over top of a
parameter to indicate the estimated value which we&#39;ve
estimated from data.
So that&#39;s a sort of funny way.
That&#39;s become a standard convention.
So how do we find the best values of the parameters?
Well, let&#39;s suppose we have the prediction for a given
value of the parameters at each value in the data set.
Then the residual, what&#39;s called the residual, is the
discrepancy between the actual outcome and
the predicted outcome.
So we define the residual sum of squares as the total square
discrepancy between the actual outcome and the fit.
The equivalent, if you write that out in detail, it looks
like this, right?
This is the error, the residual for the first
observation, square, second, et cetera.
So it makes sense to say, well, I want to choose the
values of these parameters, the intercept and slope, to
make that as small as possible.
In other words, I want the line to fit the points as
closely as possible.
Let&#39;s see.
This next slide--
I&#39;ll come back to the equation in the previous slide, but
this next slide shows in pictures.
So here are the points.
Each of these residuals is the distance of each
point from the line.
And I square up these distances.
I don&#39;t care if I&#39;m below or above.
I&#39;m not going to give any preference.
But I want the total score squared distance of all points
to the line to be as small as possible.
Because I want the line to be as close as
possible to the points.
This is called the least squares line.
There&#39;s a unique line that fits the best in this sense.
And the equations for the
slope-intercept are given here.
Here&#39;s the slope and the intercept.
So just basically a formula involving the observations for
the slope-intercept, and these [INAUDIBLE]
the least squares estimates.
These are the ones that minimize the sum of squares.
Of course, a computer program like R or pretty much any
other statistical program will compute that for you.
You don&#39;t need to do it by hand.
OK, so we have our data for a single predictor.
We&#39;ve obtained the least squares estimates.
Well, one question we want to know is how
precise are those estimates.
In particular, we want to know what?
We want to know, for example, is the slope 0?
If the slope is 0, that means there&#39;s no relationship
between y and x.
Suppose we obtained a slope of 0.5.
Is that bigger than 0 or not?
Well, we need a measure of precision.
How close is that actually to 0?
Maybe if we got a new dataset from the same population, we
get a slope of minus 0.1.
Then the 0.5 is not as impressive as it sounds.
So we need what&#39;s called the standard error for the slope
and intercept.
Well, here are the formulas for the standard errors of the
slope and intercept.
Here&#39;s the one we really care about.
This is the square standard error of the slope.
It&#39;s sigma squared, where sigma squared is the noise,
the variance of the errors around the line.
And this is interesting.
It says this is the spread of the x&#39;s around their mean.
This actually makes sense.
It says, the standard error of the slope is bigger if my
noise variance is bigger.
That makes sense.
The more noise around the line, the
less precise the slope.
This says the more spread out the x&#39;s, the more
precise the slope is.
And that actually makes sense.
I go back to this slide.
The more spread out these points are, the more I have
the slope pinned down.
Think of like a teeter totter.
Imagine I had the points, they were all actually concentrated
around 150.
Then this slope could vary a lot.
I could turn it, change the slope, and still fit the
points about the same.
But the more the points are spread out in x across the
horizontal axis, the better pinned down I have the slope,
the less slop it has to turn.
So this also says you have a choice of which observations
to measure.
And so maybe in an experiment where you can design, you
should pick your predictor values, the x&#39;s, as spread out
as possible in order to get the slopes estimated as
precisely as possible.
OK So that&#39;s the formula for the standard error of the
slope and for the intercept.
And what we do with these?
Well, one thing we can do is form what&#39;s
called confidence intervals.
So a confidence interval is defined as a range so that it
has a property that with high confidence, 95%, say, which is
the number that we&#39;ll pick, that that range contains the
true value with that confidence.
In other words, to be specific, if you want a
confidence interval of 95%, we take the estimate of our slope
plus or minus twice the estimate of
the standard error.
And this, if errors are normally distributed, which we
typically assume, approximately, this will
contain the true value, the true slope,
with probability 0.95.
OK, so what we get from that is a confidence interval,
which is a lower point and an upper point, which contains
the true value with probability 0.95 under
repeated sampling.
Now, what does that mean?
[INAUDIBLE] a little tricky to interpret that.
Let&#39;s see in a little more detail what
that actually means.
Let&#39;s think of a true value of beta, beta one, which might be
0 in particular, which means the slope is 0.
And now let&#39;s draw a line at beta one.
Now imagine that we draw a dataset like the one we drew,
and we get a confidence interval from this formula,
and that conference interval looks like this.
So this one contains a true value because they&#39;ve got the
line is in between in the bracket.
Now I get a second dataset from the same population, and
I form this confidence interval from that dataset.
It looks a little different, but it also
contains a true value.
Now I get a third data set, and I do the least squares
computation.
I form the confidence interval.
Unluckily, it doesn&#39;t contain the true value.
It&#39;s sitting over here.
It&#39;s above beta one.
Beta one&#39;s below the whole interval.
And I get another dataset.
Maybe I miss it on the other side this time.
And I get another dataset, and I contain the true value.
So we can imagine doing this experiment many, many times,
each time getting a new dataset from the population,
doing least squares computation, and forming the
confidence interval.
And what the theory tells us is that if I form, say, 100
confidence intervals, 100 of these brackets, 95% of the
time, they will contain the true value.
The other 5% of the time, they will not
contain the true value.
So I can be pretty sure that the interval contains the true
value if I form the confidence interval in this way.
I can be sure at probability 0.95.
So for the advertising data, the confidence interval for
beta one is 0.042 to 0.053.
This is for TV sales.
So this tells me that the true slope for TV advertising is--
first of all, it&#39;s greater than 0.
In other words, having TV advertising does have a
positive effect on sales, as one would expect.
OK, so that completes our discussion of standard errors
and confidence intervals.
In the next segment, we&#39;ll talk about hypothesis testing,
which is a closely related idea to confidence intervals.