OK, here we have a session in R, in R Studio in fact, and
we&#39;re going to see how we fit the logistic regression models
using the GLM functions in R. So what we first begin to do
is load the ISLR package, which has all the datasets
we&#39;re going to use.
Here we use the command require, which
is similar to library.
I tend to use require.
It&#39;s sort of more evocative, what we&#39;re doing.
And so we just click through in R Studio, and the Smarket
dataset&#39;s there, and we can query it.
So names is useful for seeing what&#39;s on the data frame, and
summary is also useful.
Summary gives you a simple summary of each of the
variables on the Smarket data frame.
And we see that there&#39;s a number of lags, and there&#39;s
volume, and there&#39;s today&#39;s price, and there&#39;s direction,
which we&#39;re going to use as a response, and that is whether
the market went up or down since the previous day.
And we can also do help on these data objects and get
some details of each of the variables.
And so there you see the description.
So we&#39;re going to use the direction as a response and
see if we can predict it as a binary response using logistic
regression.
Let&#39;s make a plot of our data.
So there&#39;s the pairs function.
And we do it, it&#39;s a little bit crowded in this plot.
We told it to plot the variables in Smarket.
And we told it to use as the color indicator, actually our
binary response.
And that&#39;s a useful way, when you&#39;ve got a two-class
variable for seeing in the plots which are members of
each class.
And here we see them.
Doesn&#39;t seem to be too much correlation going on here.
Of course, the class variable is derived from the variable
today, and so up or down seems to make a division.
And other than that, we don&#39;t see much going on.
Of course, with stock market data, you don&#39;t expect to see
much going on.
Because if things were very easy to predict, people would
be making lots of money from it, and they wouldn&#39;t be
giving lectures on using R.
So here we have a call to GLM, glm.fit.
We tell it direction is the response, and the predictors,
we&#39;re going to use the lag variables, so that yesterday&#39;s
price, previous day&#39;s price, and so on, up to lag5.
And we&#39;ll also use volume, and we tell it to use family
equals binomial.
And so that tells GLM to put fit a logistic regression
model instead of one of the many other models that can be
fit to the GLM.
So we execute that fit.
And oops.
I skipped a line here.
So there we go.
And there, it&#39;s done.
That&#39;s two lines there.
And then we do a summary, and the summary tells you some
things about the fit.
And in this case, it&#39;s giving you p values on each of the
coefficients.
It estimated coefficients, their standard errors, the
z-score, and the p value.
And it seems like none of the coefficients
are significant here.
Again, not a big surprise for these kinds of data.
It doesn&#39;t necessarily mean it won&#39;t be able to make any kind
of reasonable predictions.
It just means that possibly these variables are very
correlated.
Actually, the plot doesn&#39;t suggest that.
Anyway, none are significant.
And it gives the null deviance, which is the
deviance just for the mean.
So that&#39;s the log likelihood if you just use the mean
model, and then the deviance for the model with all the
predictors in, that&#39;s the residual deviance.
And there was a very modest change in deviance.
It looks like four units on how many degrees of freedom.
We got six degrees of freedom difference in degrees of
freedom there.
OK, so we can make predictions from the fitted model.
And so we assign to glm.probs the predict of glm.fit, and we
tell it type equals response.
So this will make predictions on the training data that we
use to fit the model.
And it gives you a vector of fitted probabilities.
We can look at the first five, and we see that they&#39;re very
close to 50%, which is, again, not too surprising.
We don&#39;t expect to get strong predictions in this case.
So this is a prediction of whether the market&#39;s going to
be up or down based on the lags and the other predictors.
We can turn those probabilities into
classifications by thresholding at 0.5.
And so we do that by using the if/else command.
So if/else takes effect, in this case, glm.probs, in fact,
a vector of logicals.
So glm.probs bigger than 0.5.
So that&#39;ll be a vector of trues and falses.
And then if/else says that, element by element, if it&#39;s
true, you&#39;re going to call it up.
Otherwise, you&#39;re going to call it down.
And so that does that for us.
And now we&#39;re going to look at our performance.
And it&#39;s convenient to actually attach the data frame
market so that the variables are available by
name, which we do.
And now we can make a table of glm.pred, which is our ups and
downs from our prediction, against the true direction.
So we do that.
And we get a table, and we see there&#39;s lots of elements on
the off diagonals.
On the diagonals is where we do correct classification, and
on the off diagonals is where we make mistakes.
And we see there&#39;s quite a lot of those.
And we can actually get our mean classification
performance.
So that&#39;s cases where glm.pred is equal to the direction.
And we just take the mean of those, so it&#39;ll give you a
proportion, in this case, 0.52.
So on the training data, we do slightly better than chance.
Well, we may have overfit on the training data.
So what we&#39;re going to do now is divide our data up into a
training and test set.
So what we&#39;ll do is we&#39;ll make a vector of logicals.
And what it is is train is equal to year less than 2005.
For all those observations for which year is less than 2005,
we&#39;ll get a true.
Otherwise, we&#39;ll get a false.
And now we refit our glm.fit, except we say
subset equals train.
And so it will use any those observations for
which train is true.
So now that means we fit just to the data in
years less than 2005.
And now, when we come to predict, we&#39;re going to
predict on the remaining data, which is
years 2005 or greater.
And so we use the predict function again.
And for the new data, we give it Smarket, but
index by not trained.
So that&#39;s going to be--
not trained is going to be true if year is 2005 or more.
And we tell it type equals response, so we actually want
to predict the probabilities in this case.
And again, we make this if/else, make
this up/down variable.
And let&#39;s make a subset, a new variable, direction.2005,
again, for the test data, which is the response
variable, direction, which is just for our test data.
In other words, not trained.
So we call it direction.2005.
And now we make a table.
So now this is on test data.
A smaller subset of the data is test.
And we compute our mean again, and it&#39;s 0.48.
So now we actually get slightly less than 50%.
So we&#39;re doing worse than the null rate, which is 50%.
So what are we going to do?
Well, we might be overfitting.
And that&#39;s why we&#39;re doing worse on the test data.
So now we&#39;re going to fit a smaller model.
So we&#39;re going to just use lag1 and lag2 and leave out
all the other variables.
And so here we do that.
The rest of it calls the same.
And then we run through our commands again, we compute our
table, and here we get a correct classification of just
about 56%, which is not too bad at all.
And so using the smaller model, it appears to have done
better here.
And if we do a summary of that guy, let&#39;s see if anything
became significant by using the smaller model, given that
it gave us better predictions.
And of course, that&#39;s what happens when you try and do
commands on the--
type on the fly, at least for me, you
make spelling mistakes.
Well, nothing became significant, but at least the
prediction of performance appeared to have increased.
So that&#39;s fitting logistic regression models in R using
the GLM function and family equals binomial.