OK, so we just talked about cross-validation, which is an
important technique for both regression classification for
getting an idea of test error and for assessing how complex
a model to fit.
For example, how many features to include in a model or the
order of the polynomial.
And it&#39;s a very important technique.
And sometimes with important techniques like this, it&#39;s a
good idea to see how one might do it wrong.
And this is actually an area that we&#39;ve seen people--
a way in which people use cross-validation
in the wrong fashion.
Which can have actually very serious consequences.
Especially these days, when you get very wide data sets.
And this next example is going to show you such a case.
So we&#39;ll go into detail of how one could do it wrong, and how
people use it wrong.
And we&#39;ll try to avoid that error, and help you to avoid
that error.
So let&#39;s think of a simple thought experiment.
We&#39;ve got 5,000 predictors, for example, and 50 samples.
This is, again, a more and more commonly occurring case,
we have more predictors than samples.
And we have two classes we&#39;re trying to predict.
OK?
And suppose we did the following.
We built a simple classifier in the following way.
First of all we filtered the predictors, find the 100
predictors having the largest correlation on their own with
the class labels.
So we&#39;re going to cherry pick here.
We pick the top 100 predictors.
Keep them--
and again, they&#39;re chosen on the basis of their correlation
with the class labels on their own.
And we throw away the remaining 4,900 predictors.
And then we use 100 predictors, we use them in a
classifier such as a [INAUDIBLE] model using only
these 100 predictors.
And we omit the other 4,900.
So that&#39;s not unreasonable with building a classifier.
For example, maybe we don&#39;t have to deal with 5,000
predictors.
We just want a small number of them.
The question we address here is, how do we get an idea of
the test set error of this classifier?
Cross-validation.
OK, thank you.
But how?
What&#39;s tempting is to say, well, let&#39;s just forget the
fact that we filtered the predictors in step one.
That we chose the 100 best among the 5,000.
Let&#39;s just pretend like we started in step two.
That we started with the 100 predictors, and
that was our data.
Can we apply cross-validation in step two,
forgetting about step one?
Well, no.
This is a serious error.
Why is it an error?
Well, the problem is that the procedure of the classifier
has already seen the labels of the training data in step one.
In choosing the best 100 predictors, it&#39;s looked at all
the labels of all the samples.
So the predictors have already used the full set of
observations in the fitting when we chose those
predictors.
So that&#39;s a form of training.
And we can&#39;t ignore it in the validation process.
The point is, we&#39;re not allowed to just start in step
two and ignore the fact that we applied step one.
Why is that?
Well, this is something you should try yourself.
You can simulate data with class labels having no
correlation with the outcome.
So [INAUDIBLE]
class, the true test error is 50%.
But cross-validation, if we ignore step one will give you
an error rate of 0.
So it&#39;s a serious, serious bias.
Cross-validation is telling you your classifier is
perfect, when in fact your classifier is the same as
flipping a coin.
Think about why this happens.
It will make the point more clearly if we increase the
5,000 to maybe 5 million predictors.
Suppose we have 5 million predictors and 50 samples.
And again, there&#39;s no correlation in the population
between the predictors and the class labels.
We go ahead and we pick the best 100 among those 5 million
predictors.
We&#39;re going to find some very good-looking predictors.
Despite the fact in the population no predictor has
correlation with the outcome.
In the data, if we look at the best among 5 million, we&#39;re
going to find some very good predictors that look in the
data like they have a lot of power for classifying.
If we then pretend like those were the predictors we started
with, those 100 cherry picked out of 5 million, they&#39;re
going to look very good to cross-validation.
So we fooled cross-validation by leaving out the first
filtering step and giving it a very cherry-picked set of
predictors in the second step.
This seems like it was done on purpose here, but actually in
some genomic studies researchers are faced with
tens of thousands of genes, maybe.
And it&#39;s just hard to handle them.
So they do some kind of screening in the beginning
just to reduce the number of variables down to
a manageable set.
And then forget about it afterwards, but that leads to
this kind of bias.
As I said earlier, I think it&#39;s good to understand this
by actually trying this yourself.
In [INAUDIBLE] you&#39;ve learned some [INAUDIBLE] now, you can
simulate a situation just like this where the true
test error is 50%.
And simulate a large number of predictors.
And apply cross-validation in step two.
And you&#39;ll see the error is actually very low.
You can see the error is low.
And as Trevor mentioned, this is not something we made up.
This is actually an error which commonly occurs in
genomics in published papers and high profile journals.
So we told you the wrong way to do things, applying
cross-validation in step two.
The right way is to apply
cross-validation to both steps.
The next few pictures will make this clear.
Here I&#39;ve got the wrong way I just described.
So I&#39;ve got my samples here and my predictors here.
And now in this first approach, we first select the
best set of predictors based on the correlation with the
outcome, that&#39;s over here.
And we keep these predictors and throw the rest away.
And now in step two, we&#39;re going to apply
cross-validation.
What does that mean?
We divide the data up into, say, five parts.
We apply our classifier to four parts.
And we predict the response in the [INAUDIBLE] part.
So again, this is wrong because the filtering step
which selected these predictors has used the
response [INAUDIBLE] for all the samples.
So this is the wrong way to do things.
The right way is as follows.
We first define our folds, five folds cross-validation.
Before we do any fitting, we remove one of the folds.
All the data for that fold, the predictors and the
response variable.
And now we can do whatever we want on the other four parts.
We can filter and fit however we want.
When we&#39;ve finished our fitting, we then take the
model and we predict the response for the [INAUDIBLE]
part.
Key point being, though, that we form the folds before we
filter or fit to the data.
So that we&#39;re applying cross-validation to the entire
process, not just the second step.
So that&#39;s the right way to do it.
So in each of the 4/5ths folds, we might screen off a
different set of predictors each time.
And we probably will.
And so that variability is going to get taken into
account here.
So this wrong way of doing cross-validation is not
something that we&#39;ve made up.
It&#39;s actually something which I mentioned occurs in a lot of
published papers.
I&#39;ve actually experienced it a number of times myself.
A few years ago I was at a Ph.D. oral in engineering here
at Stanford.
And a lot of people engineering are doing
statistics as part of their work.
This particular student was trying to predict heart
disease from SNPs.
SNPs are single-base changes in the genome.
So basically had a classification problem with I
think about 100,000 predictors and to a class response.
We get done something very much like this.
He had so many predictors he wanted to filter them.
So he applied a filtering of some sort to the data set to
reduce the 100,000 predictors I think down to 1,000.
And then he fit some sort of a model to the 1,000 predictors.
And he got an error rate of about 35%, I think.
Which doesn&#39;t sound that impressive, but for this
particular area it was actually
quite a low error rate.
And during the oral, he presented this.
And I said, actually, I think there&#39;s a problem with this.
And I pointed out the point you&#39;ve just seen.
That he actually had filtered the data--
oh, sorry, I didn&#39;t say--
[INAUDIBLE] detail.
He had applied cross-validation
in the second step.
So he had filtered the data down to 1,000 predictors.
He applied cross-validation.
And the cross-validation error rate was about 35%.
And he was quite happy, and this was part of this
presentation.
And I mentioned, well, that doesn&#39;t look right to me.
Because you have done cross-validation wrong in the
way I just described.
He didn&#39;t agree, and his supervisor didn&#39;t even agree.
I will not name the person.
Wasn&#39;t me.
Wasn&#39;t you.
The supervisor said, well, maybe you&#39;re right.
But you&#39;re really being picky, you&#39;re splitting hairs here.
It&#39;s not going to make much difference.
And I said, well, I think it might make a difference.
You really have to go back and do it.
So a few months later, the student knocked
on my door, my office.
Did he pass?
He did pass, because he had other things in the thesis
which were reasonable.
But a few months later, he knocked on my door, came to my
office, said I redid the experiment.
And the error rate is now 50%.
He was quite surprised, and a bit upset.
But basically, it was I told you so.
That with a large number of predictors, if you filter them
you&#39;ve got to include that in your cross-validation.
And if you don&#39;t, you can incur a serious error in your
cross-validation estimate.
So that was again, it happens, and Trevor and I talk about
this a lot.
And other people have written papers about this error.
But people continue to make this error in
cross-validation.
So that&#39;s a big heads up.
And of course, another heads up is not [INAUDIBLE].
OK, so that completes our discussion of
cross-validation.
We spent quite a bit of time on that topic, because it&#39;s a
very important technique for all the methods we&#39;ll see in
this course.
In the next session we&#39;ll talk about a closely related idea,
but a different one, called the bootstrap.