OK, so we&#39;ve seen a variety of different models, from linear
models, which are rather simple and easy to work with
and interpret, to more complex models like nearest neighbor
average and thin plate splines.
And we need to know how to decide amongst these models.
And so we need a way of assessing model accuracy, and
when is a model adequate?
And when may we improve it?
OK, so suppose we have a model, f hat of x, that&#39;s been
put through some training data.
And we&#39;ll denote the training data by Tr.
And that consists of n data pairs, xi yi.
And remember, the notation of xi means the i-th observation,
and x may be a vector.
So it may have a bunch of components.
yi is typically a single y, a scalar.
And we want to see how well this model performs.
Well, we could compute the average squared prediction
error over the training data.
So that means we take our y, observe y.
We subtract from it f hat of x.
We square the difference to get rid of the sign.
And we just average those over all the training data.
Well, as you may imagine, this may be biased towards more
overfit models.
We saw with that thin plate spline, we could fit the
training data exactly.
We could make this means squared error sub train, we
could make it zero.
Instead, we should, if possible, compute it using a
fresh test data set, which we&#39;ll call Te.
So that&#39;s an additional, say, m data pairs xi yi different
from the training set.
And then we compute the similar quantity, which we&#39;ll
call mean squared error sub Te.
And that may be a better reflection of the performance
of our model.
OK, so now I&#39;m going to show you some examples.
We got back to one dimensional function fitting.
In the left hand panel, we see the black curve, which is
actually simulated.
So it&#39;s a generating curve.
That&#39;s the true function that we want to estimate.
The points are data points, generated from
that curve with error.
And then we actually see--
you have to look carefully in the plot-- we see three
different models fit to these data.
There&#39;s the orange model, the blue model,
and the green model.
And they&#39;re ordered in complexity.
The orange model is a linear model.
The blue model is a more flexible model, maybe some
kind of spline, one dimensional version of the
thin plate spline.
And then the green one is a much more
flexible version of that.
You can see it gets closer to the data.
Now since this is a simulated example, we can compute the
mean squared error on a very large population of test data.
And so in the right hand plot, we plot the mean squared error
for this large population of test data.
And that&#39;s the red curve.
And you&#39;ll notice that it starts off high for the very
rigid model.
It drops down and becomes quite low for
the in between model.
But then for the more flexible model, it
starts increasing again.
Of course, the mean squared error on the training data--
that&#39;s the grey curve--
just keeps on decreasing.
Because the more flexible the model, the closer it gets to
the data point.
But for the mean squared error on the test data, we can see
there&#39;s a magic point, which is the point at which it
minimizes the mean squared error.
And in this case, that&#39;s this point over here.
And it turns out it&#39;s pretty much spot on for the medium
flexible model in this figure.
And if you look closely at the plot, you will see that the
blue curve actually gets fairly close
to the black curve.
OK.
Again, because this is a simulation model, the
horizontal dotted line is the mean squared error that the
true function makes for data from this population.
And of course, that is the irreducible error, which we
call the variance of epsilon.
Here&#39;s another example of the same kind.
But here, the two functions are actually very smooth.
Same setup.
Well, now we see that the mean squared error, the linear
model does pretty well.
The best model is not much different
from the linear model.
And the wiggly one, of course, is overfitting again and so
it&#39;s making big prediction errors.
The training arrow, again, keeps on going down.
And finally, here&#39;s quite a wiggly true
function on the left.
The linear model does a really lousy job.
The most flexible model does about the best.
The blue model and the green model are pretty good, pretty
close together, in terms of the mean squared
error on the test data.
So I think this drums home the point.
Again, the training mean squared error just keeps on
going down.
So this drums home the point that if we want to have a
model that has good prediction error--
and that&#39;s measured here in terms of mean squared
prediction error on the test data--
we&#39;d like to be able to estimate this curve.
And one way you can do that, the red curve.
You can do that is to have a hold our test data set, that
you can value the performance of your different models on
the test data set.
And we&#39;re going to talk about ways of doing this later on in
the course.
I want to tell you about one aspect of this, which is
called a bias-variance trade-off.
So again, we&#39;ve got a f hat of x, which is fit to the
training data.
And let&#39;s say x0 y0 is a test observation drawn from the
population.
And we&#39;re going to evaluate the model at the single test
observation, OK?
And let&#39;s supposed the true model is given by the function
f again, where f is the regression function or the
conditional expectation in the population.
So let&#39;s look at the expected prediction error
between f hat at x 0.
So that&#39;s the predicted model.
The fitted model on the training data evaluated at the
new point x 0.
And see what the expected distance is from the test
point, y 0.
So this expectation averages over the variability of the
new y 0, as well as the variability that went into the
training set used to build f hat.
So it turns out that we can break this.
We can break up this expression into
three pieces exactly.
The one piece is again the irreducible error that comes
from the random variation in the new test point, y 0, about
the true function f.
But these other two pieces break up the reducible part of
the error, what we called the reducible part before, into
two components.
One is called the variance of f hat.
And that&#39;s the variance that comes from having different
trainings sets.
If I got a new training set and I fit my model again, I&#39;d
have a different function f hat.
But if I were to look at many, many different training sets,
there would be variability in my prediction at x 0.
And then, a quantity called the bias of f hat.
And what the bias is is the difference between the average
prediction at x 0 averaged over all these different
training sets, and the truth f of x 0.
And what you have is, typically as the flexibility
of f hat increases, its variance increases.
Because it&#39;s going after the individual training set that
you&#39;ve provided, which will of course be different from the
next training set.
But its bias decreases.
So choosing the flexibility based on average test error
amounts to what we call a bias-variance trade-off.
This will come up a lot in future parts of the course.
For those three examples, we see the
bias-variance trade-off.
Again, in this part the red curve is the mean squared
error on the test data.
And then below it, we have the two components of that mean
squared error, the two important components, which
are the bias and the variance.
And in the left plot, we&#39;ve got the bias decreasing and
then flattening off as we get more flexible, and the
variance increasing.
And when you add those two components, you get the
u-shaped curve.
And in the middle and last plots that correspond to the
other two examples, the same decomposition is given.
And because the nature of their problem changed, the
trade-off is changing.
OK, so we&#39;ve seen now that choosing the amount of
flexibility of a model amounts to a bias-variance trade-off.
And depending on the problem, we might want to make the
trade-off in a different place.
And we can use the validation set or left out data to help
us make that choice.
But that&#39;s the choice that needs to be made
to select the model.
Now, we&#39;ve been addressing this in terms
of regression problems.
In the next segment, we&#39;re going to see how all this
works for classification problems.