OK, here we are going to see situations where our nearest
neighbor averaging doesn&#39;t work so well.
And we&#39;re going to have to the find ways to deal with that.
Nearest neighbor averaging, which is the one we just saw,
can be pretty good for small p, small numbers or variables.
Here we had just one variable.
But small, maybe p less than or equal to 4 and largeish N.
Large N so that we have enough points in each neighbor to
average to give us our estimate.
Now this is just one version of a whole class of techniques
called smoothers.
And we&#39;re going to discuss later on in this course much
cleverer ways of doing this kind of averaging such as
kernel and spline smoothing.
Now there&#39;s a problem though.
Nearest neighbor methods can be really
lousy when P is large.
And the reason has got the name the curse of
dimensionality.
What it boils down to is that nearest neighbors tend to be
far away in high dimensions.
So and that creates a problem.
We need to get a reasonable fraction of the N values of yi
to average to bring the variance down.
So we need to average the number of points in each
neighborhood so that our estimate has got a nice,
reasonably small variance.
And let&#39;s suppose we want 10% of the data points to be in
each interval.
The problem is that 10% neighborhood in high
dimensions need no longer be local.
So we loose the spirit of estimating the conditional
expectation by local averaging.
So let&#39;s look at a little example of that.
In the left panel, we&#39;ve got values of two
variables, X1 and X2.
And they are actually uniformly distributed in this
little cube with edges minus 1 to plus 1, minus 1 to plus 1.
And we form two 10% neighborhoods in this case.
The first neighborhood is just involving the variable X1,
ignoring X2.
And so that&#39;s indicated by the vertical dotted lines.
Our target point is at 0.
And so we spread out a neighborhood to the left and
right until we capture 10% of the data points with respect
to the variable X1.
And the dotted line indicates the width of the neighborhood.
Alternatively, if we want to find a neighborhood in two
dimensions, we spread out a circle centered at the target
point, which is the red dot there, until we&#39;ve captured
10% of the points.
Now notice the radius of the circle in two dimensions is
much bigger than the radius of the circle in one dimension
which is just the width between
these two dotted lines.
And so to capture 10% of the points in two dimensions, we
have to go out further and so we are less local than we are
in one dimension.
And so we can take this example further.
And on the right hand plot, I&#39;ve shown you how far you
have to go out in one, two, three, five, and 10
dimensions.
In 10 dimensions, these are different versions of this
problem as the dimensions get higher In order to capture a
certain fraction of the volume.
OK, and so take, for example, 10% or 0.1
fraction of the volume.
So for p equals 1, if the data is uniform, you roughly go out
10% of the distance.
In two dimensions, we store you went more.
Look what happens in five dimensions.
In five dimensions, you have to go out to about 0.9 on each
coordinate axes to get 10% of the data.
That&#39;s just about the whole radius of this sphere.
And in 10 dimensions, you actually have to go break out
of this sphere in order to get points in the corner to
capture the 10%.
So the bottom line here is it&#39;s really hard to find new
neighborhoods in high dimensions and stay local.
If this problem didn&#39;t exist, we would use the near neighbor
averaging as the sole basis for doing estimation.
So how do we deal with this?
Well, we introduce structure to our models.
And so the simplest structural model is a linear model.
And so here we have an example of a linear model.
We&#39;ve got p features.
It&#39;s just got p plus 1 parameters.
And it says the function of X, we can
approximate by a linear function.
So there&#39;s a coefficient on each of
the X&#39;s and at intercept.
So that&#39;s one of the simplest structural models.
We can estimate the parameters of the model by fitting the
model to training data.
And we&#39;ll be talking more about how you do that.
And when we use such a structural model, and, of
course, this structural model is going to avoid the curse of
dimensionality.
Because it&#39;s not relying on any local properties and
nearest neighbor averaging.
That&#39;s just fitting quite a rigid model to all the data.
Now a linear model is almost never correct.
But it often serves as a good approximation, an interpretive
approximation to the unknown true function f of X. So
here&#39;s our same little example data set.
And we can see in the top plot, a linear model gives a
reasonable fit to the data, not perfect.
In the bottom plot, we&#39;ve augmented our linear model.
And we&#39;ve included a quadratic term.
So we put in our X, and we put in an X squared as well.
And we see that fits the data much better.
It&#39;s also a linear model.
But it&#39;s linear in some transformed values of X. And
notice now we&#39;ve put hats on each of the parameters,
suggesting they&#39;ve been estimated, in this case, from
this training data.
These little hats indicate that they&#39;ve been estimated
from the training data.
So those are two parametric models, structured models that
seem to do a good job in this case.
Here&#39;s a two dimensional example.
Again, seniority, years of education, and income.
And this is simulated data.
And so the blue surface is actually showing you the true
function from which the data was simulated with errors.
We can see the errors aren&#39;t big.
Each of those data points comes from a particular pair
of years of education and seniority with some error.
And the little line segments in the data points
show you the error.
OK.
so we can write that as income as a function of education and
seniority plus some error.
So this is with truth.
We actually know this in this case.
And here is a linear regression model fit to those
simulation data.
So it&#39;s an approximation.
It captures the important elements of the relationship
but doesn&#39;t capture everything.
OK.
It&#39;s got three parameters.
Here&#39;s a more flexible regression model.
We&#39;ve actually fit this using a technique
called thin plate splines.
And that&#39;s a nice smooth version of a
two dimensional smoother.
It&#39;s different from nearest neighbor averaging.
It&#39;s got some nicer properties.
And you can see, this does a pretty good job.
If we go back to the generating data and the
generating surface, this thin plate spline actually captures
more of the essence of what&#39;s going on there.
And for thin plate splines, we&#39;re going to talk about them
later in Chapter 7.
There&#39;s a tuning parameter that controls how smooth the
surfaces is.
Here&#39;s an example of a thin plate spline.
We basically tuned the parameter all
the way down to 0.
And this surface actually goes through
every single data point.
In this case, that&#39;s overfitting.
the data.
We expect to have some errors.
Because with true function generate
data points with errors.
So this is known as overfitting.
We are overfitting the training data.
So this is an example where we&#39;ve got a family of
functions, and we&#39;ve got a way of controlling the complexity.
So there&#39;s some trade offs when building models.
One trade off is prediction accuracy versus
interpretability.
So linear models are easy to interpret.
We&#39;ve just got a few parameters.
Thin plate splines are not.
They give you a whole surface back.
And if given a surface back in 10 dimensions, it&#39;s hard to
understand what it&#39;s actually telling you.
We can have a good fit versus over-fit or under-fit.
So in this previous example, the middle one was a good
fit.The linear was slightly under-fit.
And the last one was over-fit.
So how do we know when the fit is just right?
We need to be able to select amongst those.
Parsimony versus black-box.
Parsimony means having a model that&#39;s simpler and can be
transmitted with a small number of parameters and
explained in a simple fashion, involved, maybe, in a subset
of the predictors.
And so those models if they do as well as say a black-box
predictor, like the thin plate spline was somewhat of a
black-box predictor.
We&#39;d prefer the simpler model.
Here&#39;s a little schematic which shows a variety of the
methods that we are going to be discussing in this course.
And they are ordered by interpretability and
flexibility.
And at the top, there are two versions of linear regression,
subset selection and lasso, which we&#39;ll talk about, that
actually even think the linear regression models too complex
and try and reduce it by throwing
out some of the variables.
Linear models and least squares.
Slightly more flexible, but you loose some
interpretability because now all the
variables are thrown in.
Then we have generalize additive models which allow
for transformations in an automatic way
of each of the variables.
And then at the high flexibility, low
interoperability, and bagging, boosting, and
support vector machines.
We&#39;ll discuss all these techniques but
later on in the course.
OK, so we covered linear regression.
And we covered nearest neighbor averaging.
And we talked about ways, places where that&#39;s
not going to work.
And so we&#39;ve briefly introduced a number of other
different methods.
And they are all listed on the screen, different methods that
they can use to solve the problem when the dimensions
are high and when linearity doesn&#39;t work.
But we have to choose amongst these methods.
And so we need to develop ways of making those choices.
And that&#39;s what we&#39;re going to cover in the next segment.