So let&#39;s look again in the simple case when we&#39;ve got one
variable, one x.
Again, we&#39;re going to get a bit more math-y now.
This is the form, the mathematical form, of the
Gaussian density function for class k when you&#39;ve
got a single x.
So there&#39;s some constants over here.
The important part that depends on x is in this
exponential form over here.
And we see there is a mu sub-k, which is the mean for
the observations in class k, or the population
meaning class k.
And sigma sub-k is the variance for that
variable in class k.
Now, in the first instance, we can assume that the variance,
sigma sub-k, is actually just sigma, the same
in each of the classes.
Now, that&#39;s a convenience.
It turns out this is an important convenience.
And it&#39;s going to determine whether the discriminant
function that we get, the discriminant analysis, gives
us linear functions or quadratic functions.
So, if we could plug into Bayes&#39; formula, the formula we
had two slides back, we get a rather complicated expression.
So we&#39;ve just plugged in a form of the
density in the numerator.
And there&#39;s the sum of the classes in the denominator.
And it looks pretty nasty.
Well, luckily there&#39;s some simplifications and
cancellations.
Now, we get this, because to classify an observation to a
class, we don&#39;t need to initially evaluate the
probabilities.
We just need to see which is the largest.
So if we take logs--
whenever you see exponentials the first thing you want to do
is take the logs.
And if you discard terms that do not depend on k, that
amounts to doing a lot of cancellation of terms that
don&#39;t count.
This is equivalent to assigning to the class with
the largest discriminant score.
And so that complicated expression boils down to a
much simpler expression of here.
And notice it involves x, a single variable in this case.
And then it involves the mean and variance for the
distribution.
And it involves the prior.
And importantly, in this case, this is a
linear function of x.
So there&#39;s a single coefficient for x.
There&#39;s a constant.
And then there&#39;s a constant term, which consists of these
two pieces over here.
And so we get one of those functions
for each of the classes.
If there are two classes, you can simplify even further.
And let&#39;s suppose now that the probability of class one is
equal to the probability of class two, which is 0.05.
Then you can see, in this case, that the decision
boundary is exactly at mu1 plus mu2 over 2.
So it&#39;s back to this picture.
In the previous slide, in this case, the priors were equal.
These are actually two Gaussian distributions.
And the decision boundary here is at zero.
In this case, the two means were exactly the equal amount
on the opposite side of zero.
So the average is at zero.
So intuitively, that&#39;s the right value for the decision
boundary, which is the point at which we classify to one
class, the boundary at which we switch from classifying to
one class versus the other.
It&#39;s not that hard to show.
So see if you can show that.
You basically use this expression for each of the two
classes and look to see when the one is
bigger than the other.
It&#39;s not that hard to do.
I&#39;m confused.
There was a square term in the previous expression.
And it&#39;s gone.
Oh, Rob, are you causing trouble here again?
I was hoping to avoid that nasty bit.
Rob&#39;s right.
If you expand out this squared term here, there&#39;s going to be
an x squared.
But, you know, there&#39;s an x squared in the numerator.
And there&#39;s x squareds in each of the terms in the
denominator.
And there&#39;s no coefficients in front of that x squared that&#39;s
specific to a class.
So that&#39;s one of the things that cancel out in this ratio.
You knew that, didn&#39;t you, Rob?
Rob knew that.
All right, this is with populations.
What happens if we have data?
We can&#39;t draw nice density functions like
we&#39;ve done over here.
But we just estimate them.
So here&#39;s a picture where we&#39;ve actually got data.
So we&#39;ve drawn histograms instead of density functions.
Now, what we do is we actually need to estimate, for the
Gaussian rule, the means, and the two populations, and the
common standard deviation.
Well, in this case, the true means are minus 1.5 and 1.5,
which means the average mean is zero.
And the probabilities were 0.05.
But we don&#39;t know these.
So we&#39;re going to estimate them from the observed data
and then plug them into the rule.
So this is how we estimate them.
The priors, we need to estimate them.
So that&#39;s just the number in each class divided by their
total number.
That&#39;s obvious.
The means in each class, we just compute the sample mean
in each of the classes.
This is a tricky little notation here.
This is one over nk, that&#39;s the number in class k.
And this is the sum over i such that yi is equal to k.
So yi is recording the class label.
So this will just sum those xi&#39;s that are in class k.
And clearly that&#39;s the right thing to do to
get the sample mean.
The sigma squared is a little trickier.
We&#39;re assuming that the variance is the same in each
of the classes.
And so this is a formula, it&#39;s called a
pooled variance estimate.
So we subtract from each xi the mean for its class.
So this is what we do if we were computing the
variance in class k.
But we sum all those square differences.
And we sum them over all the classes and then divide
it by n minus k.
So if that doesn&#39;t make too much sense, another way of
writing that is in this form over here, which says we
estimate the sample variance separately
in each of the classes.
And then we average them using this formula over here.
So this is just like a weight on each of those variances.
And that weight is to do with how many observations were in
that class relative to the total number of observations.
And then the minus 1 and the minus k, that&#39;s a detail.
And it&#39;s to do with how many parameters we&#39;ve estimated for
each of these estimates.
It&#39;s one parameter.
It&#39;s a mean.
[SNORING]
Rob&#39;s falling asleep.
Sorry.
Too much detail, Rob?
Exactly.
Way too much detail, OK.
So there we have it.
Those are the formulas.
You plug those back in, you&#39;ll now get
estimated decision boundary.
And instead of being exactly zero, it&#39;s, in this case,
slightly to the left of zero, but pretty close.