We&#39;re now going to start our discussion of multiple linear
regression, which is regression with
more than one predictor.
I should say the term
&quot;regression&quot; is kind of unusual.
You might be wondering, why linear regression?
It&#39;s a linear model.
And this actually is an unusual term.
It&#39;s actually historical.
It comes from the idea of regression towards the mean,
which is a concept which was discussed in the early 1900s.
You might want to look that up yourself and later on in the
course we&#39;ll describe what regression
towards the mean is.
But it&#39;s resulted in a sort of unusual name for a linear
model called linear regression.
But we have to live with this term because
it&#39;s become time honored.
So multiple linear regression now extends the simple model
to we have more than one predictor.
Like in our example, we have three predictors.
So we want to fit them all together and use them all
together to predict the outcome.
So here&#39;s the model.
We have an overall intercept term, and then we have a slope
for each of the predictors in the model.
Which again, the betas or the parameters, they&#39;re unknown.
And the x&#39;s are observed.
And we&#39;re trying to use the x&#39;s to predict y.
So in the advertising example we particularly will have the
three predictors TV, radio, and newspaper advertising.
And we&#39;re going to try to predict sales.
And we have the error term along points to deviate around
the function.
And now the function actually is a--
it&#39;s called a hyperplane.
Let&#39;s actually flip a head to slide 19 for a moment where I
have a picture of this.
So whereas before we had a line, now it&#39;s a hyperplane.
So I&#39;ve been able to draw it here just for two predictors.
It&#39;s hard to draw it for three.
But now the line is now replaced by this flat surface
called a plane or hyperplane.
So here&#39;s our data points.
For each point we have its two predictor values, let&#39;s say TV
and newspaper.
And we have its sales on the vertical axis.
And here&#39;s each data point is a red point.
What multiple aggression does, it fits a hyperplane, a plane
to these points to minimize the square distance between
each point and the closest point on the plane.
Very intuitive.
The same way we did it for a line, now the
line becomes a plane.
So let&#39;s now go back to the.
So the model, again.
So it&#39;s an equation of hyperplane with its
coefficients.
Well, before we talk about the least squares estimates and
some of the details, let&#39;s step back for a moment and
think about how you might interpret the regression
coefficients.
Because now there&#39;s more than one of them.
In a simple model we had only one to deal with.
Now we have a multiple, say three coefficients.
How do we interpret them together?
Well, if the predictors had no correlation in the data, then
we could talk about each coefficient separately.
We can make statements like, a unit change in xj, for
example, is associated with a beta j change-- that&#39;s its
coefficient--
in the outcome.
With all the other variables fixed.
But predictors are not usually uncorrelated in the data.
For example, here we can expect--
and we&#39;ll see it actually--
that the various amounts spent on the three kinds of
advertising are correlated.
So these kind of interpretations are difficult
in observational data where they&#39;re correlated.
What problem does the correlation cause?
Well, the variance of all coefficients tend to increase,
sometimes dramatically.
In particular, imagine we have two predictors which are
almost identical.
Then we can&#39;t really separate their coefficients, right?
If I have a coefficient on one variable I could just as soon
move that coefficient to the other variable.
And the fit of the model is going to be
pretty much the same.
So the variance of the coefficients of those two
predictors are going to be very large.
And then interpretation becomes difficult when there&#39;s
a correlation.
Because one can&#39;t really say, suppose I were to change xj.
And we can think about, suppose I was to increase the
TV advertising by a certain amount.
What would be the effect on sales?
Well if that happened, we probably wouldn&#39;t be
reasonable to assume that the other advertising
budgets stay the same.
For example, maybe the company has a fixed budget overall.
So that if I increase TV advertising I&#39;d have to
decrease the other advertising.
Or maybe TV advertising is increasing just because that
company has more money in general and decides it wants
to spend more on advertising of all kinds.
So in both those cases we can&#39;t really talk about the
change of one predictor where the other one&#39;s fixed.
Because the predictors will tend to move
together in real data.
And what this means is claims of
causality should be avoided.
We can&#39;t really say that one predictor causes the outcome
when there&#39;s predictors in the system that are correlated
with that given predictor.
So this becomes a complicated challenge to
try to discuss causality.
And we&#39;re going to avoid that.
And there&#39;s a nice book which actually when I was a graduate
student it was one of the books I learned from, Data
Analysis and Regression by Mosteller and Tukey, two very
famous statisticians.
And I look at the book now and I don&#39;t like the book that
much overall.
But there&#39;s one wonderful chapter called the woes of
regression coefficients that talks about the problems of
interpreting regression coefficients in a multiple
regression model.
That&#39;s a very useful chapter to read.
And I&#39;ve made this point.
So the first point here I&#39;ve just made it, a regression
coefficient what it measures is the change in y per unit
change in xj with all other predictors held fixed.
But this is not usually a reflection of reality.
Because usually when you change one predictor the
others change as well.
I mentioned the example with advertising.
So here&#39;s couple of examples which I&#39;ll just
have you think about.
And maybe we&#39;ll put it on a quiz.
But here&#39;s an example, the first example, to have you
think about this point.
Suppose I measure the total amount of
change in your pocket.
That&#39;s y.
I also measure two predictors, the number of coins and the
number of pennies, nickels, and dimes.
That&#39;s x2.
Now by itself, the regression coefficient of y on the total
number of pennies, nickels, and dimes will probably be
positive, right?
The more you have of these, the more likely the you have
more change.
But what about if I have x1 in the model?
So for a given level of x1, think about whether the
coefficient of x2 will be positive or negative.
And talk about the answer to this later on.
But that&#39;s a simple example where you can see now how the
presence of one predictor affects the way that we think
about and interpret the
coefficient of another predictor.
And of course, these two predictors are highly
correlated by construction.
Another example, which is actually from a chapter in
this book, from American football.
y is the number of tackles by a football player in a season.
w and h are his height and weight.
And they imagine that they take data from this situation,
they fit a regression model, and they obtain beta zero.
But the coefficient of weight is 0.50.
Coefficient of height is minus 0.10, which seems to say that
it&#39;s better to be short to make more tackles.
So the question we&#39;re asking here is, how would you
interpret this coefficient of height given the
weights in the model?
And again, think about this and we&#39;ll return
to the answer later.
And they also mention in that same book, there&#39;s two quotes
essentially by George Box who was another famous
statistician.
Essentially all models are wrong but some are useful.
This is interesting.
Because it&#39;s true that, as we saw like on the very first
slide, the regression model, a linear model, is
never exactly right.
But it&#39;s often very useful.
So it&#39;s important to remember that the model that you assume
is not to take it too seriously.
Test out your model.
Remember that it&#39;s going to be wrong.
But also remember the fact that, despite the fact it&#39;s an
approximation, it can be a very useful approximation in
many situations.
And then this point in their chapter, also paraphrasing
George Box, which really sort of sums up what I talked about
during [INAUDIBLE] coefficients, the only way to
find what will happen when a complex system is disturbed is
to disturb the system, not merely
to observe it passively.
In other words, if you want to make a causal statement about
a predictor for an outcome, you actually have to be able
to take the system and perturb that particular predictor
keeping the other ones fixed.
That will allow you to make a causal statement about a
variable like xj and its effect on the outcome.
It&#39;s not good enough simply to observe some observations from
the system.
We can&#39;t use that data to conclude causality.
So if you want to know what happens when a complex system
is perturbed, you have to perturb it.
You can&#39;t simply observe it.
So I think that&#39;s a very wise summary of the use of models
and observational data.
So how do we find the least squares estimates for the
multiple regression model?
Well, t&#39;s really very much the same, the same tack we took
for the simple model.
So first of all, our predictions will be given by
this equation.
This is the intercept.
And now we have one slope parameter for each predictor.
We put hats on there, as we always will when we infer that
value from data, the estimates.
And now what&#39;s called the multiple least squares
estimates are the values that minimize the sum of square
deviations of points around the plane.
Let&#39;s go--
remember, I showed this picture.
Here&#39;s my data points, here&#39;s my approximating
least squares plane.
And I&#39;m going to choose the orientation and height of this
plane to minimize the total squared distance between the
red points and the closest point on the hyperplane.
Those are called the least squares estimates.
They&#39;re called the multiple least squares estimates
because there&#39;s multiple predictors.
There&#39;s is a formula for these
coefficients, for the estimates.
It&#39;s kind of messy.
And it&#39;s not something that anyone ever computes by hand.
Although probably in the early 1960s people use to do these.
Poor guys used to actually compute least squares
estimates by hand.
They were good at doing matrix computations.
But today we have the luxury of fast computers.
And in a program like R or any other statistical package, we
can compute the least squares estimates for very big data
sets very quickly.
So we don&#39;t need to worry about the formula.
We just need to know what we&#39;re doing, which is we&#39;re
finding the values of the coefficients that minimize the
sum of squares.
So here&#39;s what we get for the advertising data.
The top table are the coefficients,
standard errors et cetera.
So these are the least squares estimates.
Again, there&#39;s a lot of terminology here.
Coefficient or parameter, we&#39;ll use those
interchangeably as people do.
The intercept.
Again, we&#39;re not typically interested in the intercept.
Because that&#39;s just telling us whether setting the other
three predictors to 0, whether the sales is the
average sales value.
So we don&#39;t really care about that.
But we care about the slopes, which are these guys.
These three values here.
So we see, for example, the coefficient of TV is 0.46.
Standard error, the t statistic is the ratio, 0.46
divided by 0.0014.
And the t statistic, remember I said a t statistic of bigger
than about 2 is significant at p value of 0.5.
So the p value of 32 is huge.
And p value is less than 0.0001.
Similarly for radio.
Very big effect.
Newspaper.
Newspaper looks like it&#39;s not having much effect.
Its t statistic is minus 0.18, which has got a p
value which is large.
And p values close to one--
p values above 0.05 or 0.1 are not significant.
They&#39;re not evidence against the null hypothesis, which is
that the coefficient is 0.
But let&#39;s be a little more careful how we interpret this.
Remember, each of these statements is made conditional
on the other two being in the model.
So in particular, this coefficient says, given I have
the amount of money spent on radio and newspaper, spending
money on TV still produces a change in sales.
So in the presence of the other two
predictors, TV is important.
Similarly for radio.
The presence of TV and radio advertising--
excuse me, TV and newspaper advertising, radio advertising
can be effective.
But newspaper is not, in the presence of these two.
So in particular, on its own newspaper may be significant,
its coefficient may be significant.
But in the presence of the other two, in the multiple
model, it&#39;s not showing significance.
And we can look at the correlations actually here.
Here are the simple correlations between the
predictors.
And we see there&#39;s some significant correlations.
For example, TV and sales--
well, sales is the outcome.
But in particular, radio and newspaper have a
correlation of 0.35.
So what&#39;s likely happened here is that any effect of
newspaper has been soaked up by radio because they&#39;re
correlated at 0.35.
So with radio in the model, newspaper&#39;s no longer needed.
It doesn&#39;t tell us anything more.
It doesn&#39;t improve the prediction given we&#39;ve
measured the radio advertising.
And that&#39;s because of the correlation being 0.35.
And the other hand, it looks like TV and radio were pretty
uncoordinated.
And their effects are somewhat complimentary.
So that completes our discussion of this example, in
the next segment we&#39;ll talk about some important questions
that arise when you use regression
for real data analysis.