OK, so we&#39;re back.
Some more discussion of the bootstrap--
we saw an example of the bootstrap with the
investments.
And now, in general, we&#39;re going to talk about the
bootstrap and think about it in more complex situations.
So here&#39;s a schematic, which I think is
very useful, actually.
It&#39;s due to David Friedman at Berkeley.
It&#39;s the real world bootstrap worldview of the bootstrap.
So on the left, we have a cloud.
And the ingredients we&#39;re imagining-- there&#39;s a real
population that gives our data, which I&#39;m calling
genetically Z, observations Z1 through Zn.
So these are like our training data?
Right, that&#39;s our training data.
For example, in the investment example we just saw, this
training data was a set of investments x, y--
x1, y1 to xn, yn.
All right, but we&#39;re going to call each of these pairs a Z,
Z1 through Zn.
So we imagined in that situation that we have our
training data from a population of investments.
This is in the real world.
We have a training sample.
And from that training sample, we derive a
statistic, an estimate.
In that particular case, it was the alpha hat, which is
the optimal proportion of investments for x.
So this is a summary, in a sense, of what we did in the
investment example for our training data.
And what we wanted to get was an idea of the standard error
of alpha hat.
Now, we made the point earlier that ideally, if we had access
to the population, we could get more training data.
We could simply grab more samples of training data from
the population, more investments from the possible
population investments.
You mean like a new sample, the same size?
Yeah, exactly, a new sample--
and from the new sample, do the same analysis, get an
estimate alpha hat, and do that many times.
And we showed how you could do that on the computer in the
previous example.
But we made the point that not often can you actually do that
in practice.
Because you don&#39;t have access to the population.
You can&#39;t get more training data, typically.
What you have to work with is just your
given training example.
So a way of thinking of the bootstrap in the abstract is
to say, well, we don&#39;t have access to the population.
Let&#39;s replace the population, which we don&#39;t have, by P hat,
which in the bootstrap&#39;s case is the training sample itself.
It&#39;s a population that puts probability 1 over n, n being
the sample size, on each of the training points.
So it says, our guess for the population--
which we don&#39;t have access to but we have
from a training sample--
is we have no more information.
We&#39;re going to say with equal probability, a training point
can come from the first point we saw, the second point we
saw, up to the nth point we saw.
So that&#39;s what we&#39;ll call P hat--
the empirical distribution function.
That&#39;s another name for that--
empirical distribution function.
So when you draw from this empirical distribution
function, that is sampling with replacement.
And that&#39;s what the bootstrap does, right?
It samples--
we saw that we draw samples with replacement from the
training sample.
That&#39;s this random sampling here--
P hat giving Z star.
This is now the bootstrap sample.
Remember, we&#39;re going to use a superscript star to indicate a
bootstrap sample as distinct from a training sample, which
has no superscript.
So this is one bootstrap draw.
It&#39;s the sample of size n from our training sample now, our
bootstrap sample, giving us the bootstrap data.
And from that, we derive the estimate.
Again, in this case, it&#39;s alpha.
And we&#39;ll call it alpha hat star.
So bootstrap sampling simply repeats this operation a few
hundred times, say.
For each time, we get a bootstrap sample of size n,
and we get a bootstrap quantity alpha hat star.
And then, the standard error of alpha hat star is the
bootstrap estimate of standard error of alpha hat.
Since there&#39;s nothing new here, we&#39;re simply describing
what we already saw in more general terms, OK?
But we can now think about how we carry this out in more
complex situations.
So in general, we need to figure out how we can carry
out bootstrap sampling.
For example, suppose we have a time series.
So let&#39;s draw the time axis here.
And we have a series, like for example stock price.
And let&#39;s just draw some imaginary data, all right?
So this is--
let&#39;s call it y1.
This is stock price at time one, stock price at
time two, et cetera.
And we want, for example, to predict the stock price for a
given day from the previous day&#39;s stock price.
So we&#39;ll fit a model, a regression model like we&#39;ve
seen, to each stock price as a function of the stock price on
the previous day.
Well, that&#39;s fine.
We can do that by least squares.
But now, we might imagine doing bootstrap sampling like
the way we just described where we sample with
replacement from the data.
Well, one problem with that that&#39;s a significant problem
is that the data are not independent, right?
There&#39;s correlation in the time series.
We expect the stock price for a given day to be correlated
with the stock price from the previous day.
As a matter of fact, if we&#39;re trying to predict the stock
price from a given day from the previous day, we hope
there&#39;s correlation.
If they were independent, the prediction
wouldn&#39;t be very useful.
But this creates a problem for the bootstrap.
Because in the schematic, we were sampling here where we
assumed that the sampling was IID from the population.
But in this situation, that&#39;s not a reasonable assumption.
Because the observations are not independent.
So in general, when you set up the bootstrap and arrange for
the sampling, you must figure out what parts of the data are
independent.
So one thing people do in a time series--
because the observations are not independent-- to correlate
across time is to use what&#39;s called the block bootstrap.
The block bootstrap divides the data up into blocks.
And between blocks, one assumes that things are
independent.
Oops, my spelling&#39;s not good.
OK, so for example, if we use a block size
of three, we might--
these would be the first block, these three
observations.
These three would be the second block.
These would be the next block.
And now our sampling units are not individual observations.
But they&#39;re entire blocks.
So we would sample with replacement from all the
blocks and then paste them together
into a new time series.
In other words, if this guy&#39;s sampled, he might become the
first block, second block, et cetera.
And then, we paste them together in order.
And that becomes the bootstrap sample to which we apply the
estimate-- in this case, a regression model.
So the point is you have to sample the things that are
uncorrelated.
You have to arrange for--
find the parts of the data that are uncorrelated and use
that as a basis for bootstrap sampling.
In this case, we use a block of size three under the
assumption that beyond a time lag of three, things are
somewhat uncorrelated.
But within a block, we expect correlation.
So we keep the blocks intact and sample them as units.
That&#39;s called the block bootstrap.
I say that here, OK?
So we talked about the bootstrap for standard errors.
The main use of the bootstrap is to estimate the standard
errors of an estimate like the alpha hat in
our investment example.
Another very common use of the bootstrap is
for confidence interval.
So let&#39;s go back to confidence interval for our parameters.
Let&#39;s go back to slide 29.
And remember, this is the histogram we got from the
bootstrap for the values of alpha hat over bootstrap
sampling, 1,000 bootstrap samples.
And if you look at this histogram, a reasonable way to
derive a confidence interval is to take the percentiles
from this histogram.
Suppose I want a 0.9 confidence interval so that it
contains a true value with probability 90%.
It makes sense to grab the fifth and
95th percent quantiles.
In other words, find the 5% point of this histogram and
the 95% point of that histogram.
There&#39;s 1,000 points here.
So actually, the 5% point would be the 50th biggest and
9/50 biggest value of alpha.
You mean smallest and biggest.
Did I say that wrong?
You said it wrong.
I&#39;m sure they understood, just like I did.
OK, so if we do that, that provides a confidence
interval for alpha.
And what do we actually get?
I&#39;ve got that back on the slide.
It&#39;s that, so 0.43 and 0.72.
So this is actually an appropriate confidence
interval for alpha.
And remember how to interpret this confidence interval.
What this means is that if we were to repeat this experiment
from the population many times, it would be the case
that the confidence interval that we obtain would contain
the true value of alpha 90% of the time.
That&#39;s what a 90% confidence interval is.
We talked about that earlier.
This particular way of constructing intervals is
called a bootstrap percentile interval.
And there&#39;s actually an entire field in statistics to do with
confidence intervals in the bootstrap.
And there&#39;s many, many, many papers and books that have
been written about this topic.
This bootstrap percentile interval is the simplest way
of constructing a confidence interval from the bootstrap.
And it&#39;s very useful.
We just use the histogram of bootstrap values themselves,
and use their percentiles.
So we&#39;ve talked about the bootstrap for standard errors
and confidence intervals.
How about prediction error like misclassification error
that we&#39;ve seen in the course already?
Well, the major tool we talked about for that was
cross-validation.
And let&#39;s think back on
cross-validation, how it worked.
We have K folds in K fold cross-validation.
We divide the data up into K parts, let&#39;s say five.
And I&#39;ll just draw this again.
Remember, what we did is our five parts created at random K
fold cross-validation is like, remember, a five act
play if K is 5.
At one stage of the play, these four are the training
set, these four parts.
And the remaining fifth part is the validations part, set.
And cross-validation fits to the four parts, fits a model,
and then uses that model to predict the fifth part.
And then, in turn, this guy gets to play the role of the
validation set in the next stage, and
this guy, et cetera.
And this is five stages.
But a crucial part of cross-validation was that when
we do one stage like this, there&#39;s no overlap between the
training set and the validation set.
In other words, the observations in one do not
appear in the other.
And that&#39;s important, because we&#39;re trying to get an idea of
test set error on new data.
So cross-validation is taking a piece of data, separating it
out from the training set so that when I fit on this data,
predicted on this data, this data is, in a sense, new.
It hasn&#39;t been seen by the model train on the first four.
So there&#39;s a separation, a clean separation, between
training and validation.
Well, what if we were to try to use the bootstrap to
estimate prediction error?
Let&#39;s just draw in the bootstrap sampling process.
Here&#39;s my training set.
And I&#39;m going to draw samples with replacement from the
training set, bootstrap samples, each one of the same
size, and a few hundred them.
Well, the first kind of obvious idea is to say, well,
let&#39;s train on a bootstrap data set and then predict the
original training set as my validation set.
I can do that for each bootstrap sample.
Each bootstrap sample gets to play the role of the training
set to fit.
And then, I&#39;m going to predict my original training sample as
my validation set.
Well, there&#39;s a big problem with that.
And the problem is there&#39;s an overlap between the bootstrap
data sets and the original data set.
In particular, about 2/3 of the original data points
appear in each bootstrap sample.
And you should think about how to prove this.
It&#39;s not hard, but you&#39;ll find out that about 2/3 of these
points, so the training set points, are in
the bootstrap sample.
This creates a problem, because now when I train here
and I do the prediction of a training set, 2/3 of the
points in this training set have already
been seen by the model.
Because they&#39;re in the bootstrap data set.
So on average, this 2/3 overlap means that most of the
training points are not novel.
So this is a big problem, because the prediction error
from this process will be biased downward.
It&#39;ll be a lot lower than the actual prediction error,
because 2/3 of the points I&#39;m predicting I&#39;ve already seen
in the bootstrap data set.
So this is not a good way of estimating prediction error.
OK, I say that it underestimates the true
prediction error quite dramatically.
Now, you can think about it the other way around.
You could train on the training set and use the
bootstrap samples as the validations sets.
And that&#39;s even worse.
And you can think about why that is.
So it&#39;s even worse in the sense that it&#39;s going to be
even more biased.
Well, how do you fix this problem?
You can fix it by, when you train on the bootstrap sample
and then predict the training sample, just recording the
predictions for the points that did not occur in the
bootstrap sample-- in other words, the points that are
actually novel points.
But then, this gets complicated.
And in the end, it&#39;s really not worth it.
If you push this idea to its conclusion, you can get
something which is about as good as cross-validation.
But it&#39;s much more complicated.
So our view is for this particular problem,
cross-validation is easier, and better, and
the thing we recommend.
If I can just interrupt, Rob--
that actually brings up an interesting point.
A lot of the time, we have simple methods like
cross-validation.
And then, a new method comes along like using bootstrap to
estimate prediction error.
And we see it&#39;s quite a lot more complicated.
And you don&#39;t get much in return.
And so our general philosophy is if you can get the job done
with a simple method, it&#39;s far better than using a more
complicated method just because it maybe
looks sexy or whatever.
So keep it simple-- that&#39;s the idea.