Hi.
I&#39;m Trevor Hastie.
And I&#39;m Rob Tibshirani.
Cut.
I&#39;m not--
And then you say, welcome to the course [INAUDIBLE].
Hi, I&#39;m Trevor Hastie.
And I&#39;m Rob--
Cut.
[LAUGHING]
Hi, I&#39;m Trevor.
No, I&#39;m Rob Tibshirani.
And I&#39;m Trevor Hastie.
And welcome to our course on statistical learning.
It&#39;s the first online course we&#39;ve ever given.
And we&#39;re excited to tell you about it.
And a little nervous, as you can hear.
So by way of background, what is statistical learning?
Trevor and I are both statisticians.
We were actually graduate students here at
Stanford in the &#39;80s.
We&#39;ve known each other for about 30 years.
Oh, my goodness.
And back then, well, we did applied statistics, like a lot
of statisticians did.
Statistics has been around since about 1900 or before.
But in the 1980s, people in computer science developed the
field of machine learning.
Especially, neural networks became a very hot topic.
I was at University of Toronto, and
Trevor was at Bell Labs.
And one of the first neural networks was developed at Bell
Labs to solve the ZIP code recognition problem, which
we&#39;ll show you a little bit about in a few slides.
So around that time, Trevor and I and then some
colleagues, Jerry Friedman, Brad Efron--
[? Neil Bryman ?]
And actually, you&#39;ll hear from Jerry and Brad,
both in this course.
We have some interviews with them.
About that time, we started to work on the area of machine
learning and sort of developed our own view of it, which is
now called statistical learning.
So along with colleagues here at Stanford and other places,
we developed this field of statistical learning.
So in this course, we&#39;ll talk to you about some of the
developments in this area and give lots of examples.
So let&#39;s start with our first example, which is a computer
program playing Jeopardy called Watson that IBM built.
And it beat the players in a three game match.
And the people at IBM who developed the system said it
was really a triumph of machine learning.
There were a lot of very smart technology, both hardware, but
also the software and the algorithms were based on
machine learning.
So this was a watershed moment, I think, for the area
of artificial intelligence and machine learning.
Google is a big user of data and a big analyzer of data.
And here&#39;s a quote that came in the New York Times in 2009
from Hal Varian, who&#39;s the Chief Economist at Google.
You can see the quote there. &quot;I keep saying that the sexy
job in the next 10 years will be statisticians.&quot;
And indeed, there&#39;s a picture of Carrie Grimes, who was a
graduate from Stanford Statistics.
She was one of the first statisticians hired at Google.
Now Google has many statisticians.
Our next example-- this is a picture of Nate
Silver on the right.
Nate has a masters in economics, but he calls
himself a statistician.
And he writes-- at least he did write a blog called
FiveThirtyEight for the New York Times.
And in that blog, he predicted the outcome of the 2012
Presidential and Senate elections very well.
As a matter of fact, he got all the Senate races right.
And the Presidential election, he predicted very accurately
using statistics, using carefully sampled data from
various places, some careful analysis.
He did an extremely accurate job of predicting the election
when a lot of news outlets weren&#39;t sure
who&#39;s going to win.
Pretty nerdy looking guy, isn&#39;t he, Rob?
Yes.
But he&#39;s really famous.
And--
He&#39;s like a rock star these days.
Yes.
We joke about--
when you&#39;re a statistician, when you go to a party and
someone says, what do you do?
When you say, I&#39;m a statistician,
they run for the door.
But nowadays, we can say, well, we do machine learning.
And well, they still run for the door.
But they take a little longer to get there.
In fact, we now call ourselves data scientists.
It&#39;s a trendier word.
So we&#39;re going to run through a number of statistical
learning problems.
You can see there&#39;s a bunch of examples on this page.
And we&#39;ll go through them one by one, just to give you a
flavor of what sort of problems we&#39;re going to be
thinking about.
So the first data set we&#39;re going to look at is on
prostate cancer.
This is a relatively small data set, 97 men, sampled from
97 men with prostate cancer actually by a Stanford
physician, Doctor Stamey, in the late &#39;80s.
And what we have is the PSA measurement for each subject,
along with a number of clinical and blood
measurements from the patients.
Some measurements are on the cancer itself and some
measurements from the blood, the measurements to do with
cancer size and the severity of the cancer.
And this is a scatter plot matrix, which
actually shows the data.
And you see on the diagonal is the name
of each of the variables.
And each little plot is a pair of variable.
So you get in one picture, if you&#39;ve got a relatively small
number of variables, you can see all the data at once in a
picture like this.
And you can see the nature of the data, what variables are
correlated and so on.
And so this is a good way of getting a view of your data.
And in this particular case, the goal was to try and
predict the PSA from the other measurements.
So it&#39;s along the top.
And you can see there&#39;s some correlations between these
measurements.
This is actually another view of these data which looks
rather similar except in one instance over here, which is--
this is the log weight.
These variables are on the log scale.
And this is log weight.
And you notice there&#39;s a point over here.
It looks like somewhat of an outlier.
Well, it turns out on the log scale, it looks
a bit like an outlier.
But when you look on the normal scale, it&#39;s enormous.
And basically, that was a typo.
And that would say--
if that was a real measurement, it would say that
this particular patient would have a 449 gram prostate.
Well, we got a message from a retired urologist, Doctor
Steven Link, who pointed this out to us.
And so we corrected an earlier published version of this
scatter plot.
Which is a good thing to remember.
The first thing to do when you get a set of data for analysis
is not to run it through a fancy algorithm.
Make some graphs, some plots.
Look at the data.
I think in the old days before computers, people did that
much more because it was easier.
I mean, you do it by hand.
And your analysis took many, many hours.
So people would look first at the data much more.
And we need to remember that, that even with big data, you
should look at it first before you jump in with an analysis.
So the next example is phonemes for two vowel sounds.
And this is looking at-- this graph has the log periodograms
for two different phonemes, the power at different
frequencies for two different phonemes, AA and AO.
How do you pronounce those, Trevor?
AA is odd, and AO is ought.
So as you can tell, Trevor talks funny.
But hopefully, during the course, you&#39;ll be able to--
Well, how can you say it, then?
Odd and ought?
OK.
So you see the log periodograms at various
frequencies of these two vowel sounds as spoken by different
people, the orange and the green.
And the goal here is to try to classify the two vowel sounds
based on the power at different frequencies.
So on the bottom, we see a logit model&#39;s been fit to the
data, looking at trying to classify the two classes from
each other based on the power of different frequencies.
The logit model&#39;s from logistic regression, which is
used to classify into one of the two vowel sounds, based on
the log periodogram.
And we&#39;ll cover it in detail in the course.
And the coefficients, the estimated coefficients from
the logistical model are in the gray profiles here in the
bottom plot.
And you can see, they&#39;re very non-smooth.
You&#39;d be hard pressed to tell where the important
frequencies were.
But when you apply a kind of smoothing, which we&#39;ll also
discuss in the course--
we use the fact that the nearby frequencies should be
similar, which the gray did not exploit.
We get the red curve.
And the red curve shows you pretty clearly that the
important frequencies--
looks like the one vowel sound&#39;s got more power around
25, and the other vowel sound has more power
around just before 50.
Predict whether someone will have a heart attack on the
basis of demographic, diet, and clinical measurements.
So these are some data on actually
men from South Africa.
The red ones are those that had heart disease, and the
blue points are those that didn&#39;t.
It&#39;s a case controlled sample.
So all the heart attack cases were taken as cases, and a
sample of the controls remained.
And the idea was to understand the risk
factors in heart disease.
Now when you have a binary response like this, you can
color the scatter plot matrix so you can see the points,
which is rather handy.
And these data come from a region of South Africa where
the risk of heart disease is very high.
It&#39;s over 5% for this age group.
The people, especially men around there, eat lots of--
these were men.
They eat lots of meat.
They have meat for all three meals.
And in fact, meat&#39;s so prevalent, chickens regard it
as a vegetable.
Poor chicken.
Rob loves that joke.
I used to love that joke.
OK.
So again, you can see there&#39;s correlations in these data.
And the goal here is to fit a model that jointly involves
all these different risk factors in coming up with a
risk model for heart disease, which in this case, is as I
said, colored in red.
Our next example is email spam detection.
As everyone uses email, and spam is definitely a problem,
so spam filters are a very important application of
statistical machine learning.
The data on this table actually--
I think it&#39;s from maybe the late &#39;90s.
Is that right?
Before-- before--
yeah.
Late &#39;90s, exactly.
It&#39;s from Hewlett Packard.
So this is a person named George who
worked at Hewlett Packard.
So this was early in the days of email, where as well spam
was also not very sophisticated.
So what we have here is data from over 4,000 emails sent to
an individual named George at HP Labs.
Each one&#39;s been hand labeled as either being
spam or good email.
And the goal here is to try to predict--
Actually, they call good email ham these days, Rob.
OK.
So a goal was to try to classify spam from ham based
on the frequencies of words in the email.
So here we just have a summary table of some of the more
important features.
So it&#39;s based on words and characters in the email.
So for example, this is saying that if this email had George
in it, it was more likely to be good email than spam.
Back then, if your name&#39;s George, and you saw George in
your email, it was more likely to be good email.
Nowadays, of course, spam is much more sophisticated.
They know your name.
They know a lot about your life.
And the fact that your name&#39;s in it actually may be a
smaller chance it&#39;s actually good email.
But back then, spammers were much less sophisticated.
So for example, if your name was in it, it more chance to
be hot email.
What&#39;s with that remove word, Rob?
Remove.
OK.
So I guess it probably said something like, don&#39;t remove.
Is that right?
I think it says, if you want to be removed
from this list, click.
I see.
That&#39;s usually a spam.
So the goal was that--
and we&#39;ll talk about this example in detail-- to use the
57 features--
and these are seven of those features--
as a classifier together to try to predict whether an
email is spam or ham.
Identify the numbers in a hand written ZIP code.
This is what we were alluding to earlier.
Here&#39;s some handwritten digits taken from envelopes.
And the goal is to, based on an image of any of these
digits, say what the digit is, to classify into
the 10 digit classes.
Well to humans, this looks like a pretty easy task.
We&#39;re pretty good at pattern recognition.
It turns out it&#39;s a notoriously
difficult task for computers.
They&#39;re getting better and better all the time.
So this was one of the first learning tasks that was used
to develop neural networks.
Neural networks were first brought to
bear on this problem.
And we thought this should be an easy problem to crack.
It turns out it&#39;s really difficult.
Actually, I remember the first time, Trevor, that we worked
on a machine learning problem, it was this problem.
And you were working at Bell Labs.
I visited Bell Labs.
And you had just gotten this data.
And you said, these people in artificial intelligence are
working on this.
And we thought, oh, let&#39;s try some statistical methods.
And we tried discriminant analysis, right?
That&#39;s right.
And we got an error rate of about
eight and a half percent.
And the best error rate--
In about 20 minutes or so.
Right.
And the best error rate anyone else had was about 4% or 5% at
that point.
We thought, oh, this is going to be easy.
We&#39;re already at 8% in 10 or 15 minutes.
Six months later--
Six months later, we were maybe at the same place.
So we realize actually--
as often is the case, you can get some of the
signal pretty quickly.
But getting down to a very good error rate, in this case,
trying to classify some of the harder to classify things,
like maybe this four--
or actually, most of these are pretty easy.
But if you look at the database, some of them are
very hard, so hard that the human eye can&#39;t really tell
what they are or has difficulty.
And those are the ones that machine learning algorithms
area really challenged by.
Anyway, it&#39;s a lovely problem.
And it&#39;s fascinated machine learners and statisticians for
a long time.
So the next example comes from medicine, classifying a tissue
sample into one of several cancer classes based on the
gene expression profile.
So Trevor and I both work in a medical school part time here
at Stanford.
And a lot of what we do and others do is to try to use
machine learning, statistical learning, big data analysis to
learn about data in cancer and other diseases.
So this is an example of that.
This is data in breast cancer.
It&#39;s called gene expression data.
So this has been collected from gene chips.
And what we see here on the left is a matrix of data.
Each row is a gene.
And there&#39;s about 8,000 genes here I think.
And each column is a patient.
And this is called a heat map.
So what this heat map is representing is low and high
gene expression for a given patient for a given gene, so
green being low and red meaning high.
And gene expression means the gene is working.
So if a gene is expressing, it&#39;s working hard in the cell.
If it&#39;s not expressing, it quiet.
It&#39;s silent.
And the goal is to try to figure out which genes--
well, try to figure out the pattern of gene expression.
These are patients.
These are women with breast cancer.
Trying to figure out the common patterns of gene
expression for women with breast cancer and seeing where
there&#39;s subcategories of breast cancer showing
different gene expression.
So what we see here is a heat map of the full data.
88 women in the columns and about 8,000 genes in the rows.
And hierarchical clustering, which we&#39;ll discuss in the
last part of this course, is being applied to the columns.
And you see the clustering tree at the top here, which
has been expanded for your view at the top.
And hierarchical clustering is being used to divide these
women into roughly one, two, three, four, five, six
subgroups based on the gene expression.
They&#39;re very effective, especially with these colors.
You can just see these clusters standing out.
Yeah.
Hierarchical clustering and heat maps have actually been a
very important contribution for genomics, which this is an
example of, simply because they enable you to see and to
organize the full set of data on just a single picture.
In the bottom right here, we&#39;ve drilled down to look
more at the gene expression.
For example, this subgroup here, these red patients, seem
to be high largely in these genes and
maybe in these genes.
So we&#39;ll talk about this example in detail later on in
the course.
Establish the relationship between salary and demographic
variables in population survey data.
So here&#39;s some survey data.
We see income from the central Atlantic region
of the USA in 2009.
And you see what you might expect to see.
As a function of age, income initially goes up, then levels
off, and then finally goes down as people get older.
Incomes gradually increase with year as the cost of
living increases.
And incomes change with education level.
That&#39;s the right hand plot Those are box plots.
And so here we see three of the
variables that affect income.
And again, the goal is-- we&#39;ll use regression models to try
and understand the roles of these variables together and
see if there&#39;s interactions and so on.
And the last example is Landsat images
of land use in Australia.
So this is a rural area of Australia.
Those are harsh colors, Rob.
Did you choose those colors.
You probably did, Trevor.
You&#39;re the color [INAUDIBLE].
This is before--
When did that happen?
I didn&#39;t see the news memo.
OK.
So these are from Landsat images.
So let&#39;s start here in this panel.
So this is again a rural area of Australia where the land
use has been labeled, I think, actually by graduate students
or researchers into one of one, two,
three, four, five, six--
They don&#39;t have to pay the graduate students as much
there as we do.
So they&#39;ve been labeled in these columns indicating the
different labels.
These are the true labels.
And the goal is to try to predict these true labels from
the spectral bands at four frequencies taken from a
satellite image.
And so here&#39;s the power at the different frequencies in four
spectral bands.
So we have features which are-- now they&#39;re pretty
complicated because we have features, spatial features,
four layers of them.
And we&#39;re going to try to use those combination of features
to predict the land use that we see here.
Pixel by pixel, right?
Pixel by pixel.
Although we might want to use the fact that nearby pixels
are more likely to be the same land use than ones
that are far away.
And we&#39;ll talk about classifiers.
I think the one we use here is actually nearest neighbor, a
very simple classifier.
And that produces the prediction
in the bottom right.
And you can see it&#39;s quite good.
It&#39;s not perfect.
There&#39;s a few mistakes it makes.
But it&#39;s, for the most part, quite accurate.
OK.
So that&#39;s the end of the series of examples.
In the next session, we&#39;ll just tell you some notation
and how we set up problems for supervised learning, which
we&#39;ll use for the rest of the course.