So that&#39;s one extension of the linear model.
A number of extensions are interactions and
non-linearity.
We&#39;ll talk about interactions first.
So in our previous analysis with advertising data, we
assumed that the effect on sales of increasing one
advertising medium is independent of the amount
spent on the other media.
So for example, in the linear model, we&#39;ve
got TV, radio, newspaper.
It says that the average effect on sales of a one unit
increase in TV is always beta 1 regardless of the amount
spent on radio.
But suppose that spending money on radio advertising
actually increases the effectiveness of TV
advertising, so that the slope term for TV should increase as
radio increases.
So in this situation, suppose we&#39;re given a fixed budget of
$100,000, spending half on radio and half on TV may
increase sales more than allocating the entire amount
in either TV or to radio.
So in marketing, this is known as a synergy effect, and in
statistics, we often refer to it as an interaction effect.
So here&#39;s a nice, pretty picture of the regression
surface, sales as a function of TV and radio.
And we see that when the levels of either TV or radio
are low, then the true sales are lower than predicted by
the linear model.
But when advertising is split between the two media, then
model tends to underestimate sales.
And you can see that by the way the points stick out of
the surface at the two ends, or below the
surface in the middle.
So how do we deal with interactions or include them
in the model?
So what we do is we put in product terms.
So here we have a model where we have a term for TV and the
term for radio, and then we put in a term that is the
product of radio and TV.
So we literally multiply those two variables together, and
call it a new variable, and put a
coefficient on that variable.
Now you can rewrite that model slightly, as we&#39;ve done in the
second line over here.
And we&#39;ve just collected terms slightly differently.
And the way we&#39;ve written it here is showing that by
putting in this interaction, we can interpret it as the
coefficient of TV, which had been originally beta 1, is now
modified as a function of radio.
So as the values of radio changes, the coefficient of TV
changes by amount beta three times radio.
So that&#39;s a nice way of interpreting what this
interaction is doing.
And if you look at a summary of the linear model below,
indeed we see that the interaction is significant,
which we might have guessed from the previous picture.
So in this case, the interaction really is
significant.
So the results in this table suggest that
interactions are important.
The p-value for the interaction is extremely low,
so there&#39;s strong evidence in favor of the alternative here,
that beta three, which was the coefficient for
interaction, is not 0.
We can also look at the R squared for the model with
interaction, and it&#39;s jumped up to 96.8% compared to 89.7%
by just adding this one extra parameter to the model.
And we get that by adding an interaction
between TV and radio.
Another way of interpreting this is that we have 69% of
the variability in sales that remains off to fit in that
it&#39;s a model has it been explained by the interaction
to because we went from 89.7 to 96.8 and if we think of
that in terms of the fraction of unexplained variance, that
69% of unexplained variance.
The coefficient estimates in the table suggest that an
increase in TV advertising of $1,000 is associated with an
increased sales of--
and we plug in the numbers for beta 1 in beta 3.
It&#39;s 19 plus 11 times radio units.
Sorry 1.1 times radio units.
Alternatively, an increase in radio advertising of $1,000
will be associated with an increase in sales of--
so now we&#39;ve written it the other way around.
We factored it the other way around, and now thinking of
the coefficient of radio as changing as a function of TV,
and it&#39;ll be 29 plus 1.1 times TV units.
So you can make either of those interpretations when you
put an interaction in the model.
Sometimes it&#39;s the case that an interaction term has a very
small p-value, but the associated main effects-- in
this case, TV and radio-- do not.
But when we put an interaction in, we tend to leave in the
main effects, and we call this the hierarchy principle.
And so there it&#39;s stated if we put in an interaction, we put
in the main effects, even if the p-values associated with
the coefficients are not significant.
So why do we do this?
It&#39;s just that interactions are hard to interpret in a
model without main effects--
their mean: actually changes, and so it&#39;s just generally not
a good practice.
Another way of saying this is that the interaction term also
contains main effects, even if you [? foot ?] the model with
no main effect terms.
So it just becomes more cumbersome to interpret.
Now what if we want to put in the interactions between a
qualitative and a quantitative variable?
Turns out that actually easier to interpret, and
we&#39;ll see that now.
So let&#39;s look at the credit card data set again, and let&#39;s
suppose we&#39;re going to predict balance, as before, and we&#39;re
going to use income, which is a quantitative variable, and
student status, which is qualitative.
And so we&#39;ll have a dummy variable for student, which
will be 1 if the person&#39;s a student, otherwise a 0.
So without an interaction, the model looks like this.
And we see we&#39;ve got an intercept, we&#39;ve got a
coefficient for income, and then we&#39;re going to have beta
2 is the person is a student, and 0 if the
person&#39;s not a student.
And another way to write that is a coefficient on income,
and we just lump together the intercept and the dummy
variable for student.
And by grouping them like that, we can think of this as
having a common slope in income, but a different
intercept depending on whether the person is
a student or not.
And if a person as a student, the intercept is beta 0 plus
beta 2, and if the person&#39;s not a student,
it&#39;s just beta 0.
So that&#39;s without an interaction.
With interactions in the model, it takes the following
form, but before we study this, let&#39;s just look at a
picture of these two situations, because that&#39;ll
make things clear.
So in the left panel, we&#39;ve got no interaction, and we see
very clearly that there is a common slope for whether
you&#39;re a student or not, but just the intercept changes.
But if you put an interaction between the slop of income and
student status, you&#39;re going to get both a different
industry and the different slope.
And so that makes it really simple
explanation in this case.
And if we look at the actual model, it looks like this.
So we can write it in several different ways.
And so this second term over here is showing us what
happens with the interaction.
And so, if you&#39;re a student, you get both a different
intercept--
that&#39;s beta 2--
and you get a different slope on income-- which is beta 3.
And if you&#39;re not a student, there&#39;s 0, which means you get
the baseline intercept and slope.
And you can rearrange those terms in the following fashion
and it&#39;s telling you the same thing.
So the interpretation of interactions with categorical
variables and the associated dummy variables is more simple
than even in the quantitative case.
The other modification of the linear model is what if we
want to include nonlinear effects?
So here we&#39;ve got the plot of two of the variables in the
auto data set.
So we&#39;ve got miles per gallon against horsepower, and we&#39;ve
included three fitted models here.
We&#39;ve got the linear regression model, which is the
orange curve over here.
And you can see it&#39;s not quite capturing the
structure in the data.
And so to improve on that, what we&#39;ve actually done is
fit two polynomial models.
We&#39;ve fit a quadratic model, which is the blue curve, and
you can see that better captures the curvature in the data than
the linear model.
And then we&#39;ve also fitted a degree five polynomial, and
that one looks rather wiggly.
So we have an ability to fit models of different
complexity, in this case, using polynomials.
And these are very easy to do.
So just like we created an artificial dummy variable for
categorical variables, we can make extra variables to
accommodate polynomials.
So we make a variable horsepower squared, which we
just include in our data set, and now we fit a linear model
with the coefficient for horsepower, and a coefficient
for horsepower squared.
And of course that&#39;s a polynomial expression, and
we&#39;ll notice that that improves the fit.
We do the summary, and we see that the coefficient of both
horsepower and horsepower squared are strongly
significant.
And so you can do this, you can add a cubic term as well,
and in the previous example, we went all the way up to a
polynomial of degree five.
So that&#39;s a very easy way of allowing for nonlinearities in
a variable, and still use linear regression.
We still call it a linear model, because it&#39;s actually
linear in the coefficients.
But as a function of the
variables, it&#39;s become nonlinear.
But the same technology can be used to fit such models.
So that expands the scope of linear regression enormously.
OK so we&#39;ve reached the end of the session.
If you&#39;re reading along in the chapter, you&#39;ll see there&#39;s
some topics we didn&#39;t cover.
We didn&#39;t cover outliers.
There&#39;s non-constant variance of the error terms.
High leverage points, which means if you&#39;ve got points of
observations in x that really stick out far from the rest of
the crowd, what effect they have on the model.
And colinearity, if you have variables that are very
correlated with each other, what happens if you include
them in the model.
So we&#39;re not going to cover those here, but they&#39;re
covered in some detail in the book, and if you look at
section 3.33, you&#39;ll find coverage on that.
OK, so that finishes our coverage of linear models.
There are a lot of generalizations of linear
model, and as I&#39;ve hinted at [INAUDIBLE], it&#39;s actually
quite a powerful framework.
So we used similar technology for classification problems,
and that will be discussed in next.
So we&#39;ll be doing logistic regression and support vector
machines, which also have linear models underneath the
hood, but expand the scope greatly of linear models.
And then we&#39;ll cover non-linearity.
So we&#39;ll talk about techniques like kernel smoothing, and
splines, and generalized additive models, some of which
are also just extensions of linear models, and some of
which are richer form of modelling that are for
non-linearities in a more flexible way.
We covered some simple interactions in linear models
here, but we&#39;ll talk about much more general techniques
for dealing with interactions in a much more systematic way.
And so there we&#39;ll cover tree-based methods, and then
some of the state-of-the-art techniques, such as bagging,
random forests, and boosting, and these also captured
non-linearities.
And these really bring our bag of tools up to what we call
state-of-the-art.
And then another important class of methods we will
discuss use what&#39;s known as regularized fitting.
And so these include ridge regression and lasso.
And these have become very popular lately, especially
when we have data sets where we have very large numbers of
variables--
so-called wide data sets, and even linear models are too
rich for them, and so we need to use methods to control the
variability.
And so that&#39;s all still to come, and so we have lots of
nice things to look forward to.