We&#39;re not going to go into more detail on multinomial
regression now.
What we&#39;re going to do is tell you about a different
classification method, which is called discriminant
analysis, which is also very useful.
And it approaches a problem from a really quite different
point of view.
In discriminant analysis, the idea is to model the
distribution of x in each of the classes separately.
And then use what&#39;s known as Bayes theorem to flip things
around to get the probability of y given x.
In this case, for linear discriminant analysis, we&#39;re
going to use Gaussian distributions for each class.
And that&#39;s going to lead to linear or quadratic
discriminant analysis.
So those are the two popular forms.
But as you&#39;ll see, this approach is quite general.
And other distributions can be used as well.
But we&#39;ll focus on normal distributions.
So what is Bayes&#39; theorem for classification?
It sounds pretty scary, but not too bad.
So, of course, Thomas Bayes was a famous mathematician.
And his name now, today, represents a burgeoning
subfield of statistical and probabilistic modeling.
But here we&#39;re going to focus on a very simple result which
is known Bayes theorem.
And it says that the probability of y equals k
given x equals x.
So the idea is you&#39;ve got two variables.
In this case, we&#39;ve got y and x.
And we&#39;re looking at aspects of their joint distribution.
So this is what we&#39;re after, the probability of y
equals k given x.
And Bayes theorem says you can flip things around.
You can write that as a probability that x is x given
y equals k--
that&#39;s the first piece on the top there--
multiplied by the marginal probability or prior
probability that y is k and then divided by the marginal
probability that x equals x.
So this is just a formula for probability theory.
But it turns it&#39;s really useful and is a basis for
discriminant analysis.
And so we write things slightly differently in the
case of discriminant analysis.
So this probability y equals k is written as pi k.
So if there&#39;s three classes, there&#39;s going to be three
values for pi, just the probability
for each of the classes.
But here we&#39;ve got class little k, so that&#39;s pi k.
Probability that x is x given y equals k, well, if x is a
quantitative variable, what we write for that is the density.
So that&#39;s a probability density function
for x in class k.
And then the marginal probability f of x is just
this expression over here.
So this is summing over all the classes.
And so that&#39;s how we use Bayes theorem to get to the
probabilities of interest, which is y equals k given x.
Now, at this point it&#39;s still quite general.
We can plug in any probability densities.
But now what we&#39;re going to do is go ahead and plug in the
Gaussian density for f sub-k of x.
Before we do that, let me just show you a little picture to
make things clear.
In the left-hand plot, what have we got here?
We&#39;ve got a plot against x, single variable x.
And in the vertical axis, what we&#39;ve got is actually pi sub-k
multiplied by f sub-k of x.
For both classes, k equals 1 and k equals 2.
Now, in this case, remember in the previous slide, the
probability was essentially proportional to pi sub-k times
f sub-k of x.
And in this case, the pi&#39;s are the same for both.
So it&#39;s really to do with which density is the highest.
And you can see that the decision boundary, or the
vertical dash line, is at zero.
And that&#39;s the point at which the green density is higher
than the purple density.
And so anything to the left of zero we classify as green.
And anything to the right we&#39;d classify as purple.
And it sort of makes sense that that&#39;s what we do there.
The right-hand plot has different priors.
So here the probability of 2 is 0.7 and of 1 is 0.3.
And now, again, we&#39;re plotting pi sub-k times f sub-k
of x against x.
And that big prior has bumped up the purple.
And what it has done is move the decision boundary slightly
to the left.
And that makes sense, too.
Again, that&#39;s where they intersect.
That makes sense as well.
Because we&#39;ve got more purples here.
Actually, I&#39;ll say they are pinks.
It looks purple to me.
There&#39;s more of them.
So everything else being equal, we&#39;re going to make
less mistakes if we classify it to purples and to greens.
So that&#39;s how these priors and the densities play a role in
classification.
So why discriminant analysis?
It seems like logistic regression was
a pretty good tool.
Well, it is.
But it turns out there&#39;s room for
discriminant analysis as well.
And so it&#39;s three points we make here.
When the classes are well separated, it turns out that
the parameter estimates for logistic regression are
surprisingly unstable.
In fact, if you&#39;ve go a feature that separates the
classes perfectly, the
coefficients go off to infinity.
So it really doesn&#39;t do well there.
Logistic aggression was developed in largely the
biological and medical fields where you never found such
strong predictors.
Now, you can do things to make logistic
regression better behave.
But it turns out linear discriminant analysis doesn&#39;t
suffer from this problem and is better behaved in those
situations.
Also, if any small, the sample size is small, and the
distribution of the predictor&#39;s x is approximately
normal in each of the classes, it turns out that discriminant
model is again more stable than logistic regression.
And finally, if we&#39;ve got more than two classes, we&#39;ll see
logistic regression gives us nice low dimensions
views of the data.
And the other point, remember, in the very first section, we
showed that the Bayes rule, if you have the right population
model, Bayes rule is the best you can possibly do.
So if our normal assumption is right here, then this
discriminant analysis in the Bayes rule is the best you can
possibly do.
Good point, Rob.