Welcome back.
We&#39;re now going to talk about some important questions that
arise when you use aggression in real problems.
So is at least one of the predictors useful in
predicting the response?
That&#39;s the first order question.
Do the predictors on the whole have anything to
say about the outcome?
If not, we probably want to stop there.
But given that there is some effect overall, which of the
predictors are important?
Are they all important, or only some subset?
How well does the model fit the data?
And also, given a set of predictor values, what
response value should we predict?
So what&#39;s our prediction of sales given a certain level of
advertising in the three modes?
And how accurate is that prediction?
So these are all things we can answer from the model.
Well, at least 1, 2, and 4.
3 we&#39;ll examine by looking at some alternative models.
So the answer to the first question-- is at least one
predictor useful?-- does a model overall have any
predictive value.
We look at the drop in training error.
So this is the total sum of squares.
Remember, if we just used the mean to predict, that&#39;s the no
predictor model.
This is the residual sum of squares achieved using all
three predictors.
And we can look at the drop, the present variance
explained--
which I actually have that here for that.
We defined this earlier.
Now it&#39;s 0.897.
So it was about 0.6 something before.
Now by adding the two more predictors, we&#39;ve increase
that to 0.897.
So this says that we reduced the variance of sales around
its mean by almost 90% by using these three predictors.
That seems pretty impressive.
To quantify that in a more statistical way, we can form
the f ratio, which is defined as follows.
It&#39;s the drop in training error divided by p--
p is number of parameters we fit.
Here, it&#39;s three, right?
The three kinds of advertising budgets, divided by the mean
squared residual.
So n is the sample size, and we subtract off the number of
parameters we fit, which is p plus 1 for the intercept.
So statistical theory tells us that we can compute the
statistic and under the null hypothesis, that there&#39;s no
effective of any of predictors, this will have an
f distribution with p and n minus p minus
1 degrees of freedom.
And again, there are tables of this.
Or your computer program will compute this for you.
This f statistic here is huge.
And its p value I haven&#39;t recorded here, but it&#39;s less
than 0.0001.
So this says what we believe already, looking at this
previous tables and the graphs, that there&#39;s a strong
effect here of the predictors on the outcome.
They have something to say about the outcome.
OK, when we fit linear regression models, one of the
things we have to do is decide on what are the important
variables to include in the model.
By the way, this is not Rob anymore.
Rob asked me to do this section because it&#39;s a little
hard for him.
Kidding.
So the most direct approach is called all subsets or best
subsets regression.
So basically, what you&#39;re going to do is you&#39;re going to
compute the least squares fit for all the possible subsets
of the variables and then choose between them based on
some criterion that balances the train error
with the model size.
Now, this might seem like a reasonable thing to do if you
have a small number of variables.
But it gets really hard when the number of
variables gets large.
So if you&#39;ve got p variables, there are 2 to the p subsets.
And you know, that 2 to the p grows exponentially with the
number of variables.
So for example, when p is 40, there are
over a billion models.
So we&#39;re talking about subsets like the model might have
variable 1, 3, and 5 in it.
That&#39;s a subset of size 3.
And then another model might have a subset of size four.
And with 40 variables, there&#39;s over a billion such models.
So that clearly becomes cumbersome, searching through
such a big model space.
And so what we need instead is an automated approach that
searches through for us, and that finds a subset of them.
And so we&#39;ll describe two commonly used approaches next.
Forward selection is a very attractive approach, because
it&#39;s both tractable and it gives a
good sequence of models.
So this is how it works.
You start with a null model.
And the null model has no predictors in it, but it&#39;ll
just have the intercept in it.
And the intercept is the mean of y with no other variables
in the model.
And now what you do is you add variables one at a time.
So the first variable you add, you do it as follows.
You fit p simple linear regression models, each with
one of the variables in and the intercept.
And you look at each of them.
And you add to the null model the variable that results in
the lowest residual sum of squares.
So basically, you just search through all the
single-variable models and pick the best one.
Now having picked that, you fix that
variable in the model.
And now you search through the remaining p minus 1 variables
again and find out which variable should be added to
the variable you&#39;ve already picked to best improve the
residual sum of squares.
And you continue in this fashion, adding one variable
at a time, until some stopping rule is satisfied--
for example, when all the remaining variables have a p
value above some threshold.
Now, this sounds like it might be computationally quite
difficult as well, but it turns out it&#39;s not.
There are some clever tricks you can use to do all these
evaluations very efficiently.
So in a similar fashion, and this is if p is not too large,
you can start from the other end.
So you start with a model with all the
variables in the model.
And now you&#39;re going to remove them one at a time.
And this time, at each step you&#39;re going to remove the
variable that does the least damage to the model.
In other words, you want to remove the variable that&#39;s got
the significance.
And that you can actually find from looking at the t
statistics for each of the variables.
And remove the one with the least significant t statistic.
But now you&#39;ve got a model with p minus 1 variables, and
you just repeat.
And you keep going in that fashion again until you reach
some threshold that you&#39;ve defined, perhaps in
terms of a p value.
So these are two approaches.
They might seem somewhat ad hoc.
But they&#39;re very effective.
And later, we&#39;ll discuss more systematic criteria for
choosing an optimal member in the path of models produced by
the either forward or stepwise model selection.
Some of these criteria include something known as well
Mallow&#39;s Cp, Akaike Information Criterion, AIC--
that&#39;s the abbreviation--
and then BIC, which is
Bayesian Information Criterion.
These all sound like very important methods.
They&#39;re named often important people.
And they&#39;re very popular.
And then there&#39;s something called adjusted R squared.
And one of our favorites is this cross-validation, which
you&#39;ll be learning about.
We&#39;ll talk more about model selection in later sessions.
Now there are some other considerations in regression
models that we haven&#39;t really touched on yet.
And the one is qualitative predictors.
So some variables are not quantitative, but qualitative.
In other words, they don&#39;t take values on
a continuous scale.
But they take values in a discrete set.
So we call them categorical
predictors, or factor variables.
We going to see a matrix of data in the next slide.
It&#39;s a credit card data.
In fact, I&#39;ll just take you there now.
And so here&#39;s a bunch of variables on
credit cards and ratings.
And we see the current balance on the credit card, the age,
number of cards, and so on.
These are all quantitative variables.
Now in addition to these variables, we have some
qualitative variables.
So one of them is gender.
So that take on values male and female.
Student, so the student status of the cardholder, whether
they are a students or not.
So these are qualitative values.
Marital status, say, married, single, or divorced.
There&#39;s no order really in those variables.
They&#39;re just different categories.
And likewise, ethnicity.
Say Caucasian, African-American, or Asian.
Again, in no way an ordered variable.
So how do we deal with such qualitative predictors when
we&#39;re fitting linear regression models?
So let&#39;s consider an example on credit cards.
Imagine investigating the difference in credit card
balance between males and females,
ignoring the other variables.
So what we do is we do we create a new variable.
Let&#39;s call it x.
We call it x.
And the i value is going to be 1, if the ith person is a
female, and a 0 if the ith person is a male.
So we&#39;ve got a name for such a variable.
We call it a dummy variable.
It&#39;s a created variable just to represent
this categorical feature.
So for each value of i, we score an individual as 0 or 1,
depending on if they&#39;re male or female.
And so now if we put such a variable in a model, let&#39;s say
on its own, we&#39;ve got the linear regression model with a
coefficient for this dummy variable, xi.
And let&#39;s see what it produces.
Well, since xi takes on only two possible values, 0 or 1,
the model&#39;s either going to be beta 9 plus beta 1 plus error
if the person is female.
And if the person is male, it&#39;s just going to be beta 0
plus error.
So beta 1 is telling us the effect of being female versus
the baseline, in this case, of being male.
And so that&#39;s how we deal with the categorical variable with
just two levels.
So you will see the results of the regression model using
just the single variable gender and the dummy variable
0, 1, the 1 representing female.
And so we see the result.
And the coefficient is 19.73, but it&#39;s not significant.
The p value is 0.66, which is not significant.
So contrary to popular wisdom, females don&#39;t generally have a
higher credit card balance than males.
The number 19.73 is slightly higher, but it&#39;s not
significant.
So what do we do it if we have a variable with
more than two levels?
So ethnicity is such a variable.
Well, we just make more dummy variables.
So ethnicity has three levels.
So we&#39;ll make two dummy variables in this case, and
we&#39;ll call them x1 and x2.
And so xi1 is the value for the ith individual for dummy
variable one.
We&#39;ll call it a 1 if the ith person is Asian, otherwise 0.
And the second dummy variable will be 1 if the ith person is
Caucasian, and 0 if not.
And of course if they&#39;re both zero, the person, the
individual, will be African-American.
And so that&#39;s the general rule if you&#39;ve got a categorical
variable with three levels, you make two dummy variables.
If it&#39;s got two levels, you make one dummy variable.
And if it&#39;s got k levels, you&#39;ll make k minus 1 dummy
variables to represent each of those categories.
So what does the model look like in this case?
Well, we&#39;ll have a model now with two coefficients, one for
each of these dummy variables.
And let&#39;s look at the different cases.
So if the person&#39;s Asian, they&#39;ll get the beta 1.
If the person&#39;s Caucasian, they&#39;ll get the beta 2.
And if the person&#39;s African American, they don&#39;t have beta
1 or beta 2, so the baseline, beta 0, represents such an
individual.
And so what we see now is that beta 1 represents the
difference between the baseline beta 0, which is
African American, and the difference between that
individual and an Asian.
So it&#39;s the additional effect for being an Asian, and beta 2
is an additional effect for being Caucasian.
And as I said, there will be always one fewer dummy
variable than the number of levels.
So in this case, we call the category African-American is
known as the baseline level, because it doesn&#39;t have a
parameter representing it except beta 0.
So here&#39;s the linear model.
We&#39;ve picked African-American as a baseline.
And so that actually determines which
comparisons we make.
So the coefficient minus 18.69 is comparing Asian to
African-American.
And that&#39;s not significant.
And likewise, the Caucasian to African-American, which is
also not significant.
Now, it turns out the choice of the baseline does not take
the fit of the model.
The residual sum of squares would be the same no matter
which category you chose as the baseline.
But the contrasts would change, because picking the
baseline determines which contrasts you make.
And so the p values potentially would change as
you change the baseline.