OK.
Another R session also on classification.
This time, we&#39;re going to look at k-nearest neighbor
classification, which it&#39;s one of those tools that&#39;s a very
simple classification rule, but it&#39;s effective
a lot of the time.
Some experts have written that k-nearest neighbors do the
best about one third of the time.
And it&#39;s so simple that, in the game of doing
classification, you always want to have k-nearest
neighbors in your toolbox.
OK.
So we&#39;ve got a little session here that we&#39;ll run.
And if we go into our RStudio session, you see we&#39;ve got it
set up here for k-nearest neighbors.
And for that we&#39;ll use the Class Library.
So we go to Library Class, and that sets us up for doing
k-nearest neighbors classification.
And let&#39;s ask for help on k-nearest neighbors, and we
see the Help file, which, again, is always a useful
thing to do.
And it tells us it&#39;s got a slightly different format to
the previous session, where we used LDA.
It doesn&#39;t take a formula.
It asks for the training x variables, the test x
variables, and the class label for the training.
And then it asks for what value of k you want, and then
the sum of the arguments.
OK?
So we&#39;ll use this again on our stock market example.
So in this case, since we&#39;re going to have to list all
these variables by name in the call, we&#39;ll just
attach stock market.
And recall when you attach a data frame, it makes available
the variables on the data frame by name in your frame.
So if I go down into the session window and say LS--
well, that didn&#39;t do it actually.
I can say objects 2 because stock market is in position 2.
There we go.
So they&#39;re available in location 2 on the search list.
And there&#39;s all the variables in s market available by name.
OK.
So what we&#39;ll do is we&#39;ll make a matrix of lag1 and lag2.
We can use the same two variables we used in the
previous session.
So we&#39;ll say x lag is C bind that makes a matrix of two
columns, in this case, of lag1 and lag2.
OK?
And let&#39;s just make sure that actually did what we want.
I mean, I know it did, but let&#39;s look at the first five
rows of that matrix.
And there they are, so it did what we wanted.
And then we&#39;ll make a indicator variable Train which
is year less than 2005.
So that&#39;s just going to be a binary variable of trues and
falses depending on whether the variable year
was less than 2005.
OK, now we&#39;re ready to call k and n, so we give our matrix x
lag, and right in line there we index it by Train which is
just using the training observations.
And then, for the test observations, we give
it x lag not Train.
So those not train will be, therefore, those that are
equal to 2005--
for year equal to 2005.
So Train and Not Train.
That exclamation mark means not.
And the response is direction, again, indexed by Train.
And k equals 1 says we want one nearest neighbor
classification.
And, again, just to remind you, that means what the
algorithm does is, it says to classify a new observation,
you go into the training set in the x space, the feature
space, and you look for the training observation that&#39;s
closest to your test point in Euclidean distance and you
classify to its class.
And so this will do it.
And we can look at the--
we put the results in knn.pred, and we can do a
table of knn.pred and the true response, which is Direction
at Not Train.
And we get a little confusion matrix again, and we can look
at the classification performance there.
And it&#39;s exactly 0.5.
So it was useless.
One nearest neighbor did no better than flipping a coin.
So, what to do next?
Well, one could proceed further and try nearest
neighbors with multiple values of k.
We haven&#39;t done that in this session, but we leave it up to
you and you can look in the end of the chapter and you
will see that there&#39;s examples of this.