OK, logistic regression.
So now we&#39;re going to get a little bit more mathy.
Let&#39;s, for shorthand, write p of X for the probability that
y is 1 given X. And we&#39;re going to consider our simple
model for predicting default, yes or no, using balance--
one of the variables.
So single variable.
So here&#39;s the form of logistic regression.
So that e is the scientific constant, the exponential
value, and we raise e to the power of a linear model.
We&#39;ve got a beta 0, which is the intercept, and beta 1 is
the coefficient of x.
And you see that appears in the numerator and in the
denominator, but there&#39;s 1 plus in the denominator.
So it&#39;s a somewhat complicated expression, but you can see
straight away that the values have to lie between 0 and 1.
Because in the numerator, e to anything is positive.
And the denominator is bigger than the numerator, so it&#39;s
always got to be bigger than 0.
And you can show that&#39;s it&#39;s got to be less than 1.
When beta 0 plus beta x gets very large, this approaches 1.
So this is a special construct, a transformation of
a linear model to guarantee that what we get out is a
probability.
So that&#39;s called the logistic regression model.
And actually, the name &quot;logistic&quot; comes from the
transformation of this model.
So this is a monotone transformation.
We take log of p of X over 1 minus p of X and out pops our
linear model.
And that transformation is called the log odds or the
logit transformation of the probability.
And this is the model that we&#39;re going to
talk about right now.
To summarize, we got a linear model still.
But it&#39;s modeling the probabilities on
a non-linear scale.
And so back to our picture again.
The picture on the right was produced by a logistic
regression model and that&#39;s why the probabilities lie
between 0 and 1.
So we&#39;ve written down the model, how do we estimate the
model from data?
Well, the popular way is to use maximum likelihood.
Maximum likelihood was introduced by who, Rob?
Me, actually.
Oh, you?
Yes, just last week.
Did you reinvent it?
I didn&#39;t realize--
actually, yeah.
Because the correct answer is Fisher back in the 1920s,
Ronald Fisher.
Fisher.
Ronald Fisher, a very famous statistician, invented a lot
of the tools that we use in modern applied statistics, and
maximum likelihood is one of them.
Well, the way maximum likelihood works is you&#39;ve got
a data series of observed 0&#39;s and 1&#39;s and you&#39;ve got a model
for the probabilities.
And that model involves parameters.
In this case, beta 0 and beta.
So for any values of the parameters, we can write down
the probability of the observed data.
And since each observation is meant to be independent of
each other one, the probability of observed data
is the probability of the observed
string of 0&#39;s and 1&#39;s.
So wherever we observed a 1, we write down the probability
of a 1, which is p of x.
So if xi, i f observation i was a 1, the probability is p
of xi, and we write that down.
And since they&#39;re all independent, we just multiply
these probabilities.
And these are the probabilities of a 0, which is
1 minus the probability of a 1.
So this is the joint probability of the observed
sequence of 0&#39;s and 1&#39;s.
And of course, it involves the parameters.
And so the idea of maximum likelihood is pick the
parameters to make that
probability as large as possible.
Because after all, you did observe the
sequence of 0&#39;s and 1&#39;s.
And so that&#39;s the idea.
Simple to say, not always simple to execute.
But likely, we have programs that can do this.
And for example, in R, we&#39;ve got the glm function, which in
a snap of a finger will fit this model for you and
estimate the parameters.
And in this case, this is what it produced.
The coefficient estimates were minus 10 for the intercept and
0.0055 for the slope for balance.
That&#39;s beta and beta 0.
So there are the coefficient estimates.
It also gives you standard errors for each of the
coefficient estimates.
It computes a Z-statistic and it also gives you P-values.
I think I just realized something.
So you had a picture a couple slides ago of a curve?
Yes.
And is that how you found--
I was wondering how you found the parameters for that curve.
Is that how you found--
That&#39;s exactly right, Rob.
So this curve over here is the curve corresponding to those
estimates that we just produced in the table.
And you might be surprised because the slope is very
small here.
Yet, it seemed to produce such a big change in the
probabilities.
That may be a typo?
Or, is it?
I certainly hope not.
But let&#39;s look a bit closer.
Look at the units of balance.
They&#39;re in dollars.
So we got $2,000, $2,500.
And so the values of the coefficients, which are going
to multiply that balance variable, they sort of take
into account the units that are used.
So this is 0.005 per dollar, but it would be 5
per thousand dollars.
So slopes, you have to take the units into account.
And so the Z-statistic, which is a kind of standardized
slope, does that.
And then if we look at the P-value, we see that the
chance that actually this balance slope
is 0 is very small.
Less than 0.001.
So both intercept and slope strongly
significant in this case.
How do I interpret that P-value for the intercept?
Do I care about that?
We usually don&#39;t care so much about the
P-value for the intercept.
The intercept&#39;s largely to do with the preponderance of 0&#39;s
and 1&#39;s in the data set.
And so that&#39;s of less importance.
That&#39;s just inherent in the data set.
It&#39;s the slope that&#39;s really important.
What do we do with this model?
We can predict probabilities.
And so let&#39;s suppose we take a person with
a balance of $1,000.
Well, we can estimate their probability.
So we just plug in the $1,000 into this formula over here.
And notice I&#39;ve put hats on beta 0 and beta 1 to indicate
that they&#39;re now being estimated from the data.
Put a hat on the probability.
And yeah, we&#39;ve plugged in the numbers and we use our
calculator or computer and we get 0.006.
So somebody with a balance of $1,000 has a probability or
0.006 of defaulting.
In other words, pretty small.
What if they&#39;ve got a credit card balance of $2,000?
That means they owe $2,000 rather than $1,000.
Well, if we go through the same procedure, now the
probability has jumped up to 0.586.
So it&#39;s got much higher.
And you can imagine if we put in $3,000,
we&#39;d get even higher.
Let&#39;s do this again using some of the other variables.
We haven&#39;t seen student yet, but one of our
predictors is student.
And it&#39;s a binary variable in this case.
It&#39;s a yes or no variable.
Is the credit card owner a student or not?
And so we code that as a 0, 1 variable and we fit a simple
logistic regression model.
And it gets a coefficient of 0.4049.
And that&#39;s also significant.
OK, let&#39;s do it again using the variable
student as a predictor.
This is a binary variable.
Is the credit card holder a student or not?
And we find we get a coefficient of 0.4049 in this
case, which is also significant.
So this is another variable in our database.
And just like before, we can evaluate the probability of
default is yes.
Given that the card holder is a student, it
comes out to 0.04.
And if they&#39;re not a student, it comes out to be a bit
lower, 0.029, close to 0.03.
And we&#39;re going to examine the interactions between student
and balance and the other variables in a little while.