OK.
Well, we can have another on session.
This time, we can look at validation methods,
cross-validation and we&#39;ll start off with leave-one-out
cross-validation.
So we&#39;ll go to our studio session and see what we can do
with validation.
So here we are, we first of all require ISLR, it is
outdated for our session.
And this time, we require the boot package, and so requires,
just like using library, it will also return a true and
false if the package doesn&#39;t exist.
So let&#39;s look at the function cv.glm.
So that&#39;s a general
cross-validation package for glms.
And it&#39;ll give you some help on that.
And so again, it&#39;s always useful before you use a
package or use a function to look at the help file and make
sure you&#39;re using it correctly.
So we&#39;re gonna use the auto data.
And in particular, we look at two variables, miles per
gallon and horsepower.
So we&#39;ll make a plot of those data.
And plot takes a formula.
So you can use a formula in plot.
And tell it where to evaluate the formula in
the data set auto.
So we make that plot.
And we see, as we might expect, miles per gallon drops
down quite substantially as horsepower increases.
And now we can use this data set to investigate
cross-validation.
So the first thing we&#39;ll do is leave-one-out
OK?
And so we&#39;ll fit a linear model.
And we&#39;ll use glm to fit this, even though we just fit in a
linear model.
So glm can fit nonlinear models as well, in particular
logistic regression models.
But it will also fit linear models.
And so if you don&#39;t give the family to glm by default, it
just fits a linear model.
OK?
And then we&#39;ll run cv.glm on that linear model.
Now, just to remind you what leave-one-out cross-validation
does, it puts the model repeatedly n times, if there&#39;s
n observations.
Each time, it leaves out one observation, produces a fit on
all the other data, and then makes a prediction at the x
value for that observation that you lift out.
OK?
And so cv.glm actually does that by brute force, actually
refits the model all those times.
It&#39;s a little slow.
You may have noticed it took a while before the
results came up.
And eventually it came up and produced two numbers.
We see them on the screen here.
Well, it produced quite a lot, actually.
But we just looked at the delta, which is the
cross-validated prediction error.
And even there it gives two numbers, and if you look on
the help file, you&#39;ll see why.
The first number is the raw leave-one-out, or lieu
cross-validation result.
And the second one is a bias-corrected version of it.
And the bias correction has to do with the fact that the data
set that we train it on is slightly smaller than the one
that we actually would like to get the error for, which is
the full data set of size n.
Turns out that has more of an effect for k-fold
cross-validation.
Now the thing is, for leave-one-out cross-validation
and for linear models, this function doesn&#39;t exploit the
nice simple formula we saw in the chapter.
So let me just remind you what that nice simple formula is.
And it goes like follows.
We want to do this classification error for each
observation yi minus our right y hat i minus i.
So this is what we&#39;d like to compute.
And we call that the leave-one-out
sum of squared errors.
And this notation, y hat minus i, what it means is
just what we said.
For each observation, the i-th observation you leave it out.
You compute the fit using all of the other data.
And then you make a prediction at that point.
So that&#39;s what this notation refers to.
And we have this really nice formula that says that this is
equal to 1/n summation.
I&#39;ll make this explicit here, i going from 1 to n.
It&#39;s the ordinary residuals, which I&#39;ll just write as yi
hat squared.
OK.
So these would be the ordinary residuals if you didn&#39;t leave
the observations out.
So that just comes from the least squares fit.
But now we have to divide them by 1 minus Hii squared.
And so this is like a magic formula.
The Hii that we have there is the diagonal element of the
hat matrix.
The hat matrix is the operator matrix that produces the least
squares fit.
This is also known as the self influence.
It&#39;s a measure of how much observation i contributes to
it&#39;s own fit.
And you notice, what happens if these values Hii vary
between 0 and 1.
And if Hii is close to 1-- in other words observation i
really contributes a lot to its own fit--
1 minus Hii is small.
And that will inflate that particular residual.
So this is like a magic formula.
It tells you that you can get your cross-validated fit by
the simple modification of the residuals from the full fit.
And that&#39;s much more efficient,
and cheaper to compute.
OK, so that&#39;s a slight detour.
Now we&#39;re going to write our own function to do that.
OK?
And that&#39;s formula 5.2 in the book.
So here we write our function.
We&#39;ll call it LOOCV, LOO-CV, takes the fit as an argument.
And it uses a function called ln.influence.
And that&#39;s a post-processor for ln fit.
And it&#39;ll extract the element h from that, which gives you
those diagonal elements Hii, right?
So we&#39;ll put that in a vector H. And then right on the fly,
we&#39;ll compute that quantity on the right hand side of our
panel over there.
First of all, the residuals of the fit give you the residuals
from the full fit.
So those are the terms in the numerator.
And then we divide by 1 minus h squared.
And the residuals of fit is a vector.
And 1 minus h is a vector.
And the divide, now, does element by element division in
that vector.
And we take the whole lot, square them, and
take the mean of that.
And so that&#39;s going to be computing this
formula over here.
OK?
So that we just build into our function.
And then end off our function.
And since that was the last quantity computed, that&#39;s will
be what&#39;s returned.
OK?
So let&#39;s see if that works.
We&#39;ll do LOOCV.
And lo and behold, very quickly it produced the 24.23
that we saw above for the first element of
the results of cv.glm.
So our function works.
OK, great.
So now we&#39;re going to use it.
And the way we&#39;re going to use it is we can fit polynomials
of different degrees to our data.
Remember what the data looked like?
Let&#39;s just go up here and plot it again.
The data looks very nonlinear.
So we plotted it again.
And now we&#39;re going to fit some polynomials of
degrees 1 up to 5.
Right?
And so we set ourselves up.
We&#39;ve got a vector for collecting the errors.
OK?
And now we create the variable degree, which
takes values 1 to 5.
And then we go into a loop for d in degree.
Fit the glm using the polynomial of that degree, so
we use the poly function, the function of
horsepower and degree.
And then we use our little function to compute the error,
the leave-one-out cross-validation error, and
put it in our error vector.
OK?
And look, it&#39;s finished already.
It&#39;s done all of them.
And if we plot this error against degree, we see that
degree 1 does pretty poorly.
Degree 2 jumps down from 24 down to just above 19.
And then higher degrees really don&#39;t make much difference.
And we might have guessed that, looking at the plot of
the data, that a quadratic would do a good job.
OK.
Well that was leave-one-out cross-validation.
Let&#39;s try 10-fold cross-validation out.
So recall with 10-fold cross-validation, you do
actually much less work.
What you do here is you divide the data up into 10 pieces,
and each 1/10 is a test set.
And the 9/10 acts as a training set.
So for 10-fall cross-validation, you don&#39;t
have to fit the model 10 times.
With leave-one-out you have to in principle fit the model n
times, where n is the number of training points.
Although we did have the shortcut for linear
regression.
The reason cv.glm doesn&#39;t use that shortcut is that it&#39;s
also set up to work on logistic regressions and other
models, and there the shortcut doesn&#39;t work.
OK.
So here we&#39;ll do 10-fold.
And we&#39;ll again set up a vector to collect our errors.
And the same thing, go through the list, we have a loop, a
list of degrees, fit our model.
And now we&#39;ll actually use a cv.glm function
to compute the errors.
And so we call cv.glm, and we tell it k is 10.
So that tells the number of folds.
OK?
And that&#39;s pretty quick, because it&#39;s only fitting the
model 10 times each time.
And now we&#39;ll include the errors on our plot.
We&#39;ll color them in red.
And so we use the function lines.
And it&#39;s not much difference.
In this case, 10-fold and leave-one-out cross-validation
pretty much told us the same story.
In general we favor 10-fold cross-validation
for computing errors.
It tends to be a more stable measure than leave-one-out
cross-validation.
And for the most time, it&#39;s cheaper to compute.