OK.
We&#39;ve learned about methods for regression and for
classification involving predictors and for making
predictions from our data.
How do we test these out?
Well, ideally, we&#39;d like to get a new sample from the
population and see how well our predictions do.
Well, we don&#39;t always have new data.
So what do we do?
And we can&#39;t use our training data just straight off,
because it&#39;s going to be a little bit optimistic.
So we&#39;re going to tell you about cross-validation.
Rob&#39;s going to tell you about cross-validation, which is a
very clever device for using the same training data to tell
you how well your prediction method works.
The other thing--
You&#39;re going to give my entire lecture?
Oh, I&#39;ll try not to, Rob.
Just in case you miss out some of the salient points.
The other thing we&#39;re going to look at is standard errors of
estimators.
Sometimes our estimators are quite complex and we&#39;d like to
know the standard error, which means what happens if we got
new samples from the population over and over
again, and we&#39;d recomputed our estimate?
And the standard error is the standard deviation of those
estimates under resampling.
Well, of course, we can&#39;t resample from the population.
We only have one sample.
Again, Rob&#39;s going to tell you about the bootstrap, which is
a very clever device for using the one, single training
sample you have to estimate things like standard
deviations.
Rob?
OK.
Well, thanks for that great introduction.
Good overview.
So we&#39;re going to talk about cross-validation and the
bootstrap as Trevor mentioned.
And these are resampling methods.
So the word resampling, our original data is a sample.
We&#39;re going to resample.
We&#39;re actually going to sample from a data set in order to
learn about the quantity of interest.
And the cross-validation and the bootstrap are both ways of
resampling from the data.
And the purpose of it is to get information, additional
information, about the fitted model.
For example, the main thing we use cross-validation for is to
get an idea of the test set error of our model.
We&#39;re going to review that concept of training error.
And we&#39;ll see, as we&#39;ve talked about before, the training
error is too optimistic.
The more we fit to the data, the lower the training error.
But the test error can get higher if we over fit.
It often will.
So cross-validation is a very important tool that we&#39;re
going to talk about in this section.
And we&#39;ll use, throughout the course, to get a good idea of
the test set error of a model.
Bootstrap, on the other hand, is most useful to get an idea
of the variability or standard deviation of an
estimate and its bias.
So we&#39;ll talk about first cross-validation validation,
and then bootstrap.
But let&#39;s, before we get into those, let&#39;s review the idea
of the concept of training error versus test error.
Remember, test error is the error that we
incur on new data.
So we fit our model to the training set.
We take our model, and then we apply it to new data that the
model hasn&#39;t seen.
The test error is actually how well we&#39;ll do on future data
the model hasn&#39;t seen.
Training error is much easier to compute.
We can do it in the same data set.
What is it?
It&#39;s the error we get applying the model to the same data
from which we trained.
And as you can imagine, train error is often
lower than test error.
The model has already seen the training set.
So it&#39;s going to fit the training set with lower error
than it was going to occur on the test set.
And the more we over fit, the harder we fit the data, the
lower the training error looks.
On the other hand, the test error can
be quite a bit higher.
So training error is not a good surrogate for test error.
And this picture is a good one to look at to summarize the
concepts here.
So what do we have here?
Well, first of all, along the horizontal axis is the model
complexity, from low to high.
For example, in a linear model, the model complexity is
the number of features, or the number of coefficients that we
fit in the model.
So low means a few number of features or coefficients or
predictors.
High means a large number.
Think about fitting a polynomial with the higher and
higher degree.
You can see how model complexity
increases with degree.
So if we move to the right, we&#39;d have a higher complexity,
a higher order of polynomial.
The predictor error is on the vertical axis.
And we have two curves here--
the training error in blue, and test error in red.
So what do we see?
Let&#39;s first look at the blue curve.
On the left, the model complexity is low.
For example, we&#39;re fitting a small number of parameters,
maybe just a single constant.
The training error is high.
Now, as we increase the model complexity, we fit more and
more features in the model or higher complexity or higher
order polynomial, the training error goes down.
And actually in this picture, it continues to go down a
consistent way.
In most cases, for most models, the more complex the
model, the training error will go down as it
does in this case.
On the other hand, the test error is the red curve.
It does not consistently go down.
It starts off high like the training error.
It comes down for a while, but then it
starts to come up again.
It has a minimum, looks like around the middle here.
But after this point, the more complex the model, the higher
the test error.
What&#39;s happened there?
Well, that is an example of over fitting, right?
On the left, we&#39;ve added complexity, some features that
actually are important for predicting the response.
So they reduce the test error.
But at that point, we seem to have fit all
the important features.
And now we&#39;re putting in things which are just noise.
The trainer error goes down as it has to, but the test error
is starting to go up.
That&#39;s over fitting.
So we don&#39;t want to over fit, because we&#39;ll increase the
test error.
The training error has not told us anything about over
fitting, because it&#39;s using the same
data to measure error.
The more parameters, the better it looks.
So it does not give us a good idea of the test error.
The test error curve, on the other hand, is minimized
around this level, at this complexity.
And beyond that is over fitting.
The ingredients of prediction error are
actually bias and variance.
So the bias is how far off on the average the
model is from the truth.
The variance is how much that the estimate
varies around its average.
When we don&#39;t fit very hard, the bias is high.
The variance is low, because there are few
parameters being fit.
As we increase the amount of complexity moving to the
right, the bias goes down because the model can adapt to
more and more subtleties in the data.
But the variance goes up, because we have more and more
parameters to estimate from the same amount of data.
So bias and variance together give us prediction error.
And there&#39;s a trade off.
They sum together to get protection error.
And the trade off is minimized, in this case,
around a model complexity in the middle here.
So bias and variance together give us test error.
We want to find the model complex given the smallest
test error, and training error does not give us a good idea
of test error.
They refer to it as the bias-variance trade off.
OK, so we can&#39;t use training error to estimate test error,
as the previous picture shows us.
So what do we do?
Well, the best solution, if we have a large test
set, we can use that.
So we typically take our model that we&#39;ve applied to fit on
the training set applied to test set.
But very often, we don&#39;t have a large test set.
We if we can&#39;t do that, what we do?
Well, there are some ways too get an idea of test error
using an adjustment to training error.
Basically, training error can be too small, as we&#39;ve see in
the previous picture.
So these methods adjust the training error by increasing
it by a factor that involves the amount of fitting that
we&#39;ve done to the data and the variance.
And these methods could the Cp statistic,
the AIC and the BIC.
We&#39;ll talk about these later on in the
course, not in this section.
Here instead, we&#39;re going to talk about cross-validation,
validation and cross-validation.
And these involve removing part of the data, the holding
it out, fitting the model to the remaining part, and then
applying the fitted model to the data that we&#39;ve held out.
And this is called validation, or
cross-validation, as we&#39;ll see.
So let&#39;s first of all talk about the validation approach.
So here, the simple idea is basically we&#39;re going to
divide the data into two parts at random, approximately of
equal size.
We&#39;ll call the first part a training set and the second
part the validation or hold-out set.
So the idea is simple.
We take the model.
We fit it on the training half.
And then we apply the fitted model to the other half, the
validation or hold-out set.
And we record the error that we get on hold-out set.
And that error, the validation set error, provides us a good
idea of the test error.
Well, at least some idea of the test error.
And the error we&#39;ll measure by mean squared error in the case
of quantitative response, or misclassification error rate
in the case of a qualitative or a discrete response
classification.
So just to make that clear, let&#39;s look at the next slide.
We have our data set here.
I&#39;ve divided it in two at random.
The blue part on the left is the training set.
And the orange part or pink part on the right is the
validation or hold-out set.
These observations, for example, 7, 22, 13 and more of
them were at random chosen to be in the training set.
Observation 91 was at random chosen to be in
the hold-out set.
We fit the model to the blue part.
And then we apply it and predict the observations in
the pink part.
And that&#39;s validation.
Or we might call that twofold validation, where we--
well, maybe I shouldn&#39;t call it twofold, because as we&#39;ll
see, we don&#39;t cross over.
This is simply a one-stage process.
We divide it in half, train on one half and predict on the
other half.
It seems a little wasteful if you&#39;ve got a very
small data set, Rob.
Yeah.
That as wasteful.
And as we&#39;ll see, cross-validation will remove
that waste and be more efficient.
But let&#39;s first see how this works in the auto data.
Recall, we&#39;re comparing the linear model to high-order
polynomials in regression.
And we have 392 observations divided up into two parts at
random, 196 in one part and 196 in the other part.
The first part being the training set, and the other
part being the validation set.
If we do this once, do a single split, and we record
the mean squared error, we get this red curve as a function
of the degree of the polynomial.
So a linear fits on the left, and quadrant is here, et
cetera, as we increase the polynomial order.
And we see the minimum seems to occur maybe around 2.
Well, it&#39;s rising a bit and coming down a bit after that.
It&#39;s pretty flat after about 2.
So it looks like a linear model.
Or actually, a quadratic model, excuse me, is
probably the best.
And after that, we&#39;re not getting much
gain, if any at all.
But look what happens when we repeat this process with more
and more splits at random into two parts.
We get a lot of variability.
The minimum does tend to occur around 2 generally.
But look at the error.
It&#39;s varying from about 16 up to 24, depending on the split.
So this is a consequence part of the fact that we divided up
into two parts.
And when you divide data in two, you get a lot of
variability depending on the split.
The training set, for example, is half as big as it was
originally.
It&#39;s interesting, Rob, that even though you get that
variability, it seems to often have this pattern where the
shape of the curves are much the same.
But the height, the level, hops around.
So that&#39;s a good point.
And it actually reminds me to say there&#39;s two things you
want to use validation for, cross-validation.
Both to pick the best size of the model-- and in this case,
the degree of polynomial.
And also to give us an idea of how good the error is, because
of the idea of the actual test error at the end of the
fitting process.
So a twofold, this breaking up into two parts, is successful
at the first thing as Trevor just mentioned.
The minimum&#39;s around 2 pretty consistently.
So that seems to be OK.
But the actual level of the curve is varying a lot.
So it wouldn&#39;t be so good at telling an idea of the error,
because we get a very wide range here in error.
So I&#39;ve said a little bit of this first point already, that
this method is highly variable because we&#39;re
splitting into two parts.
And there&#39;s lots of ways of splitting into two parts.
And because we&#39;re splitting in two, we&#39;re losing a lot of the
power of the training set.
We&#39;re throwing away half the data each time in training.
And another consequence of that that, remember, one of
our original questions was, well, what&#39;s the best size
model to pick?
Second of all, how well does that model do in
terms of test error?
Our training sets here are half as big as our original
training set.
And if we go back to this previous slide, we split the
data in half.
We actually want the test error for a
training set of size n.
We&#39;re getting an idea of test error for a
training set of size n/2.
And that&#39;s likely to be quite a bit higher than the error
for a training set of size n.
Why, Rob?
Why?
That was my question.
Well, that&#39;s because in general, the more data one,
the lower the error.
If I offer you a choice of, would you rather have 100
observations or 200 observations, you&#39;d generate
like 200 observations to train on.
Because the more data, the more information you have, and
in general, the lower your error is.
So if your training sets only half as big as your original
training set, as it is in this situation, the error that it
yields is probably be higher n the actual
error you want to get.
So as we can see, there are some drawbacks of validation.
In the next section, we&#39;ll talk more cross-validation,
which will help to remove some of these drawbacks.