Welcome back.
In the last section, we talked about validation, and we saw
some drawbacks with that method.
Now we&#39;re going to talk about K-fold cross-validation, which
will solve some of these problems.
This is actually a very important technique that we&#39;re
going to use throughout the course in various sections,
and also something we use in our work all the time.
So it&#39;s really important to understand K-fold
cross-validation.
It&#39;s used for a lot of methods.
It&#39;s an extremely flexible and powerful technique for
estimating prediction error and to get an idea of model
complexity.
So what&#39;s the idea of K-fold cross-validation?
Well, it&#39;s really in the name.
It&#39;s validation, as we&#39;ve seen, but done sort
of like K part play.
It&#39;s done K times, with each part, again, playing the role
of the validation set.
And you have the K minus 1 parts playing the role of the
training set.
Which I say here.
But let me go to the picture here, and I&#39;ll sort of point
to the pictures as I say it.
So here, you&#39;re doing 5-fold cross-validation.
As we&#39;ll talk about in more detail, the best choices for
K, the number of folds, is usually about 5 or 10.
And we&#39;ll talk about that in a few minutes, about why those
are good choices.
But let&#39;s fix here K equals 5.
So I&#39;ve taken the data set.
I&#39;ve divided at random the samples into five parts.
Again, a size about the same.
The first box looks a bit bigger, huh?
OK, well, that&#39;s my lack of drawing ability.
But anyway, it&#39;s supposed to be the same.
I was trying to squish the word validation in.
So the boxes are supposed to be about the same size and
number of observations.
But in this case, the first part&#39;s the validation set.
The other four are the training parts.
So what we&#39;re going, what cross-validation does, it
forms these five parts.
We&#39;re going to train the model on the four training parts put
together as one big block, take the third model, and then
predict on the validation part, and record the error.
And then, that&#39;s phase one.
Phase two, the validation set will be part two.
This block.
All the other four parts will be the training set.
We fit them all to the training set, and then apply
it to this validation part.
And the third stage, this is the
validation piece, et cetera.
So we have five stages.
In each stage, one part gets to play the
role validation set.
The other four parts are the training set.
We take all the prediction errors from all five parts, we
add them together, and that gives us what&#39;s called the
cross-validation error.
Now, in algebra, I&#39;ll just basically give you the details
of what I said in words.
So let the K parts of the data be C1 through CK.
So these are the observations that are in
each of the five parts.
K was 5 in our example.
And we&#39;ll try to make the number of observations about
the same in every part, versus if N&#39;s not a multiple of K or
5, we can&#39;t do that exactly, but we&#39;ll do it approximately.
So we&#39;ll let n sub K be the number of
observations in the K-th part.
So here&#39;s the cross validation error rate.
Basically, this is the mean square error we get by
applying the fit to the K minus 1 parts that don&#39;t
involve part number K. That gives us our fit yi hat for
observation i.
4/5 of the data in this case.
Right.
And then we add up the error.
This is the mean square error that we obtain now on the
validation part using that model.
So this is for the K-th part.
And now we do this for all five parts in turn.
The five acts of the play.
And then we get the cross-validation error rate.
And a special case of this is leave-one out
cross-validation, where the number of folds is the same
number of observations.
So that means in this picture, that actually would be one box
per observation.
And in leave-one out cross-validation, each
observation by itself gets to play the role of the
validation set.
The other n minus 1 are the training set.
Now, actually, leave-one out cross-validation is a nice
special case of that.
It represents a nice special case in the sense that this
cross-validation can be done without actually having to
refit the model at all.
So leave-one out cross-validation, at least for
a least squares model, or a polynomial model, the
leave-one out cross-validation has the following form.
So the yi hat is now just to fit on the full data set.
Each i is the diagonal of the hat matrix.
So have a look in the book for details.
But the hat matrix is the projection matrix that
projects y onto the column space of x to
give you the fit.
This is something that can get computed easily when you fit
your mean squares model.
So [INAUDIBLE].
We haven&#39;t emphasized it, but it&#39;s available.
It&#39;s one of the things that&#39;s available when you fit your
least squares model.
So the overall point of this is that to do a leave-one out
cross-validation for these particular models, you don&#39;t
actually have to leave anything out.
You can do the fit on the overall data set, and then
extract the information you need to get the
cross-validation sum of squares.
And it&#39;s interesting.
Because the hi tells you how much influence an observation
has on its own fact.
It&#39;s a number between 0 and 1.
And so as an observation, it&#39;s very
influential on its own fit.
You can see it punishes the residual, because it divides
by a number that&#39;s small, and it inflates the residual.
So, it sort of does the right thing there.
OK.
Although leave-one out cross-validation does have
this nice computation formula.
For most of the methods we talk about in this book and
most statistical learning methods, it&#39;s better to choose
K to be 5 or 10, rather than have a leave-one out
cross-validation.
And why is that?
Well, one problem with the leave-one out cross-validation
is that each of the training sets look very much like the
other ones.
Right?
They only differ by one observation.
So when you take the average--
cross-validation is you take the average of
errors over the n folds.
And in leave-one out cross-validation, the n folds
look very similar to each other, because the training
sets are almost the same.
They only differ by one observation.
So as a result, that average has a high variance, because
the ingredients are highly correlated.
So that&#39;s the main reason why it&#39;s thought, and we also
agree, that a better choice for K in
cross-validation is 5 or 10.
On the other hand, the leave-one out cross-validation
is actually trying to estimate the error rate for the
training sample of almost the same size as what you have.
So it&#39;s got low bias.
But as Rob said, high variance.
So actually, picking K is also a bias variance trade-off for
prediction error.
And as Rob said, K equals 5 or 10 tend to be a good choice.
So the next slide I&#39;ve got a comparison of a leave-one out
cross-validation and 10-fold CV for the auto data.
Remember, before we started 2-fold validation, we started
with just validation into two parts, we&#39;ve got a lot of
variability between when we change the sample, the half
sample, that we took.
Now let&#39;s see what happens with leave-one out
cross-validation.
We get a curve that&#39;s, again, got the minimum around the
same place, as we saw before.
And it&#39;s pretty flat after that.
A 10-fold cross-validation, now again, it&#39;s also showing
the minimum around 2, but there&#39;s not the--
what we&#39;re seeing here is the 10-fold cross-validation as we
take different partitions into 10 parts of the data.
And we see there&#39;s not much variability.
They&#39;re pretty consistent.
In contrast to when you divide it into two parts, we got much
more variability.
And those get averaged as well, those
curves on the right.
Right.
Exactly.
So they&#39;re averaged together, which we saw here.
They&#39;re averaged together to give us the overall estimate
of cross-validation.
Which the overall cross-validation curve will
look very much like this, with its minimum around 2.
OK.
This is figure 5.6 from the textbook.
And this is the simulated example, which is from figure
2.9 of the book.
Just recall that this is smoothing splines in three
different situations.
In this case, the true error curve is the blue curve.
And again, there&#39;s three different
functions that we&#39;re examining.
It says mean square error simulated data.
The true error curve.
How did we get that, Rob?
Well, it&#39;s simulated diagram.
So we just--
Oh.
So we can get a very big test set and
estimate the error exactly.
Leave-one out cross-validation is the black broken line, and
the orange curve is 10-fold cross-validation.
So what do we see?
Well here, we see that the test error curve is a little
higher than the 10-fold and leave-one out
cross-validation.
The minimum&#39;s fairly close, but the minimum of
cross-validation is around 8, whereas the true curve minimum
is around 6.
In this case, the two cross-validation methods are
doing a better job of approximating
the test error curve.
Well, the minimum&#39;s fairly close.
Not exactly on the mark.
Black curve is minimized around 6.
And the true error curve is minimize around--
it&#39;s maybe 3.
Although those error curves are fairly flat.
So there&#39;s obviously a high variance in where the
minimum should be.
Right.
And it doesn&#39;t really matter, really.
That&#39;s right.
It&#39;s not going to matter much if you choose a model with a
flexibility of 2, or maybe even 10 here, because the
error is pretty flat in that region.
And then in the third example, the two cross-validation
curves do quite a good job of approximating the test error
curve, and the minimum&#39;s around 10 in each case.
So actually, I said this already,
but I&#39;ll say it again.
One issue with cross-validation is that since
the training set is not as big as the original training set,
the essence of prediction will be biased up a little bit,
because you have less data that you&#39;re working with.
And I also said, and I&#39;ll say again, that leave-one out
cross-validation has smaller bias in this sense, because
the training set is almost the same in size as
the original set.
But on the other hand, it&#39;s got higher variance, because
the train sets that it&#39;s using are almost the same as the
original set.
They only differ by one observation.
So K equals 5 or 10-fold is a good compromise for this
bias-variance trade-off.
OK.
So we talked cross-validation for a quantitative response,
and we used mean square error.
The classification problems, that is exactly the same.
The only thing that changes is the measure of error.
Of course, no longer square error, but a
misclassification error.
Otherwise, cross-validation process is exactly the same.
Divide the data up into K parts.
We train on K minus 1 parts.
We record the error on the K-th part, and we add things
up together to get the overall cross-validation error.
It looks like a weighted average formula, right?
With nk over n?
Do you want to explain that?
Each of the folds might not be exactly the same size.
So, we actually compute a weight which is the relative
size of the fold, and then use a weighted average.
Right.
And if we are lucky that the n divides by k exactly, then
that weight will just be 1/k.
Right.
1/k.
One other thing to add is that since this cross-validation
error is just an average, the standard error of that average
also gives us a standard error of the
cross-validation estimate.
So we take the error rates from each of the folds.
Their average is the cross-validation error rate.
The standard error is the standard deviation of the
cross-validation estimate.
So here&#39;s the formula for that.
So this is a useful quantity.
When we would draw a CV curve, we should always put a
standard air band around the curve [INAUDIBLE]
the variability.
So in these previous pictures, we should&#39;ve had a standard
error band around the curves to give us an idea of how
variable they are.
I say here is a useful estimate, but not quite valid.
Why is that?
Dr. [INAUDIBLE]?
Well, I wonder why.
Well, the thing is, we&#39;re computing the standard error
if these were independent observations.
But they&#39;re not strictly independent.
Error sub k overlaps with, Error sub j because they share
some training samples.
So there&#39;s some correlation between them.
But we use this anyway.
We use it, and it&#39;s actually quite a good estimate.
And people have shown this mathematically.
An important point being that is that the cross-validation
separates the training part of the data from
the validation part.
When we talk about bootstrap method in the next part of
this section, we&#39;ll see that that&#39;s not the case, and
that&#39;s going to cause a problem.
So cross-validation explicitly separates the training set
from the validation set in order to get a good idea of
test error.
OK.
So this again, I&#39;ll reemphasize that
cross-validation is a very important technique to
understand, both for quantitative responses and
classification.